AND GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYBODY. WELCOME TO THE MAY 12TH 2026
REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN PRESIDENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER NOT PRESENT SUPERVISOR
MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN PRESIDENT
MANDOLIN PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR PRESENT
SUPERVISOR SADR SADR PRESENT SUPERVISOR CHERYL SHERRELL
PRESENT SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR
WONG WONG PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT YOU HAVE A QUORUM.
>> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL
HOMELAND OF THE DRAMATIST SALONI, WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL
INHABITANTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO PENINSULA AS THE
INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW MATERIALS WE HAVE NEVER CEDED
LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE
CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO
RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL TERRITORY AS GUESTS WE
RECOGNIZE THAT WE BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR
TRADITIONAL HOMELAND. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE
RAMAKRISHNA ONLY COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND THE REPUBLIC WHICH STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD
INDIVISIBLE WITH. >> ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD I
WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV TODAY ESPECIALLY
KALEENA MENDOZA. THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR
MEETINGS AND MAKE THE TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE
PUBLIC ONLINE. >> MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR
2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER. YES THE 2 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER IS
THE MONTHLY APPEARANCE OF THE HONORABLE MAYOR DANIEL LURIE
HERE TODAY. THERE ARE NO QUESTIONS
SUBMITTED FROM MEMBERS OF THE BOARD REPRESENTING DISTRICTS
ONE, TWO, 3 OR 4. BUT THE MAYOR MAY ADDRESS THE
BOARD FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES. >> WELCOME, MR. MAYOR.
AS OUR CLERK INDICATED, WE HAVE NO TOPIC SUBMITTED FOR YOU
TODAY SO WE WELCOME YOU TO SPEAK FOR UP TO FIVE MINUTES.
>> THANK YOU. GOOD AFTERNOON.
BOARD PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
OVER THE LAST 16 MONTHS WE'VE TALKED MANY TIMES ABOUT THE
WORK THAT WE'VE DONE TOGETHER TO GET PEOPLE OFF THE STREET
AND INTO SHELTER AND TREATMENT AND ONTO A PATH TO STABILITY.
IT'S CLEAR THAT SAN FRANCISCANS FEEL LIKE OUR CITY IS MOVING
IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION AND TODAY I WAS EXCITED TO
ANNOUNCE ANOTHER IMPORTANT MILESTONE.
ACCORDING TO THE PRELIMINARY READ 2026 POINT IN TIME COUNT
UNSHELTERED HOMELESSNESS IN SAN FRANCISCO IS NOW AT THE LOWEST
LEVELS IN 15 YEARS. SINCE 2024, UNSHELTERED
HOMELESSNESS IS DOWN 22%. THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE IN TENTS
IS DOWN 85% AND OVERALL HOMELESSNESS IS DOWN WITH
NEARLY 1000 FEWER PEOPLE SLEEPING ON OUR STREETS
COMPARED TO 2024. THOSE NUMBERS REPRESENT PEOPLE
COMING INDOORS, GETTING HELP AND GETTING ON THE PATH TO
STABILITY. WHEN I TOOK OFFICE WE COMMITTED
TO TRANSFORMING HOW SAN FRANCISCO RESPONDS TO
HOMELESSNESS, ADDICTION AND BEHAVIORAL HEALTH.
WE FOCUSED ON ACCOUNTABILITY, COORDINATION AND GETTING PEOPLE
OFF THE STREET FASTER. WITH THIS BOARD'S SUPPORT
AND LEADERSHIP WE PASSED THE FENTANYL STATE OF EMERGENCY
ORDINANCE AND LAUNCHED OUR BREAKING THE CYCLE PLAN.
WE INTEGRATED STREET OUTREACH TO BETTER CONNECT PEOPLE TO
CARE. WE ENDED THE POLICY OF HANDING
OUT FENTANYL SMOKING SUPPLIES WITHOUT PATHWAYS TO TREATMENT.
LAST YEAR ALONGSIDE SUPERVISORS CHERYL AND SOUDER, WE OPENED
822 GEARY, A 24 SEVEN STABILIZATION CENTER.
AND JUST LAST WEEK WE OPENED THE RESET CENTER AND SUPERVISOR
DORSEY'S DISTRICT MAKING CLEAR THAT OPEN AIR DRUG USE IS NOT
ACCEPTABLE ON OUR STREETS ACROSS SANFORD CISCO WE ADDED
MORE THAN 600 SHELTER AND TREATMENT BEDS BECAUSE
RECOVERY REQUIRES MORE THAN JUST A PLACE TO SLEEP AT NIGHT.
WE'VE ALSO MADE MAJOR PROGRESS HELPING FAMILIES LIVING IN RVS.
THANKS TO THE PARTNERSHIP OF MY LEGISLATIVE CO-SPONSOR
SUPERVISOR MELGAR TODAY WE'VE HELPED 132 FAMILIES MOVE FROM
RVS INTO SHELTER OR HOUSING. AND WE'VE EXPANDED JOURNEY HOME
RECONNECTING MORE PEOPLE WITH FAMILY AND SUPPORT SYSTEMS.
IN THE LAST THREE MONTHS THAN IN ANY THREE MONTH PERIOD SINCE
THE PROGRAM STARTED AT EVERY STEP FROM OUTREACH TO SHELTER
TO PERMANENT HOUSING, WE ARE REFORMING THE SYSTEM TO DELIVER
BETTER OUTCOMES AND BREAK THE CYCLES OF HOMELESSNESS
AND ADDICTION. BUT WE ALL KNOW OUR WORK IS
FAR, FAR FROM DONE. >> FAMILY HOMELESSNESS
INCREASED SINCE 2024 REFLECTING TRENDS WE'RE SEEING ACROSS
CALIFORNIA AND THE COUNTRY. WE ARE CONTINUING TO INVEST
IN PREVENTION, SHELTER AND HOUSING SUPPORT FOR
FAMILIES BECAUSE NO CHILD SHOULD EXPERIENCE HOMELESSNESS
IN SAN FRANCISCO. AND BEYOND THE NUMBERS.
I KNOW YOU SEE IT. I SEE IT EVERY SINGLE DAY.
AND RESIDENTS ALSO STILL SEE IT AND WANT CLEANER AND SAFER
STREETS. I DO TOO AND I'M AS MOTIVATED
AS EVER. I WANT TO THANK ALL OF YOU WHO
HAVE MADE WHO HAVE MADE THIS PROGRESS POSSIBLE HERE AT THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, OUR CITY DEPARTMENTS, OUR NONPROFIT
PARTNERS, OUR FIRST RESPONDERS, OUR OUTREACH WORKERS ON THE
FRONT LINES EVERY SINGLE DAY. I WANT TO THANK YOU BOARD
PRESIDENT MANAGEMENT FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP AND FOR ALL OF YOU
HERE AT THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR YOUR
PARTNERSHIP. WE'RE ON THE RIGHT TRACK BUT WE
HAVE SO MUCH MORE WORK TO DO AND WE NEED TO DO IT TOGETHER.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO DOING THAT WITH ALL OF YOU.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU, MR. MAYOR.
>> CONGRATULATIONS AGAIN ON THE GREAT PITCH COUNT NUMBERS
AND OTHER SUCCESSES. AND WE'LL SEE YOU NEXT MONTH.
>> THANK YOU, SIR. GOOD TO SEE YOU.
THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT.
THIS MATTER HAS BEEN BEEN DISCUSSED AND IS NOW FILED.
AND WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, I THINK WE GO BACK TO
COMMUNICATIONS. >> YES.
THANK YOU. THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
WELCOMES YOU ALL TO ATTEND THIS MEETING IN PERSON HERE IN THE
BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER. IT'S ROOM 250 IN CITY HALL ON
THE SECOND FLOOR. WHEN YOU'RE NOT ABLE TO BE
HERE, THE PROCEEDING IS BEING AIRED LIVE ON S.F. GOVEE TV'S
CHANNEL TWO X. OR YOU CAN VIEW THE LIVESTREAM
AT WW W DOT S.F. GOV TV.ORG. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT
PUBLIC COMMENT TIM WRITING YOU CAN DO SO BY EITHER SENDING AN
EMAIL TO B O S AT S.F. GOV DAWG OR SEND A LETTER TO THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON B
GOOD LIT PLACE CITY HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA
94102 IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A
FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT
OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, CONTACT THE CLERK'S
OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY CALLING
(415) 554-5184. AND FINALLY, AS STATED
PREVIOUSLY PURSUANT TO A MEMO DATED APRIL 7TH, 2026 FROM
SUPERVISOR JACKIE FIELDER, A MOTION RENEWED EACH WEEK
BETWEEN APRIL 7TH AND JUNE 30TH, 2026 WOULD BE AN ORDER
TODAY, MR. PRESIDENT, TO EXCUSE SUPERVISOR FIELDER FROM TODAY'S
MEETING. THANK YOU.
MEMBERS MR. PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
CAN WE HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE SUPERVISOR FIELDER FROM TODAY'S
MEETING? MOTION MADE BY CHANCE SECONDED
BY WALTON. AND I THINK COLLEAGUES, WE CAN
TAKE THAT WITHOUT OBJECTION. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS EXCUSED. >> LET'S GO TO OUR MEETING
MINUTES. YES, MEETING MINUTES.
THE APPROVAL OF THE APRIL 7TH 2026 BOARD MEETING MINUTES.
>> ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, CAN I HAVE A MOTION TO APPROVE THESE
MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN SECONDED BY CHERYL.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED. SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN HIGH MANDEL MANDOLIN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT
AS PRESENTED. AND WITH THAT MADAM CLERK I
THINK WE GO TO OUR UNFINISHED BUSINESS.
PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER ONE. >> ITEM ONE THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE 1.5 MILLION FROM THE GENERAL
RESERVE TO THE PUBLIC DEFENDER TO SUPPORT THE PROJECTED
INCREASES IN SALARY AND FRINGE BENEFIT COSTS IN FISCAL YEAR
2025 THROUGH 2026. THIS ORDINANCE REQUIRES A TWO
THIRDS APPROVAL OR EIGHT VOTES OF ALL MEMBERS PURSUANT TO
CHARTER SECTION 9.113 SUBSIDY. >> PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM
ONE. >> SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDELL MAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SAUDER SUTTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER TWO ITEM TWO THIS IS AN ORDINANCE
TO AMEND DIVISION ONE OF THE TRANSPORTATION CODE TO
AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF TRANSPORTATION TO APPROVE
TEMPORARY STREET USE PERMITS AND UNDER CERTAIN CIRCUMSTANCES
TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR
OF TRANSPORTATION TO APPROVE CERTAIN STREET CLOSURES
PROPOSED BY COMMUNITY BENEFITS DISTRICTS UNDER THE DOWNTOWN
ENTERTAINMENT EVENT ACTIVATION PROGRAM AND TO AFFIRM THE
SECRET DETERMINATION. >> LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER THREE ITEM THREE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND
THE HOUSING CODE TO REVISE QUALIFICATIONS AND DEADLINES
FOR CONDUCTING STRUCTURAL MAINTENANCE INSPECTIONS AND TO
AFFIRM THE SEQUENCE DETERMINATION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER FOUR. >> ITEM FOUR.
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO CONDITIONALLY ACCEPT AN OFFER
OF DEDICATION AND QUITCLAIM DEED FOR REAL PROPERTY FROM THE
OFFICE OF COMMUNITY INVESTMENT AND INFRASTRUCTURE FOR A
SEGMENT OF EAST CLEMENTINA STREET BETWEEN BEAL AND MAIN
STREETS. TO CONDITIONALLY ACCEPT THE
SEGMENT OF EAST CLEMENTINA STREET FOR MAINTENANCE
AND LIABILITY TO DELEGATE TO THE PUBLIC WORKS DIRECTOR THE
AUTHORITY TO ACCEPT THE STREET SEGMENT FOR CITY MAINTENANCE
AND LIABILITY PURPOSES TO ESTABLISH THE OFFICIAL PUBLIC
RIGHT OF WAY WIDTHS AND STREET GRADES AND OTHER RELATED
ACTIONS TO CONDITIONALLY ACCEPT OFFERS OF IMPROVEMENTS FROM
TRANSBAY TO FAMILY LP AND TRANSMIT TO SENIOR LP
COLLECTIVELY KNOWN AS TRANSBAY TO FOR PUBLIC IMPROVEMENTS ON
BOTH FOLSOM AND MAIN STREETS AND TO APPROVE FOLSOM STREET
PUBLIC SIDEWALK EASEMENTS FROM TRANSBAY TO AND TO WAIVE THE
APPLICATION OF ORDINANCE NUMBER 1061 ENTITLED REGULATING THE
WIDTH OF SIDEWALKS TO ALLOW ESTABLISHMENT EXPANSION
AND REDUCTION OF OFFICIAL SIDEWALK WIDTHS THROUGH
ADMINISTRATIVE ACTION ASSOCIATED WITH THE
IMPROVEMENTS AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL OUT
A NUMBER FIVE ITEM FIVE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO AUTHORIZE THE PUBLIC UTILITIES
COMMISSION TO PURCHASE UTILITY INFRASTRUCTURE FROM CUSTOMERS
THAT THE PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION WOULD OTHERWISE BE
REQUIRED TO INSTALL SUBJECT TO SPECIFIED CONDITIONS SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER SIX ITEM SIX THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO STATE THAT IT IS CITY POLICY TO
EXPAND THE AVAILABILITY OF SITE BASED PCH OR PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING THAT PROHIBITS ONSITE ILLICIT DRUG
USE AMONG RESIDENTS. THE DRUG FREE PASSAGE TO MEET
THE DEMAND OF PEOPLE EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS WHO
PREFER SUCH A RESIDENTIAL OPTION TO BAR THE CITY FROM
FUNDING NEWS SITE BASED PCH FOR PEOPLE EXPERIENCING
HOMELESSNESS THAT PROHIBITS EVICTIONS ON THE BASIS OF DRUG
USE ALONE. THAT'S THE DRUG TOLERANT PCH
EXCEPT WHERE OPERATION OF THE HOUSING AS DRUG FREE PASSAGE
WOULD CONFLICT WITH STANDARDS IMPOSED BY LAW OR BY A
CONDITION OF OTHER FUNDING OR IF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HAS
WAIVED THE FUNDING PROHIBITION BASED ON SPECIFIC FINDINGS
AND TO REQUIRE THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS AND SUPPORT OF
HOUSING TO SURVEY RESIDENTS OF THE SITE BASED PCH TO ADDRESS
TO ASSESS THEIR INTEREST IN LIVING IN EITHER DRUG
TOLERANT PCH OR DRUG FREE PCH AND TO REPORT ON THE SURVEY
FINDINGS AND SAGE STRATEGIES TO MEET PCH RESIDENTS DEMANDS
CHAIR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
COLLEAGUES ALTHOUGH I BELIEVE WE WOULD HAVE THE VOTES TO PASS
THIS LEGISLATION IN ITS CURRENT FORM TODAY I WANTED TO REPORT
THAT WE HAD A VERY PRODUCTIVE MEETING WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO
AND MARIN MEDICAL SOCIETY LAST FRIDAY AFTER A LOT OF BACK
AND FORTH BETWEEN US OVER THE LAST MONTH WE HAVE REACHED AN
AGREEMENT AT LEAST IN PRINCIPLE ON CLARIFYING LANGUAGE FOR
EVICTION PROTECTIONS THAT I AM VERY COMFORTABLE WITH.
LIKEWISE, MANY ADVOCATES FROM THE RECOVERY COMMUNITY I'VE
SPOKEN WITH ARE COMFORTABLE WITH IT.
IT'S MY UNDERSTANDING THAT S.F. MAYOR IS ALSO COMFORTABLE WITH
IT AND IS PREPARED TO WITHDRAW ITS OPPOSITION TO THE
LEGISLATION. ALL THAT BEING SAID, THE FINAL
FINAL WORDSMITHING IS STILL BEING DONE WITH OUR CITY
ATTORNEY, THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND HHS H.
HOWEVER, IN ANY CIRCUMSTANCE THE AMENDMENT IS GOING TO BE
SUBSTANTIVE MEANING THE ITEM WILL NEED TO GO BACK TO
COMMITTEE FOR A REHEARING AND AMENDMENT GIVEN THAT WE'RE
NOT FACING ANY IMMINENT ACQUISITIONS OF PERMANENT
SUPPORTIVE HOUSING THAT REQUIRES RUSHING THIS ITEM
AND IN CONSIDERATION OF THE MANY CONVERSATIONS I HAVE HAD
INCLUDING WITH COLLEAGUES ABOUT THEIR PREFERENCE TO FORGE THE
BROADEST POSSIBLE CONSENSUS ON DRUG FREE SUPPORTIVE HOUSING IF
POSSIBLE I'D LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO SEND THIS ITEM BACK
TO COMMITTEE AT THIS TIME AND WE SHOULD SEE YOU BACK HERE
IN A MONTH. >> THANK YOU CHAIR DORSI THANK
YOU FOR YOUR WORK ON THAT. THERE'S A MOTION TO SEND THIS
ITEM BACK TO COMMITTEE. IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY
CHAN COLLEAGUES? I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT
WITHOUT OBJECTION. WITHOUT OBJECTION.
THE MOTION IS APPROVED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER SEVEN. >> ITEM SEVEN THIS IS AN
ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY 1.2 MILLION OF
AMBULANCE BILLINGS AND APPROXIMATELY 426,000 OF
FIRE OVERTIME SERVICE FEES REVENUES IN THE FIRE DEPARTMENT
TO APPROPRIATE PERMANENT SALARIES OF 500,000 IN THE
DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT PERMANENT SALARIES
OF APPROXIMATELY 6 MILLION AND DEPENDENT COVERAGE OF
APPROXIMATELY 990,000 IN THE FIRE DEPARTMENT AND PERMANENT
SALARIES OF 1.25 MILLION IN THE PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION
AND APPROXIMATELY 500,000 TO OVERTIME IN THE DEPARTMENT OF
EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT APPROXIMATELY 8.6 MILLION
IN OVERTIME IN THE FIRE DEPARTMENT AND 1.25 MILLION
IN OVERTIME IN THE PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION TO SUPPORT
THE DEPARTMENT'S PROJECTED INCREASES IN OVERTIME AS
REQUIRED PER ADMINISTRATIVE CODE.
SECTION 3.17 THIS ORDINANCE REQUIRES A TWO THIRDS VOTE OF
ALL MEMBERS FOR APPROVAL OF THE FIRE DEPARTMENT'S APPROPRIATION
OF 7.9 MILLION. COLLEAGUES, I BELIEVE WE CAN
TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO
APPROPRIATE APPROXIMATELY A 2.5 MILLION OF OPEN SPACE
ACQUISITION FUNDING AND APPROXIMATELY 2.5 MILLION
IN THE RECREATION AND PARKS DEPARTMENT FOR A LOAN TO THE
SAN FRANCISCO ZOOLOGICAL SOCIETY IN FISCAL YEAR 2025
THROUGH 2026. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
SO MUCH PRESIDENT AND CLERK I JUST WANT TO START BY SAYING
THANK YOU SO MUCH TO THE BUDGET AND FINANCE COMMITTEE
AND SPECIFICALLY TO THE CHAIR OF THE COMMITTEE AT SUPERVISOR
CHAN FOR THEIR VERY THOUGHTFUL DELIBERATIONS AT LAST WEEK
AND FOR THE WORK AHEAD OF NEXT WEDNESDAY'S MEETING REGARDING
THE LOAN AGREEMENT THAT GOES WITH THIS.
I ALSO WANT TO PROFUSELY THANK THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE
ANALYST FOR ALL OF THE NUMBER CRUNCHING AND MOST IMPORTANTLY
FOR FINISHING THE AUDIT THAT I REQUESTED A WHILE BACK.
IT TOOK US A WHILE TO GET HERE BUT I CAN REPORT THAT WE ARE
THERE. THE AUDIT SHOWED THAT THERE HAD
BEEN SOME THINGS THAT THE FORMER ZOO LEADERSHIP HAD DONE
THAT MUST BE RECTIFIED IN TERMS OF INSTITUTING NEW POLICIES
AND PROCEDURES AND DOING THE WORK THAT WE NEED TO DO TO GET
THIS VERY IMPORTANT INSTITUTION BACK ON TRACK TO SERVE THE
RESIDENTS AND VISITORS OF SAN FRANCISCO FOR GENERATIONS TO
COME. THE PROPOSED ORDINANCE IT
BEFORE YOU WOULD BE APPROPRIATE 2.5 MILLION FOR THE OPEN SPACE
ACQUISITION RESERVE AND APPROPRIATE THOSE FUNDS TO
PARK RACK AND TO BE USED AS AN INITIAL LOAD DISBURSEMENT TO
THE SAN FRANCISCO ZOO IN THE YEAR 2526.
THE FORMAL LOAN AGREEMENT IS STILL BEFORE THE BUDGET
AND FINANCE COMMITTEE. IT WILL BE HEARD AT THIS COMING
WEEK AND IT IS EXPECTED TO BE EXECUTED FOR FISCAL YEAR 2526.
THE REMAINING LOAN AMOUNTS WILL BE DISBURSED AND THE SAN
FRANCISCO ZOO IS THEN OBLIGATED TO MEET SOME STRICT MILESTONES
INCLUDING COMPLETION OF A FINANCIAL SUSTAINABILITY PLAN
AND THE STRATEGIC PLAN. >> SO I WANT TO THANK AT RAK
PARK THE MAYOR'S BUDGET OFFICE. GREG WAGNER THANK YOU FOR ALL
OF THE SUPPORT AND ADVICE. AND I ALSO WANT TO THANK THE
COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE AT DAN GONGCHA AND LINDEN BARRY FOR
ALL OF THEIR WORK. AND OF COURSE NICK MINARD,
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE SUPPORT AND WORK.
THANK YOU. COLLEAGUES I, I RESPECTFULLY
REQUEST YOUR SUPPORT. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEMS NINE
THROUGH 11 TOGETHER ITEMS NINE THROUGH 11 APPROVE VARIOUS
GRANT AGREEMENTS BETWEEN THE CITY AND FOR ITEM NINE THIS IS
WITH THE TENDERLOIN HOUSING CLINIC INC AND THE DEPARTMENT
OF HOMELESSNESS IN SUPPORT OF HOUSING FOR THE ABIGAYLE
HOUSING LADDER PROGRAM TO EXTEND THE TERM BY 36 MONTHS
FOR A TOTAL TERM JANUARY 1ST, 2021 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029
AND TO INCREASE THE AGREEMENT AMOUNT BY 5.5 MILLION FOR A NEW
TOTAL OF 15.5 MILLION FOR ITEM TEN.
THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE GRANT
AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE TENDERLOIN HOUSING CLINIC
AND THE DEPARTMENT OF HOMELESSNESS IN SUPPORT OF
HOUSING FOR SUPPORT SERVICES, PROPERTY MANAGEMENT
AND MASTERLY STEWARDSHIP AT THE GARLAND HOTEL TO EXTEND THE
TERM BY 36 MONTHS FOR A TOTAL TERM APRIL FIRST, 2022 THROUGH
JUNE 30TH OF 2029 AND TO INCREASE THE AGREEMENT AMOUNT
BY 7.3 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL OF 17.3 MILLION FOR ITEM 11.
THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE GRANT
AGREEMENT BETWEEN COMMUNITY FORWARD S.F. AND THE DEPARTMENT
OF HOMELESSNESS IN SUPPORT OF HOUSING AGAIN FOR SUPPORT
SERVICES, PROPERTY MANAGEMENT AND MASTER LEASE STEWARDSHIP AT
THE CORONADO HOTEL TO EXTEND THE TERM BY 12 MONTHS FOR A
TOTAL TERM OF JANUARY 1ST 2021 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027 AND TO
INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY 2.1 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT
OF 11.9 MILLION FOR ITEM 12. THIS RESOLUTION APPROVES THE
SECOND AMENDMENT TO THE CONTRACT AGREEMENT BETWEEN FIVE
KEYS SCHOOLS AND PROGRAMS AND THE DEPARTMENT OF HOME
ASSISTANCE BOARD OF HOUSING FOR THE PROVISION OF THIS SEMI
CONGREGATE SHELTER TO EXTEND THE TERM 24 MONTHS FOR A NEW
TOTAL TERM DECEMBER 15TH 2022 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 AND TO
INCREASE THE AGREEMENT AMOUNT BY 12.2 MILLION FOR ITEM 13.
THIS RESOLUTION RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZES THE OFFICE OF
ECONOMIC AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT TO ACCEPT
AND EXPEND A $5 MILLION GRANT FROM THE CALIFORNIA NATURAL
RESOURCES AGENCY FOR THE PRESERVATION AND REVITALIZATION
OF THE CASTRO THEATER, A HISTORIC LGBTQ VENUE TO HELP
ADVANCE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT IN THE CASTRO NEIGHBORHOOD
DURING THE GRANT PERIOD OF APRIL 1ST, 2026 THROUGH
DECEMBER 31ST, 2027 AND YOU WANTED ME TO GO ALL THE WAY TO
ITEM 15. MR. PRESIDENT?
NO. OH, OKAY.
JUST I THINK WE CAN STOP AT 13. >> OKAY.
SO ON FOR ITEMS NINE THROUGH 13 I THINK WE CAN TAKE THESE SAME
HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE
ADOPTED AND THEN PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 14 ITEM 14 THIS
RESOLUTION APPROVES AND AUTHORIZES THE DIRECTOR OF
PROPERTY ON BEHALF OF THE DRUG MARKET AGENCY COORDINATION
CENTER TO EXECUTE A LEASE WITH A 33 EIGHTH STREET LLC, A
CALIFORNIA LIMITED LIABILITY COMPANY FOR A PORTION OF THE
REAL PROPERTY LOCATED AT 33 EIGHTH STREET FOR A TERM OF TEN
YEARS AND FOUR MONTHS AT AN INITIAL ANNUAL BASE RENT OF
APPROXIMATELY 448,000 WITH 3% ANNUAL INCREASES.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN
AND COLLEAGUES BECAUSE THIS AGREEMENT HAPPENS TO BE WITH MY
OWN LANDLORD I HAVE BEEN ADVISED BY COUNSEL THAT I
SHOULD RECUSE MYSELF FROM THIS VOTE RIGHT.
>> WELL THEN YOU MAY LEAVE COLLEAGUES.
MAY I MAY I HAVE A MOTION TO EXCUSE SUPERVISOR DORSEY FROM
THIS VOTE MOVED BY CHERYL SECONDED BY CHAN
AND COLLEAGUES. >> CAN WE TAKE THAT WITHOUT
OBJECTION? WITHOUT OBJECTION.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY IS EXCUSED AND THEN MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE ITEM ON ITEM 14.
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I MANDELL MIDNIGHT A MIDDLEMAN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR MY
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE NINE EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEMS 15 AND 16 TOGETHER ITEMS
15 AND 16 ART TO RESOLUTIONS THAT RETROACTIVELY AUTHORIZE
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ACCEPT AND EXPAND EXPEND TO
GRANTS FOR ITEM 15 THIS IS $1 MILLION GRANT FROM THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE SERVICES FOR PARTICIPATION
IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE
SERVICES GRANT FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO CHINESE HOSPITAL TO
SUPPORT THE NEW ONCOLOGY CLINIC AND CHEMOTHERAPY CENTER AT THE
CHINESE HOSPITAL JULY 1ST, 2025 TO DECEMBER 31ST 2026 FOR ITEM
16. THIS RESOLUTION RETROACTIVELY
AUTHORIZES THE ACCEPTANCE AND EXPENDITURE OF GRANT FUNDS
FROM JULY FIRST 2025 RETROACTIVELY APPROVING THE
GRANT AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY ACTING BY AND THROUGH THE
DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH AND THE CALIFORNIA STATE WATER
RESOURCES CONTROL BOARD FOR THE PURPOSE OF COLLECTING BAY
AND OCEAN SHORELINE WATER SAMPLES FOR PATHOGEN ANALYSIS
FOR A TERM OF THREE YEARS JULY FIRST 2025 NOW THROUGH JUNE
30TH 2028 FOR A TOTAL OF 87,000 SUPERVISOR WONG LIKE TO BE
ADDED AS A CO-SPONSOR OF HER 15.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL AND ITEM 15
AND 16 AND ITEMS 15 AND 16 SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISE HER MY MY GOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDELL THEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
I SUPERVISOR SAUDER SAUDER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 17 ITEM 17 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT THE COMPTROLLER AND THE DEPUTY COMPTROLLER AS
AGENTS TO ACT ON BEHALF OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR ALL MATTERS PERTAINING TO STATE AND FEDERAL
DISASTER AND EMERGENCY ASSISTANCE FUNDING AND TO
PROVIDE THE ASSISTANCE AND AGREEMENTS REQUIRED BY THE
GOVERNOR'S OFFICE OF EMERGENCY SERVICES.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED. THAT BRINGS US TO 230.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL OUR 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDER? >> YES.
THE SPECIAL ORDER AT 230 IS THE RECOGNITION OF COMMENDATIONS
FOR MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO. >> ALL RIGHT THEN WE WILL BEGIN
WITH DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WONG HEY, I'M IN HONOR OF
JEWISH AMERICAN HERITAGE MONTH AS WELL AS A BELATED TRANS
HISTORY WEEK. WE ARE PROUD TO RECOGNIZE RABBI
MARTIN ROLLINS FINE FOR HIS EXTRAORDINARY LEADERSHIP
SERVICE, CREATIVITY AND COMMITMENT TO BUILDING A
MORE INCLUSIVE AND COMPASSIONATE COMMUNITY.
MARTIN IS A BAY AREA RABBI, EDUCATOR, FILMMAKER, PARENT
ADVOCATE AND COMMUNITY LEADER WHOSE WORK HAS TOUCHED FAITH
COMMUNITIES, CIVIC INSTITUTIONS, POLITICAL
ORGANIZATIONS AND CULTURAL SPACES ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO
AND BEYOND. HE HAS DEDICATED HIMSELF TO
CREATING A WORLD WHERE TRANSGENDER PEOPLE, LGBTQ
PEOPLE, JEWISH COMMUNITIES AND FAMILIES OF ALL KINDS CAN
LIVE OPENLY, AUTHENTICALLY AND OF DIGNITY.
AS A RABBI AND EDUCATOR, MARTIN HAS HELPED ADVANCE INCLUSIVE
JEWISH LIFE, CREATIVE RITUAL AND SPIRITUAL CARE FOR PEOPLE
OF MANY BACKGROUNDS THROUGH HIS LEADERSHIP WITHIN HIS
CONGREGATION AND IN BROADER JEWISH COMMUNITY SPACES.
HE HAS HELPED BUILD PLACES WHERE PEOPLE CAN BRING THEIR
FULL SELVES INTO RELIGIOUS LIFE .
HIS WRITINGS AND LITURGY HAVE ALSO CONTRIBUTED TO JEWISH
SCHOLARSHIP AND PRACTICE, INCLUDING WORK ON PRIDE,
MOURNING AND TRANSGENDER JEWISH EXPERIENCE.
>> MARTIN HAS ALSO MADE A LASTING IMPACT THROUGH CIVIC
AND POLITICAL LEADERSHIP. HE SERVED AS PRESIDENT OF THE
WALLENBERG JEWISH DEMOCRATIC CLUB AND CURRENTLY SERVES AS
CO-CHAIR OF THE ALICE B TOKLAS LGBTQ DEMOCRATIC CLUB
STRENGTHENING COALITION BUILDING AND ELEVATING LGBTQ
AND JEWISH VOICES IN PUBLIC LIFE.
HE HAS ALSO SERVED AS AN ELECTED EXECUTIVE BOARD MEMBER
AND ASSEMBLY DISTRICT DELEGATE IN DEMOCRATIC PARTY LEADERSHIP,
FURTHER REFLECTING HIS DEEP COMMITMENT TO REPRESENTATION,
PARTICIPATION AND PUBLIC SERVICE.
AT UCSF WHERE HE HAS WORKED FOR MORE THAN TWO DECADES, MARTIN
HAS SUPPORTED EDUCATION COLLABORATION AND TRANSGENDER
HEALTH ADVOCACY INCLUDING WORK CONNECTED TO THE UCSF CENTER OF
EXCELLENCE FOR TRANSGENDER HEALTH AND THE NATIONAL
TRANSGENDER HEALTH SUMMIT. AS A FILMMAKER AND COMMUNITY
BUILDER, MARTIN HAS HELPED EXPAND VISIBILITY THROUGH
STORYTELLING, CO-CREATED THE FIRST SAN FRANCISCO TRANS
MARCHES FOUNDED BY ICONIC FILM FESTIVAL AND LIFTED UP TRANS
AND BI PLUS VOICES THROUGH FILM ARTS, EDUCATION AND ADVOCACY.
WHAT MAKES MARTIN'S EXAMPLE SO POWERFUL IS THAT HIS VISIBILITY
HAS ALWAYS BEEN TIED TO SERVICE.
HE HAS USED HIS VOICE NOT ONLY TO SPEAK FOR HIMSELF BUT TO
OPEN DOORS FOR OTHERS. TODAY WE THINK RABBI MARTIN
ROLLINS FAMED FOR HIS LEADERSHIP GENEROSITY, COURAGE
AND ENDURING COMMITMENT TO DIGNITY, BELONGING AND JUSTICE
. OH WOW.
AND I WOULD JUST LIKE TO ADD MY CONGRATULATIONS.
>> HAVING KNOWN RABBI ROLLINS FINE FOR LIKE PROBABLY 20 YEARS
AT THIS POINT IT'S IMPRESSIVE TO SEE SENIOR CONTRIBUTIONS
OVER THAT TIME. >> WELL, THANK YOU VERY MUCH
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND AND ALAN, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
I, I, I FEEL LIKE IT'S MY DUTY AS A AS A PERSON OF FAITH TO
SAY THAT, YOU KNOW, WE'RE ALL LOVED.
THIS IS A BIG DEAL. PEOPLE SHOULD BE AUTHENTIC
AND BE WHO THEY ARE. AND FOR ALL THE TRANS KIDS OUT
THERE THIS IS FOR YOU BECAUSE I COULDN'T DO WHAT I DO UNLESS I
WAS THINKING ABOUT EVERYTHING WAY FORWARD BECAUSE I'M NOT
DOING THIS FOR MYSELF. I'M DOING THIS FOR EVERYBODY
WHO'S COMING AFTER ME AND AND THIS WANT TO SAY THAT YOU KNOW
,IF YOU'RE A TRANS KID OUT THERE IN THE WORLD AND YOU NEED
TO HEAR THIS YOU ARE LOVED. WE WE WILL EMBRACE YOU.
WE LOVE YOU. AND THIS IS AN IMPORTANT THING
THAT EVERYBODY NEEDS TO FIGURE OUT.
WE NEED TO REALLY EMBRACE OUR TRANS CHILDREN AND HELP THEM
AND GOING FORWARD. AND I, I JUST I'M REALLY
BLESSED TO BE HERE AND I AM REALLY WONDERFUL WONDERFULLY.
>> I THIS IS VERY TOUCHING. SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH ALL OF
YOU FOR FOR DOING THIS TODAY AND AND YOU KNOW THE ALPHABET
THE INTERNATIONAL DAY OF AGAINST HOMOPHOBIA BISEXUAL
BIPHOBIA AND UH AND AND AND TRANSPHOBIA ON MAY 17TH
THIS YEAR. AND IT'S ACTUALLY REALLY
IMPORTANT BECAUSE IT'S YOU KNOW HONESTLY DEMOCRACY THAT'S PART
OF THE THING IS YOU KNOW THIS IS THIS IS AN IMPORTANT PART OF
OF DEMOCRACY IS EVERYBODY BEING ACCEPTED.
SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH
. >> DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR
WALTON. THANK YOU, PRESIDENT, MADAM
AND COLLEAGUES. >> TODAY I WANT TO TAKE A
MOMENT TO RECOGNIZE A GROUP OF PEOPLE WHO ARE OFTEN THE VERY
FIRST FACES WHEN WE SEE WHEN WE WALK INTO THIS BUILDING.
>> EACH DAY OUR SHERIFF'S CADETS AND AS THEY COME FORWARD
BEFORE THE MEETINGS BEGIN, BEFORE THE CONVERSATION HAS
HAPPENED, BEFORE THE WORK OF GOVERNMENT GETS UNDERWAY.
YOU ARE HERE. YOU WELCOME STAFF MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC. COMMUNITY LEADERS AND VISITORS
WITH PROFESSIONALISM, PATIENCE AND RESPECT IN MANY WAYS.
YOU HELP SET THE TONE FOR THE ENTIRE BUILDING.
WHAT STANDS OUT THE MOST IS NOT JUST THE WORK YOU DO BUT HOW
YOU DO IT. OVER TIME YOU BUILD REALLY
RELATIONSHIPS WITH THE PEOPLE WHO COME THROUGH THESE DOORS
EVERY SINGLE DAY. YOU LEARN NAMES, EXCHANGE
GREETINGS, OFFER KINDNESS AND CREATE A SENSE OF
FAMILIARITY AND COMFORT THAT OFTEN GOES UNNOTICED.
>> BUT MATTERS DEEPLY. >> PUBLIC SERVICE IS NOT ONLY
ABOUT BIG MOMENTS. IT IS ALSO ABOUT CONSISTENCY,
RELIABILITY AND SHOWING UP EVERY SINGLE DAY WITH
INTEGRITY. EACH OF YOU REPRESENTS THAT
SPIRIT. >> YOUR PRESENCE HELPS MAKE
CITY HALL FEEL SAFER, MORE WELCOMING AND MORE CONNECTED TO
THE PEOPLE WE SERVE. YOU KEEP US SAFE.
AND WE ALL KNOW THAT WHEN WE WALK IN THIS BUILDING WE ARE
SECURE. >> I DON'T WANT A DAY TO GO BY
WITHOUT ALL OF YOU KNOWING HOW MUCH YOU ARE APPRECIATED.
>> ON BEHALF OF MY OFFICE. THIS BOARD I WANT TO SINCERELY
THANK YOU FOR ALL OF YOUR SERVICE.
THANK YOU FOR ALWAYS STARTING OUR DAY OFF ON THE RIGHT FOOT.
WE APPRECIATE YOU. WE VALUE YOU.
AND TODAY WE ARE PROUD TO RECOGNIZE ALL THAT YOU DO.
POINTING PEOPLE IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION KEEPING OUT DANGER.
WELCOMING COMMUNITY. REMAINING PROFESSIONAL.
GREETING THE PUBLIC WITH WARMTH .
MAINTAINING PATIENCE. WATCHING OUR BACKS.
>> ALWAYS PRESENT. AND FOR THIS WE ARE GRATEFUL.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH. >> THE SUPERVISOR WALTER.
MR. PRESIDENT. BOARD MEMBERS.
I JUST WANTED TO TAKE A MOMENT. PRESIDENT MADAM.
>> WE HAVE A LONG LINE OF SUPERVISORS.
THE SHERIFF CAN GO AHEAD FIRST IF YOU'D LIKE.
I APOLOGIZE. YEAH, GO AHEAD.
>> GO FOR IT. I JUST WANTED TO SAY IT IS A
VERY CHALLENGING JOB. SUPERVISOR WALTON.
APPRECIATE THE WORDS. THERE HAVE BEEN MANY, MANY
TIMES WHERE YOUR WORK HAS GONE UNRECOGNIZED.
AND I ONLY HAVE THE CAPACITY TO THANK ONE OF THEM ONE AT A TIME
WITH OUR EMPLOYEE OF THE MONTH. THIS RECOGNITION TODAY BY THE
BOARD IS A REFLECTION OF HOW THE COMMUNITY FEELS ABOUT YOU.
AND IT'S A REFLECTION ABOUT ALL OF US IN THE SHERIFF'S OFFICE
FAMILY FEEL ABOUT YOU. YOU REPRESENT THE VERY BEST OF
OUR COMMUNITY. THE HEART AND SOUL BEHIND YOUR
PATCHES AND BEHIND YOUR BADGES REALLY ARE A REFLECTION OF SAN
FRANCISCO. SO THANK YOU FOR KEEPING
EVERYONE SAFE AND WELCOME. AND PLEASE CONTINUE TO DO THE
GREAT WORK THAT YOU DO. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH
AND THANK YOU BOARD FOR RECOGNIZING.
>> ALL RIGHT. >> NOW WE HAVE THE LONG LINE OF
SUPERVISORS. >> SUPERVISOR JEN, THANK YOU
FOR PRESSING. THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR WALTON
FOR RECOGNIZING OUR CITY HALL CADETS.
>> I AM. YOU ALL CAN SEE BUT WE'RE NOT
WE'RE NOT DONE. >> WE WANT TO APPRECIATE YOU.
>> I AM GREATLY APPRECIATIVE OF YOUR HARD WORK.
>> YOU KEEP ARE FOR US AND THE PUBLIC SAFE FROM HARM.
>> FOR MANY VISITORS YOU ARE THE FIRST FACE THAT THEY SEE
WHEN THEY WALK THROUGH THIS DOORS AND YOU ARE THE
AMBASSADOR OF CITY HALL. >> YOUR ROLE AS MULTIFACETED
AND DEMANDING AND PROVIDING VITAL INFORMATION TO THE
PUBLIC. WHETHER YOU ARE HELPING A
RESIDENT AND FINDING THE RIGHT OFFICE OR PROVIDING FIRST AID
IN CRITICAL MOMENTS. YOUR PRESENCE ENSURES THAT OUR
SEATS OF GOVERNMENT REMAINS A SAFE AND WELCOMING SPACE FOR
ALL SAN FRANCISCANS AND VISITORS.
>> I AM AND WE ARE VERY PROUD OF YOUR DEDICATIONS THAT YOU
SHOW EVERY DAY AND OFTEN WORKING LONG HOURS AND HOLIDAYS
TO KEEP US SAFE. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD, CONGRATULATIONS.
AND I THINK JUST ONE OF THE THINK AND TWO POINTS TO ECHO MY
COLLEAGUES. ONE YOU REALLY MAKE CITY HALL
INVITING FOR NOT JUST THE PEOPLE WHO ARE VISITING BUT FOR
THE PEOPLE WHO WORK HERE DAY IN, DAY OUT BORDERS.
>> YOU WILL ASK ME ABOUT MY WIFE AS IF I GOT MARRIED
YESTERDAY. IT'S BEEN NINE MONTHS BUT YOU
STILL ASKED ME ABOUT IT. BUT YOU ALSO TELL ME ABOUT YOUR
DAUGHTER AND THE VACATIONS YOU TAKE AND IT MAKES US FEEL AT
HOME AS WE WALK IN. AND THEN SECOND, I REALLY
APPRECIATE EVERY ONE OF YOU HOLD US ACCOUNTABLE AND DON'T
LET US GO THROUGH THE SECURITY GATES WITH ANY EXCEPTIONS.
AND IT REALLY JUST SHOWS THAT YOU REALLY ARE KEEPING US SAFE
AND HOLDING EVERYONE ACCOUNTABLE.
>> BE AN ELECTED OFFICIAL OR A PERSON WHO'S VISITING CITY HALL
. SO THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU DO FOR
KEEPING US SAFE KEEPING US WELCOME AND MAKING US FEEL LIKE
WE BELONG IN OUR AND IN OUR MUTUAL OFFICE SPACE.
>> SO THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR JAN THANK YOU.
>> OF COURSE. ON A GOOD DAY WE ALWAYS
APPRECIATE YOU. BUT WE ALSO DO KNOW GIVEN THE
HISTORY OF THIS BUILDING THAT YOU DO PUT YOUR LIFE AT RISK
EVERY DAY YOU DE-ESCALATE ALL THE INTENSE SITUATION EITHER AT
THE DOOR OF THE CITY HALL OR AT THE DOORS OF OUR OFFICES.
WE APPRECIATE YOU. WE ALSO APPRECIATE YOU AT LEAST
FOR ME I WOULD SAY AS A BUDGET COMMITTEE CHAIR.
WE APPRECIATE YOU DURING THE MONTH OF BUDGET WHERE EVERYBODY
IS COMING THROUGH AND THOSE ABSOLUTELY THOSE LONG NIGHTS
THAT YOU HAVE TO STAY WITH US AND STAY PUT WITH US BUT ALSO
EVERY SINGLE MEETING THAT WE HAVE IN THIS BOARD CHAMBER OR
THAT WE HAVE OUR COMMITTEE HEARING WHEN THERE'S PUBLIC
COMMENTS, YOU'RE ALWAYS THERE TO MAKE SURE THAT SHOULD THERE
BE ATTENTION WE KNOW THAT YOU'RE ACTUALLY RIGHT THERE YOU
WILL STEP IN AND TO AGAIN THE SKILLS THAT YOU DISPLAY AND ON
DISPLAY TO ESCALATE WE APPRECIATE YOU.
AND NOT TO MENTION EVEN LAST YEAR BUDGET.
WE HAVE OUR FELLOW LABOR SIBLINGS COMING IN HERE
AND GETTING ARRESTED. AGAIN, YOU DEMONSTRATE IT
PROFESSIONALISM. WE CANNOT THANK YOU ENOUGH.
YOU KNOW WE'RE GOING TO DO THE BEST WE CAN TO TRY TO MAKE YOUR
LIFE JUST A LITTLE BIT EASIER. >> BUT BECAUSE OF YOU I THINK
THAT MANY PEOPLE FEEL ACTUALLY FREE AND SAVED TO BE ABLE TO
SPEAK THEIR MINDS IN THIS CHAMBER AND THAT IS BECAUSE THE
ROAD THAT YOU HAVE PLACED SO FORTH THAT WE APPRECIATE YOU
AND GRATEFUL. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISORS. >> CHERYL, THANK YOU FOR YOUR
KINDNESS, FOR YOUR PATIENCE FOR PRETENDING LIKE PEOPLE WHO
PRETEND LIKE THEY'VE NEVER SEEN A METAL DETECTOR BEFORE ARE
RIDICULOUS. BUT THE SMILE THAT WE SEE ON
BOTH SIDES OF YOUR FACES MOST OF THE TIME ARE REALLY
APPRECIATE IT. I WON'T PRETEND LIKE I KNOW
YOUR NAME SO I'M SORRY BUT FOR THOSE OF YOU WHO I HAVE GOTTEN
TO KNOW ON A PERSONAL LEVEL I REALLY APPRECIATE BEING ABLE TO
WALK INTO A PLACE THAT FEELS A LITTLE MORE LIKE HOME AND A
LITTLE LESS LIKE WORK AND THAT STARTS WITH YOU ALL YOU WORK
REALLY HARD BUT YOU ARE REALLY KIND, THOUGHTFUL, GENEROUS
PEOPLE AND FOR THAT I WANT TO THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN YOU KNOW MY
FIRST DAY ON THE JOB IN THIS BUILDING WAS ALMOST 24 YEARS
AGO AND IN THAT TIME I HAVE ALWAYS APPRECIATED THE
CONSUMMATE PROFESSIONALISM AND FRIENDLINESS OF OUR DEPUTY
SHERIFFS. OVER THE YEARS I HAVE HAD
THINGS WHERE I'VE HAD TO COME HERE AND GET 3:00 IN THE
MORNING BECAUSE I LEFT MY LAPTOP OR ZERO JUST SOME OF THE
THINGS THAT I HAVE HAD TO DO AND SHERIFFS HAVE ALWAYS BEEN
THERE AND IT JUST MEANS THE WORLD TO ME THAT YOU KNOW, TO
BE GREETED BY FRIENDLY FACES AND I JUST KNOWING THAT YOU
KEEP US SAFE YOU ARE SO APPRECIATED AND I'M GRATEFUL
THAT YOU'RE BEING CELEBRATED TODAY.
>> THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR, THANK YOU
SO MUCH. I WILL JUST ADD TO WHAT MY
COLLEAGUES HAVE SAID BECAUSE I APPRECIATE EVERY SINGLE ONE OF
YOU ASIDE FROM KEEPING US SAFE AND ENFORCING ORDER WHEN PEOPLE
COME INTO THE BUILDING I KNOW THAT WHEN YOU'RE HAVING A BAD
DAY I SEE YOU AND YOU SEE ME TOO.
THANK YOU FOR HOLDING THE DOOR WHEN I'M STRUGGLING WITH MY
BIKE BAGS BUT ALSO THANK YOU FOR THE COUNTLESS LONG HOURS
THAT YOU PUT IN ON EVENINGS AND WEEKENDS.
I KNOW THAT SOMETIMES SOME OF YOU WORK DOUBLE SHIFTS.
YOU'RE HERE TOO LATE AT NIGHT WHEN YOU STARTED, YOU KNOW,
EARLY IN THE MORNING TO KEEP US SAFE YOU'VE OPENED DOORS FOR ME
ON WEEKENDS AND EVENINGS AND FOR MY STAFF WHEN WE'VE
LOCKED OURSELVES OUT OF THE OFFICE LATE AT NIGHT ALL OF
THESE THINGS WE SEE YOU. WE APPRECIATE YOU AND THANK YOU
FOR YOUR KIND WORDS AND GREETINGS EVERY MORNING IT
MAKES ALL THE DIFFERENCE. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
SUPERVISOR SAUDER THANK YOU PRESIDENT.
I WILL ECHO ECHO EVERYTHING THAT HAS ALREADY BEEN SAID.
I JUST A FEW THINGS TO ADD YOU KNOW STARTING THIS ROLE NOW
1516 MONTHS AGO FROM DAY ONE I FELT VERY EMBRACED AND VERY
LOVED VERY CARED FOR BY ALL OF YOU AND I'M HAPPY TO HAVE ALL
THESE FOLKS IN THE WELL HERE AS MY COLLEAGUES AND I CONSIDER
YOU TO BE MY COLLEAGUES AS WELL .
YOU'RE ALWAYS LOOKING OUT FOR US.
YOU'RE ALWAYS ASKING ABOUT OUR DAYS AND AND LOOKING AFTER US.
>> I YOU KNOW, WEEKENDS, EVENINGS I COME INTO THE
BUILDING AND I THINK THERE'S GOING TO BE NO ONE HERE AND ONE
OF YOU IS HERE AND I ALWAYS FEEL A LITTLE BIT SURPRISED BUT
VERY HAPPY THAT YOU'RE ALWAYS WATCHING GUARD AND I I JUST
WANT TO SAY ON THE RECORD I ALWAYS FEEL A LITTLE GUILTY BUT
I'M BRINGING IN MY COFFEE AND MY PASTRIES, MY LUNCH AND I
DON'T HAVE ANY FOR YOU AND I WAS I FEEL GUILTY SO I'LL BRING
YOU SOME AT SOME POINT. >> THANK YOU FOR ALWAYS LOOKING
AFTER US AND PROTECTING US. >> I WILL JUST I HAVE THOUGHTS
. >> I WILL JUST SHAMANS READY TO
GIVE YOU YOUR SIGNIFICANCE. I'LL JUST THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON FOR DOING THIS.
>> I THINK I THOUGHT I WAS SPECIAL.
>> I THOUGHT I HAD THIS UNIQUE RELATIONSHIP WITH EACH OF YOU
BUT NOW I REALIZE THAT YOU ARE KIND AND HELPFUL AND AND START
EVERYBODY'S DAY OFF. >> RIGHT?
AND SO JUST FOR ALL THAT YOU DO TO KEEP CITY HALL RUNNING
AND ENGAGING WITH THE PUBLIC AND BEING KIND TO US
AND SOMETIMES YOU KNOW, I'M COMING IN WITH ALL MY STUFF
FALLING ALL OVER THE PLACE AND YOU DON'T MAKE TOO MUCH FUN
OF ME. I JUST WANT TO ECHO MY
COLLEAGUES BECAUSE WE ALL DO APPRECIATE YOU VERY, VERY MUCH
SO THANK YOU, CADETS. THANKS.
THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT, COLLEAGUES, WE'RE
GOING TO SHIFT AROUND THE ORDER THAT YOU ALL HAVE RECEIVED A
LITTLE BIT TODAY. I APOLOGIZE BUT I BELIEVE WE
MAY HAVE A CONSUL GENERAL IN THE IN THE ROOM AND SO WE'LL
GO TO SUPERVISOR DISTRICT ONE. >> SUPERVISOR CHANT THANK YOU,
PRESIDENT MA'AM ROMAN AND THANK YOU COLLEAGUES FOR ALLOWING ME
TO BE ABLE TO FIRST I REALLY WANT TO RESPECTFULLY INVITE OUR
HONORABLE LIM YONG TAE CONSUL GENERAL OF THE REPUBLIC OF
KOREA, DR. JONATHAN KIM, THE PRESIDENTS OF THE SAN FRANCISCO
AND BAY AREA KOREA CENTER AND LEE YONG KWANG, A
REPRESENTATIVE FROM THE CHANG CULTURAL FOUNDATION WHO'S ALSO
AN AWARD WINNING VOCALIST WHO HAS EARNED COUNTLESS TITLES
FROM INTERNATIONAL COMPETITION FROM GERMANY AND ITALY TO
TURKEY AND SEOUL. COLLEAGUES IN THE CELEBRATION
OF API HERITAGE MONTH I WOULD LIKE TO RECOGNIZE THE SAN
FRANCISCO AND BAY AREA KOREA CENTER FOR THE CONTRIBUTE
AND TO SAN FRANCISCO CULTURAL AND ECONOMIC DIVERSITY KOREA
CENTER LOCATED AT 745 BUCHANAN STREETS WAS ESTABLISHED TO
PROMOTE THE CULTURAL, SOCIAL AND EDUCATIONAL AND ECONOMIC
PROGRESS OF KOREAN AMERICANS AND TO STRENGTHEN MUTUAL
UNDERSTANDING AND PARTNERSHIP WITH COMMUNITIES ACROSS THE
CITY AND THROUGHOUT THE BAY AREA.
AS PART OF THE MAYS AAPI HERITAGE MONTH CELEBRATION
KOREA CENTER HAS INVITED TWO TOURING OF THE INCHEON CULTURAL
FOUNDATION AND PERFORMANCE GROUP TO SAN FRANCISCO SHOWCASE
KOREAN AMERICAN HERITAGE THROUGH DANCE AND PERFORMING
ARTS. SO ONE OF THE PIECES THAT THE
DANCE GROUP IS FEATURING IS A MASTERPIECE OF KOREAN FOLK
DANCE TRADITION ONLY PERFORMED DURING THE HARVEST MOON
FESTIVAL. IT IS A CELEBRATION OF LIFE,
LONGEVITY AND THE BOND BETWEEN HUMANITY AND NATURE A PERFECT
PIECE TO BRING THE COMMUNITY TOGETHER.
>> THIS MONTH AND I JUST REALLY WANTED TO THANK THEM FOR BEING
HERE. BUT I ALSO WANT TO TAKE THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO SAY THAT, YOU KNOW, FOR FOR A LONG TIME THAT
IN SAN FRANCISCO THE AAPI COMMUNITY SHOULD ALL TO REALLY
WORK IN SOLIDARITY TO RECOGNIZE EACH OTHER.
I KNOW THAT OFTEN TIME WE RECOGNIZE CHINESE-AMERICAN
COMMUNITY BUT I THINK THAT THIS IS A MOMENT TO ALSO RECOGNIZE
AND EXTEND THAT WELCOMING INCLUS ACTIVITY TO OUR
KOREAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY AND RECOGNIZE THAT THEY THEIR
POSITIONS AND THEIR CONTRIBUTION ARE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. I KNOW THAT MANY
KOREAN-AMERICANS IN SAN FRANCISCO BOTH BE IT SMALL
BUSINESS COMMUNITY LEADERS AND ARTISTS REALLY HAVE DONE
WOW INCLUDING OUR ASIAN ART MUSEUM DIRECTOR DIRECTOR LEE
ALS DR. LEE ALSO HAS CONTRIBUTED SO MUCH TO THE ART
AND CULTURE AND RICHNESS OF SAN FRANCISCO AND BAY AREA.
AND SO FOR THAT I WANT TO WELCOME THEM AND THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR BEING HERE. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISOR AS
I CONSIDER HERE THE I ESPECIALLY THANKFUL FOR THE
CORNEA CHEN FOR GIVING US IN WITH THIS THE PRECIOUS
OPPORTUNITY TO INTRODUCE OUR THE CULTURAL TROUPE THE KOREAN
COMMUNITY IS VERY THE WELCOME TO BY THE BORDER WITH
SUPERVISORS. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
SO I'M VERY HONORED TO RECEIVE RECOGNITION ON BEHALF OF THE
KOREAN COMMUNITY. >> THANK YOU.
WELL, GOOD AFTERNOON EVERYONE. MY NAME IS JONATHAN KIM ON
BEHALF OF THE JIN DOG AND COUNTS KIM FOUNDATION
AND THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA KOREA CENTER.
IT'S MY GREAT HONOR TO SUPPORT THE 5000 YEAR OLD KOREAN
CULTURE HISTORY DRAMA, MUSIC, FOOD, COSMETIC SURGERY,
COSMETIC MAKEUP, TAEKWONDO AND HANGUL THE KOREAN LANGUAGE
. >> NOW I WOULD LIKE TO TAKE A
MOMENT TO EXPRESS MY HEARTFELT CREDIT TO SUPERVISOR CONNIE
CHEN FOR HER EXCEPTIONAL LEADERSHIP.
UNWAVERING DEDICATION IS FIGHTING VISION FOR THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
AS YOU WILL SEE WE HAVE A 24 KOREAN TRADITIONAL DANCERS TO
SUPPORT THE KOREAN HERITAGE TONIGHT AT ORACLE PARK AND TO
CELEBRATE API HERITAGE MONTH IF YOU ARE INTERESTED IN SEEING
KOREAN CULTURE ARE FREE PLEASE VISIT THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY
AREA CAREER CENTER LOCATED AT 745 BUCHANAN STREET ONLY 10 TO
15 MIN A WALK FROM THE CITY HALL AND THE ASIAN ART MUSEUM
TO SAN FRANCISCO BAY AREA CAREER CENTER IS A MARKET
CULTURAL HUB THAT OFFERS AUDIENCE A WINDOW INTO KOREAN
MUSIC OUR FILM HISTORY AND LANGUAGE AND THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR YOUR ATTENTION. >> PLEASE ENJOY TODAY'S EVENT.
THANK YOU. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS LEE. I'M THE CEO OF THE ASIAN
CULTURAL FOUNDATION, REPRESENTATIVE OF A CITY
IN KOREA. THERE MAY BE SOME MORE IN SIZE
BUT IS A GIANT IN SPIRIT AND CULTURE.
TODAY I STAND BENEATH THIS MAGNIFICENT DOME OF A SAN
FRANCISCO CITY HALL WITH OUR TOTAL PLAY TROUPE.
WE COME TO YOU UNDER THE TITLE EACH YEAR ARE INSPIRED BY THE
HISTORICAL PEACE AND VOICE OF KOREA.
>> HAVING CROSSED THE VAST PACIFIC.
WE ARE DEEPLY MOVED TO SHARE OUR MESSAGE OF HARMONY IN THIS
BEAUTIFUL CITY BY THE BAY. >> LADIES MANDELMAN, WE LIVE
IN A WORLD THAT IS WEARY. HOWEVER, I STAND HERE TODAY
WITH A FIRM CONVICTION. POLITICS CANNOT SOLVE AND WHAT
ECONOMICS CANNOT FILL CAN BE HEALED BY THE POWER OF CULTURE
AND THE ARTS. >> LAST WEEK OUR ECON TEAM HAD
A WONDERFUL PERFORMANCE RIGHT HERE AT THE CITY HALL PLAZA
AND ORACLE PARK. >> MUSIC IS THE MOST BEAUTIFUL
LANGUAGE. THE TRADITIONS BORDER TOURIST
TRADITION THESE ARE MESSAGES SENT UP PAST TO GUIDE OUR
FUTURE. OURS IS SIMPLE.
FOR THE BRIEF MOMENTS OUR MELODIES LINGER IN YOUR EARS.
WE HOPE YOU CAN FORGET THE WORRIES OF THE WORLD AND FIND
TRUE HAPPINESS. EACH 1ST MAY APPEAR AS A SMALL
DOT ON A MAP BUT IT HOVERS A GIANT SIZE HOLE FOR GLOBAL
PEACE. >> PLEASE REMEMBER THE DENSITY
OF EACH ONE KOREA AND THAT EACH CULTURE FOUNDATION WILL ALWAYS
BE CHEERING FOR YOU AND FOR PEACE THROUGHOUT THE WORLD.
ACTUALLY BEFORE I CONCLUDE I HAVE A SPECIAL SURPRISE FOR ALL
OF YOU. LONG BEFORE I LAID THIS
FOUNDATION I SPENT THE MANY TIMES PRAISE FOR OPERA SINGER
AT THE THEATER BASEL IN SWITZERLAND.
TO HONOR THIS BEAUTIFUL ENCOUNTER IN SAN FRANCISCO, I
WOULD LIKE TO RAISE MY VOICE FOR YOU.
MANY OF YOU MIGHT RECOGNIZE THIS MELODY THROUGH US.
BUT TODAY I WANT TO SHARE THE ORIGINAL ROOTS OF THIS SONG.
THE TRUE SOUL OF KOREA ARIRANG. >> THANK YOU.
>> OH, DID ALL MY OH DID ALL 0000 OH OH OH DID ON IT OR NO
I'M ALL GONE. >> 000 NO
THIS DEAR LIFE OH ONCE WAS ALL IN OH OH OH VERSE NINE OH OH OH
THANK YOU THANK YOU FOR ASKING I SUPPOSE OH I ALWAYS LOVED
KINSHIP. >> HMM HMM.
>> MY FUTURE BE TO
OKAY. AND NOW WE WILL GO BACK TO OUR
REGULARLY SCHEDULED PROGRAMING BACK TO DISTRICT FIVE
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD THANK YOU, PRESIDENT COLLEAGUES TODAY
DURING POLICE WEEK IT IS MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE MEMBERS OF
THE TENDERLOIN STATION PATROL. WE HAVE THEM TO THE PODIUM
PLEASE. >> WE'RE HONORING THE
TENDERLOIN STATION PATROL WHOSE WORK REFLECTS A DEEP COMMITMENT
TO PUBLIC SAFETY, NEIGHBORHOOD SERVICE AND THE DAY TO DAY
WELL-BEING OF DISTRICT FIVE RESIDENTS.
THIS INCLUDES OFFICER NESTOR LINARES, OFFICER SIR EDWIN
ANAYA AND SAM SAMUEL BERENSON FOR THEIR SERVICE TO THE
TENDERLOIN COMMUNITY AND FOR THE WORK THEY DO EVERY SINGLE
DAY TO KEEP OUR NEIGHBORHOODS SAFE, ACCESSIBLE AND CARED FOR.
>> AS MANY KNOW, THE TENDERLOIN IS ONE OF THE MOST DYNAMIC BUT
CHALLENGING NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
IT IS HOME TO WORKING FAMILIES SENIORS, IMMIGRANTS, SMALL
BUSINESSES, STUDENTS AND LONGTIME RESIDENTS WHO
DESERVE CLEAN, SAFE AND WELCOMING PUBLIC SPACES.
RESIDENTS REQUIRE NOT JUST CONSISTENCY BUT ALSO VISIBLE
TIES TO THE COMMUNITY. THE TENDERLOIN STATION PATROL
DELIVERS THIS. THEY SHOW A LEVEL OF DEDICATION
IN THE FORM OF KNOWING THE NAMES OF THE RESIDENTS THEY
SERVE AND PUTTING IN THE TIME BY BEGINNING THEIR WORK IN THE
EARLY HOURS OF EVERY MORNING. OFTEN BUT FOR MOST OF THE CITY
IS EVEN AWAKE. >> THEY HELP ENSURE SIDEWALKS
ARE CLEAR, PUBLIC SPACES ARE MAINTAINED AND RESIDENTS CAN
SAFELY NAVIGATE THEIR NEIGHBORHOOD.
THESE OFFICERS HAVE DEDICATED MUCH OF THEIR CAREERS TO
EXACTLY THAT MISSION. >> OFFICER NESTOR LINARES
IMMIGRATED TO SAN FRANCISCO FROM EL SALVADOR AS A CHILD
AFTER HIS FAMILY FLED THE CIVIL WAR.
HE JOINED THE MARINE CORPS RESERVES AT JUST 17 YEARS OLD
AND LATER ENTERED THE S.F. PD IN 2006.
FOR THE PAST 17 YEARS HE HAS BEEN AT TENDERLOIN STATION
AND HAS SERVED AS A FIELD TRAINING OFFICER AND COMMUNITY
SERVICES OFFICER FOCUSING ON HOMELESSNESS, OUTREACH, PUBLIC
SAFETY AND NEIGHBORHOOD QUALITY OF LIFE.
>> HIS LEADERSHIP, COMPASSION AND RESILIENCE EMBODY THE VERY
BEST OF PUBLIC SERVICE. OFFICER EDWIN ANIYA IS A SAN
FRANCISCO NATIVE AND PROUD GRADUATE OF LINCOLN HIGH WHO
HAS SERVED AT TENDERLOIN STATION SINCE 27.
>> OVER THE YEARS HE HAS WORKED EXTENSIVELY AS A HOMELESS
OUTREACH OFFICER HELPING CONNECT VULNERABLE RESIDENTS TO
NAVIGATION SERVICES, SOBERING CENTERS AND CRITICAL SUPPORT
SYSTEMS. >> HIS WORK EARNED HIM A
MAYORAL COMMENDATION IN 2017 AND IN 2019 HE RECEIVED A LIFE
SAVING AWARD FOR HIS ACTIONS DURING A CRITICAL INCIDENT
IN SAN BRONSON HAS BROUGHT A COLLABORATIVE AND INNOVATIVE
APPROACH TO PUBLIC SAFETY WORK ACROSS MULTIPLE CITY
DEPARTMENTS FROM ADDRESSING ILLEGAL STREET VENDING AT
MISSION STATION TO HELPING COORDINATE DEMAK OPERATIONS
IN THE TENDERLOIN. SAM HAS WORKED CLOSELY WITH
CITY AGENCIES, PUBLIC WORKS TEAMS AND COMMUNITY PARTNERS TO
IMPROVE SIDEWALK ACCESSIBILITY AND NEIGHBORHOOD CONDITIONS.
HIS WORK ON INITIATIVES LIKE OPERATION A-FRAME DEMONSTRATE
HOW COORDINATION ACROSS AGENCIES CAN DELIVER DELIVER
MEANINGFUL IMPROVEMENTS ON THE GROUND.
>> AS CAPTAIN MATT SULLIVAN HAS SAID ABOUT HIS TEAM, THEY ARE
PART OF THE REASON SIDEWALKS ARE OPEN EVERY MORNING FOR
PEOPLE WHO GO TO WORK AND TO SCHOOL AND IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
OF 3500 CHILDREN OFTEN THE SONS AND DAUGHTERS OF IMMIGRANTS
AND REFUGEES. YOU THREE AS PART OF YOUR TEAM
HAVE GIVEN THEM HOPE FOR A BETTER LIFE.
CAPTAIN SULLIVAN ALSO NOTES THAT THEIR CONSISTENT
COMMITMENT AND PROFESSIONALISM MAKE A MEANINGFUL DIFFERENCE
IN THE COMMUNITY EACH DAY. BECAUSE YOU AT THE TENDERLOIN
STATION PATROL REPRESENT A MODEL OF PUBLIC SERVICE ROOTED
IN CONSISTENCY, COLLABORATION AND CARE FOR COMMUNITY.
YOUR WORK BEGINS BEFORE MOST OF US EVEN WAKE UP.
AND WHILE MUCH OF WHAT HAPPENS OUTSIDE THE SPOTLIGHT,
RESIDENTS SEE THE IMPACT OF WHAT YOU DO EVERY SINGLE DAY
I'LL SHARE AN ANECDOTE AS I WAS WALKING HOME FROM WORK THE
OTHER DAY, CAPTAIN SULLIVAN, I TALKED TO OUR FAVORITE BIKE
SHOP OWNER ON MARKET STREET AND HE COMMENTED HOW HE'S NEVER
SEEN THE STREET CONDITIONS BETTER IN THE TEN YEARS HE'S
BEEN RUNNING THAT BIKE SHOP IN MARKET STREET IN THE
TENDERLOIN. AND WE HAVE ALL OF YOUR HARD
WORK TO THANK FOR THE CHANGES THAT WE'RE SEEING HAPPEN TODAY
AND FOR THE YEARS YOU'VE BEEN IN SERVICE TO OUR CITY.
>> SO ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND THE RESIDENTS
OF DISTRICT FIVE, THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR SERVICE TO THE
TENDERLOIN AND TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU. BUT BEFORE YOU SPEAK, SOUP
SUPERVISOR CHEN WHO DOES NOT REPRESENT THE TENDERLOIN HAS
PUT ITSELF INTO THE QUEUE. >> THANK YOU, BOARD PRESIDENT.
I WANT TO SAY THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR SUPERVISOR MY MOVE FOR THIS
COMMENDATION. >> I'M GRATEFUL FOR THE WORK
THAT TURNER AND STATION PATROL DOES TO COLLABORATE AND WANT TO
SOLVE VERY COMPLEX ISSUES FOR THE CITY.
BUT IN PARTICULAR TODAY I WANT TO THANK SAM BERENSON FOR MANY,
MANY YEARS SERVE IN DISTRICT 11 OFFICE FIRST AS A LEGISLATIVE
AIDE AND THEN AS OUR BELOVED PUBLIC SAFETY LIAISONS.
MYSELF, MY TEAM AND MY CONSTITUENTS MISS SAM'S
DILIGENCE AND PROFESSIONALISM IN THE FIELD.
BUT I AM VERY PROUD TO SEE SAM DOING IMPORTANT WORK WITH THE
TENDERLOIN TEAM CITYWIDE. AGAIN, THANK YOU, SAM.
THANK YOU ALSO AGAIN TO THE TENORIO STATION PATROL TEAM FOR
YOUR LEADERSHIP. THANK YOU.
>> NOW THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS
. IT'S AN HONOR TO BE HERE
IN THIS BEAUTIFUL BUILDING AND TO WORK FOR THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO. IT'S BEEN MY DREAM AND I'M HERE
ON BEHALF OF OFFICER ANAYA AND SAMUEL WOULD LIKE TO THANK
YOU FOR THIS AWARD AND ALSO A SPECIAL THANKS TO OUR DPW
DEPUTY RECOLOGY AND EVERY TEAM THAT HELPS US COMPLETE OUR JOB
EVERY DAY. ALSO TO OUR CAPTAIN TENDERLOIN
GREAT LEADERSHIP AND MY FAMILY AND FRIENDS THAT CAME OVER TO
SUPPORT US TODAY AND TO MY WIFE THAT MOTIVATES ME EVERY DAY TO
BE A BETTER MAN. >> THANK YOU SO
,UH. NEXT UP DISTRICT 11 SUPERVISOR
CHEN. THANK YOU FOR PRESIDENT.
MAY I HAVE JAY THE OWNER OF THE RECOVERY ROOM TO THE PODIUM
IN CELEBRATION OF OUR EIGHT AND HPI HERITAGE MONTH.
IT IS MY GREAT PLEASURE TO RECOGNIZE JAY PHAM, OWNER OF
THE RECOVERY ROOM BAR IN THE EXCELSIOR.
>> JAY MOVED TO THE EXCELSIOR AT TEN YEARS OLD FROM HOLLAND,
VIETNAM TO LIVE IN HIS TO LIVE WITH HIS MOM AND GRANDPA.
HE LATER MOVED TO THE OCEAN VIEW NEIGHBORHOOD WHILE
ATTENDING SAN FRANCISCO STATE AND WORKED IN BARS
AND RESTAURANTS. >> WHEN JAY BECAME THE OPERATOR
OF HIS BAR. IT WAS IMPORTANT TO MAINTAIN
THE CHARACTER AS A BUSINESS OWNER.
>> HE HAS BEEN AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE EXCELSIOR COMMUNITY FROM
THE ANNUAL JERRY DAY IN AUGUST. HE HELPS WITH FUNDRAISING
AND PROVIDES A SPACE FOR GRATEFUL DEBT ENTERTAINMENT.
>> HE ALSO HOSTS EXCELSIOR STREET CLEAN UPS ON SATURDAY
MORNINGS AT THE RECOVERY ROOM. >> LAST HOLIDAY SEASON HE ALSO
HOSTED A TOY DRIVE FOR YOU FIRST AND DONATE IT TO THE
EVENT BUSINESS MY RECOVERY ROOM HOW TO KEEP OUR NEIGHBORHOODS
VIBRANT. IF YOU HAVEN'T BEEN TO OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD, I HOPE YOU WILL STOP BY FOR A DRINK AND BUY AT
THE RECOVERY ROOM. AND THANK YOU JAY, FOR
EVERYTHING THAT YOU DO TO KEEP OUR EXCELSIOR TO KEEP DISTRICT
VIBE IN. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> I THANK YOU GUYS SO MUCH FOR HAVING ME HERE.
THIS IS SUCH AN AMAZING HONOR TO REPRESENT DISTRICT 11.
>> I JUST WANT TO PERSONALLY THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR
GIVING ME THIS AMAZING HONOR. AND I WANT TO THANK DISTRICT 11
TO TAKE ME IN AS A YOUNG IMMIGRANT KID AND ALLOW ME TO
PROVIDE FOR MY FAMILY. AND TO BE HERE TODAY.
AND THAT'S BASICALLY IT. >> THANK YOU GUYS SO MUCH FOR
LISTENING TO ME. SURE
. >> DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR
CHERYL. THANK YOU.
PRESIDENT MANDELL MEAN WOULD MARLA PERKINS PLEASE COME UP TO
THE ROSTRUM? >> COLLEAGUES, IT IS MY
ABSOLUTE HONOR TO COMMEND MARLA PERKINS OF THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH
OF ST MARY THE VIRGIN LOCATED IN COW HOLLOW FOR MORE THAN 30
YEARS OF ARTISTIC EDUCATION, PERSONAL AND COMMUNITY
CONTRIBUTION TO THE WONDERFUL FAMILIES AND ESPECIALLY TO THE
CHILDREN OF THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
MARLA WAS BORN AND RAISED NEAR BRANDON, MANITOBA AND CANADA
WHERE HER LOVE OF MUSIC BEGAN AS A CHILD SINGING BESIDE HER
MOTHER AT THE PIANO. A LOVE SHE HAS SPENT HER LIFE
SHARING WITH OTHERS. SHE HOLDS ADVANCED DEGREES
IN PIANO PERFORMANCE FROM BRANDON UNIVERSITY IN THE HEART
SCHOOL OF MUSIC WHERE SHE WON THE SCHOOL'S CONCERTO
COMPOSITION COMPETITION EXCUSE ME AND LATER EARNED A
POSTGRADUATE DEGREE IN PROFESSIONAL STUDIES DIPLOMA
FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO CONSERVATORY OF MUSIC.
NOW SINCE MOVING TO SAN FRANCISCO IN 1991, MARLO'S
TAUGHT PIANO AND VOICE TO CHILDREN AND YOUTH ACROSS THE
CITY INCLUDING AT SAINT BRIDGET ACADEMY ÉCOLE NOTRE DAME DE
VICTOIRE CALVARY PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH NURSERY SCHOOL AND HER
OWN PRIVATE STUDIO. FOR OVER 20 YEARS SHE'S A
ACCOMPANIED AND COACHED YOUNG MUSICIANS THROUGH VILLAR
SINFONIA AND THE ACT YOUNG CONSERVATORY HELPING STUDENTS
FIND THEIR ARTISTIC VOICE AND PERFORM WITH GREATER DEPTH
AND CONFIDENCE. A SAINT MARY THE VIRGIN
PARISHIONER SINCE 1994, MARLA HAS SERVED AS ASSOCIATE MUSIC
DIRECTOR SINCE 2016 DIRECTING THE CHILDREN'S AND HANDBELL
CHOIRS AND PRODUCING ORIGINAL PAGEANTS AND MUSIC EACH YEAR
INCLUDING SEWING COSTUMES BY HAND FOR MARLA, MUSIC AND FAITH
HAVE ALWAYS BEEN INSEPARABLE. THROUGH HER WORK AT THE CHURCH.
SHE HAS HELPED WEAVE TOGETHER WORSHIP COMMUNITY AND THE JOY
OF MUSIC CREATING A SPACE WHERE CHILDREN AND FAMILIES FEEL
SEEN, FEEL CELEBRATED AND CONNECTED TO EACH OTHER.
HER APPROACH HAS ALWAYS BEEN ABOUT MORE THAN PERFORMANCE.
SHE TEACHES CHILDREN TO LISTEN DEEPLY, EXPRESS THEMSELVES WITH
CONFIDENCE AND CARRY A LIFELONG LOVE OF MUSIC WITH THEM.
NOW MARLO IS PREPARING TO BEGIN A NEW CHAPTER RETURNING TO
CANADA CLOSER TO HER DAUGHTER AND HER FIRST GRANDCHILD.
BUT THE HUNDREDS OF CHILDREN AND FAMILIES SHE HAS IMPACTED
HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO WILL REMEMBER HER CONTRIBUTIONS
IN THE CITY FOR GENERATIONS TO COME.
SO MARLA, ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, ON BEHALF
OF THE PARISHIONERS OF SAINT MARY, THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE
BEAUTY, THE JOY AND THE DEDICATION YOU'VE BROUGHT TO
SAN FRANCISCO'S CHILDREN, OUR FAMILIES AND THE ENTIRE
COMMUNITY FOR MORE THAN THREE DECADES.
WE WISH YOU ALL THE BEST IN THIS EXCITING NEW CHAPTER.
>> CONGRATULATIONS. >> IT'S SUCH A QUIET CROWD HERE
COMPARED TO THE CHILDREN WRIGGLING ON THE FLOOR BOUNCING
OFF THE WALLS AND HIDING UNDER THE CHAIRS.
>> BUT MY COMMUNITY WORK IN SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN ENTIRELY
THROUGH MUSIC. AND I AM SO GRATEFUL FOR THIS
HONOR. AND THROUGH THESE YEARS I TRULY
LOVE WATCHING A CHILD OPEN UP TO THE SONG AND THE DANCE
WITHIN THEMSELVES. DISCOVERING A MUSICAL VOICE
AND EXPRESSION OF THEM SHARING WITH OTHERS OF LISTENING AND IN
AN AGE OF DISTRACTION. >> TUNING IN AND ENGAGING MY
WORK IN THE CHURCH COMMUNITY OF THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH OF ST
MARY, THE VIRGIN AND THE WIDER COMMUNITY OF SAN FRANCISCO HAS
PROVIDED SO MANY OPPORTUNITIES TO WITNESS JUST THAT.
I AM SO GRATEFUL TO THIS COMMUNITY AND TO EVERY CHILD
AND ADULT IN SAINT MARY'S AND FOR ITS SUPPORT OF
CHILDREN'S PROGRAMS AND MULTIGENERATIONAL
INTERACTION. ALSO FOR MY COMMUNITIES IN THE
RICHMOND AND SUNSET DISTRICTS THE SCHOOLS AND THE MUSICAL
ORGANIZATIONS WITH WHOM I'VE WORKED AND SOCIALIZE.
>> I TRULY BELIEVE THAT IT TAKES A VILLAGE TO RAISE A
CHILD. >> I FEEL BLESSED AND HONORED
TO HAVE LIVED AND WORKED IN THIS GREAT CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR 35 YEARS AND TO HAVE RAISED MY OWN FAMILY HERE
BESIDE THE OCEAN IN THE PARKS. AMONG THE VARIETY OF PEOPLE
IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS AS I NOW PREPARE TO MOVE TO HELP RAISE
MY NEW GRANDSON, I WILL CHERISH THESE YEARS IN SAN FRANCISCO AT
ST MARY'S AND IN THIS CITY IN MY HEART.
THANK YOU
. AND NEXT WE HAVE DISTRICT THREE
SUPERVISOR SAUTER. >> THANK YOU PRESIDENT MANDOLIN
. COLLEAGUES TODAY I HAVE THE
HONOR OF WELCOMING DAVID OSMOND TO THE CHAMBERS FOR A SPECIAL
RECOGNITION. >> DAVID, WOULD YOU PLEASE COME
ON UP AND JOIN US? >> DAVID YOU HAVE SOME FANS OUT
THERE. AS YOU ALL KNOW LAST MONTH WAS
EARTH MONTH AND WE HAD PLANNED TO HAVE DAVID IN THEN BUT WE'RE
HAPPY TO USE A SCHEDULING CONFLICT AS AN EXCUSE TO EXTEND
EARTH MONTH CELEBRATIONS JUST A BIT LONGER.
NOT ONLY IS DAVID A PROUD DISTRICT THREE RESIDENT
RESIDING IN RUSSIAN HILL BUT HE IS ALSO THE RETIRED DEPUTY
DIRECTOR OF THE SAN FRANCISCO ENVIRONMENT DEPARTMENT.
DURING HIS TIME THERE HE LED RECYCLING PROGRAM EFFORTS
INCLUDING ADOPTING A ZERO WASTE GOAL.
HE WORKED TO CLOSE THE POINT IN POTRERO POWER PLANTS CREATED
THE GREEN JOBS PROGRAM AND SAW THE DEPARTMENT GROW IN SIZE
AND IMPACT OVER THE YEARS. >> DAVID IS ALSO A SAN
FRANCISCO A PROMINENT SAN FRANCISCO BIRDER
AND PHOTOGRAPHER TWO PASSIONS THAT HE'S BEEN ABLE TO SPEND
MORE TIME ON IN RETIREMENT. HE MANAGES THE ANNUAL SAN
FRANCISCO CHRISTMAS BIRD COUNT FOR THE NATIONAL AUDUBON
SOCIETY, WHICH IS AN IMPORTANT EXERCISE TO TRACK POPULATION
CHANGES AND MONITOR ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH.
>> DAVID LEADS REGULAR GOLDEN GATE BIRD ALLIANCE FIELD TRIPS
AT FORT MASON WHERE HE DELIGHTS VISITORS WITH HIS ENCYCLOPÉDIE
. KNOWLEDGE OF THE MANY SPECIES
THAT CALL A SAN FRANCISCO HOME .
IN FACT, DAVID ESTIMATES THAT HE HAS SPOTTED NEARLY 500
UNIQUE BIRD SPECIES THAT HAVE FLOWN THROUGH SAN FRANCISCO
OVER THE PAST 20 YEARS. >> DURING THE PANDEMIC HE
TURNED HIS KNOWLEDGE INTO A WELCOME DISTRACTION WHEN HE
STARTED A PRACTICE OF POSTING A NEW BIRD OF THE DAY ON NEXT
DOOR EACH DAY. NEIGHBORS OFFERED HIS POST
EVERY DAY AND COMMENTED HOW IT WAS SOMETHING TO LOOK FORWARD
TO AND LEARN ABOUT IN THE MIDST OF A DARK TIME.
DAVID THANK YOU FOR YOUR NEARLY 20 YEARS THE DEPARTMENT OF
ENVIRONMENT FOR SHARING YOUR KNOWLEDGE AND WISDOM AND ALWAYS
ENSURING THAT SAN FRANCISCO IS A PLACE THAT CONTINUES TO LEAD
IN PROTECTING OUR ENVIRONMENT. I HOPE THAT YOU'LL SHARE A FEW
WORDS MAYBE TELL US SOME OF THE BIRDS TO KEEP AN EYE OUT FOR
OUT THERE. AND THE FLOOR IS YOURS IF YOU
WANT TO SHARE A FEW WORDS. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH SUPERVISOR SAUTER FOR THIS HONOR.
AFTER A LIFE LONG CAREER IN THE ENVIRONMENTAL FIELD I'M NOW
DEDICATED TO SHARING IMAGES AND EDUCATION ABOUT THE
BEAUTIFUL WILDLIFE THAT CALL SAN FRANCISCO HOME AND TO DO
WHAT I CAN TO PROMOTE CONSERVATION.
>> DESPITE BEING 95% DEVELOPED SAN FRANCISCO IS STILL ONE OF
THE MOST BIODIVERSE CITIES IN THE NATION.
HERE ARE JUST A HANDFUL OF EXAMPLES.
WE ALL KNOW ABOUT THE WILD PARROTS OF TELEGRAPH FAIL THE
OFFICIAL CITY ANIMAL AND WE PROBABLY ARE FAMILIAR WITH THE
SEA LIONS HAD PIER 39 INCLUDING ITS ANCHORS THE STELLAR SEA
LION AND THE SHORE SHOWN UP. >> BUT THERE'S LOTS OF OTHER
ACTIVITY IN THIS CITY. THERE'S THE HARBOR SEALS NOW
BRINGING THEIR YOUNG TO THE DOCKS ACROSS THE STREET FROM
THE SAFEWAY AND THE MARINA THERE.
AND THEN THERE ARE THE BIRDS. LAST NIGHT RADAR PICKED UP
275,000 BIRDS FLYING OVER THE CITY AS THEY MIGRATED ON THE
PACIFIC FLYWAY WITH A NUMBER OF THEM STOPPING HERE TO REST OR
TO SPEND THE SUMMER. WE HAVE 75 SPECIES OF BIRDS
THAT RAISE THEIR YOUNG IN THE COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> ALSO THERE'S THE GRAY AND HUMPBACK WHALES THAT
MIGRATE THROUGH SAN FRANCISCO WATERS AND SOMETIMES HANG
AROUND ALCATRAZ OR THE CLIFF HOUSE.
>> THERE ARE THE MANY SPECIES OF BUTTERFLIES THAT LIVE HERE
ON MIGRATE THROUGH HERE. >> THERE ARE 20 PLUS SPECIES OF
MAMMALS THAT LIVE HERE INCLUDING THE REESTABLISHED
COYOTES. >> AND THERE ARE HUNDREDS OF
NATIVE PLANT SPECIES INCLUDING SOME THAT ARE FOUND NOWHERE
ELSE IN THE WORLD. I WOULD LIKE TO END BY
DEDICATING THIS COMMENDATION TO THE SPECIES THAT SHARE OUR HOME
ISN'T SLEEPING. >> ALL RIGHT.
LAST BUT NOT LEAST IT IS MY GREAT HONOR TO PRESENT A
COMMENDATION TO THE PEOPLE WHO HELPED PULL OFF SAN FRANCISCO'S
ST PATRICK'S DAY PARADE AND FESTIVAL THIS YEAR.
AND SPECIFICALLY I WANT TO INVITE UP JAMES QUINN, P.J.
MASTERSON AND ALLIE SHAFER WHO ARE THESE AMAZING PEOPLE?
WELL, LET ME TELL YOU. SO THE SAME SAINT PATRICK'S DAY
PARADE HAS BEEN A PART OF SAN FRANCISCO HISTORY SINCE 1851
AND IS ONE OF THE CITY'S LONGEST RUNNING AND MOST
BELOVED TRADITIONS. THE UNITED IRISH SOCIETIES OF
SAN FRANCISCO, A VOLUNTEER RUN ORGANIZATION THAT CELEBRATES
IRISH CULTURE AND COMMUNITY HAS BEEN THE LONG TIME HOST IN 2024
. >> JAMES QUINN STEPPED INTO THE
ROLE OF PARADE DIRECTOR AT UNITED IRISH SOCIETIES ASSUMING
RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE PARADE'S OVERALL COORDINATION AND VISION
. AS THE HEAD OF THE ORGANIZING
COMMITTEE. JAMES MANAGES THE BIG PICTURE
ELEMENTS OF THE EVENT INCLUDING INVITATIONS, COORDINATION WITH
GRAND MARSHALS AND ORGANIZING THE MANY VOLUNTEERS
AND PARTICIPANTS THAT MAKE THE CELEBRATION POSSIBLE.
JAMES WORKS CLOSELY WITH P.J. MASTERSON, HIS RIGHT HAND MAN
TO HIS RIGHT WITH WITHIN THE UNITED IRISH SOCIETY'S WHO
HELPS HIM WITH THE FINER DETAILS OF THE EVENT
AND TROUBLESHOOT ITS CHALLENGES.
UNDER JAMES'S LEADERSHIP, THE UNITED IRISH SOCIETY'S ALSO
LAUNCHED THE ST PATRICK'S DAY FESTIVAL IN 2024 AS PART OF THE
EFFORT TO RE-ENERGIZE THE CELEBRATION AFTER THE PANDEMIC.
JAMES AND THE COMMITTEE WORK TO RECRUIT PERFORMERS, FOOD
VENDORS AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATIONS FROM ACROSS THE
CITY AND THAT FIRST FESTIVAL LAUNCHED UNDER THE THEME UNITE
S.F. AIMING TO SHARE ST PATRICK'S DAY WITH MORE PEOPLE
AND EMBRACE ALL THE UNIQUE CULTURAL GROUPS THAT MAKE SAN
FRANCISCO UNIQUE NOW. ALTHOUGH IT WAS A SUCCESS IT
WAS ALSO COSTLY AND THOSE EXORBITANT COSTS AND MYRIAD OF
LOGISTICAL CHALLENGES MADE IT IMPRACTICAL IMPOSSIBLE TO DO A
ST PATRICK'S DAY FESTIVAL IN 2025.
FORTUNATELY JAMES IS NOT SOMEONE WHO GIVES UP.
HE PLOTS, HE MEETS, HE CAJOLES .
>> I WAS IN SOME I WAS INVITED TO AT LEAST SOME OF THOSE
MEETINGS DETERMINED TO HOST A FESTIVAL IN 2026 HE MET
REPEATEDLY WITH CITY DEPARTMENTS TO BETTER
UNDERSTAND THE MANY REQUIREMENTS AND PROCESSES
INVOLVED. AND THROUGH THAT PERSISTENCE HE
FORGED CRITICAL PARTNERSHIPS WITH CITY AGENCIES AND LEADERS
WHOSE SHARED COMMITMENT ULTIMATELY HELPED MAKE THE
FESTIVAL A REALITY. I DO WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THEY
WERE NOT ABLE TO BE HERE TODAY BUT I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE
PARK FOLKS WHO WORKED CLOSELY WITH THE UNITED IRISH SOCIETY'S
ON THE PARADE AND FESTIVAL AND SPECIFICALLY I WANT TO CALL
OUT BEVERLY NG, SHAUNA BO GATES AND DANA KETCHUM.
BUT I REALLY WANT TO CELEBRATE HONOR LEE SCHAEFER, THE
DIRECTOR OF LARGE SPECIAL EVENTS IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE
AND MY CONSTITUENTS WHO WAS AN INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT CHAMPION
FOR THE PARADE AND FESTIVAL INSIDE TD CITY HALL.
AND I'VE SEEN HER DO THIS FOR OTHER EVENTS WHERE SOMEONE HAS
A GOOD IDEA THE CITY IS BIG, DAUNTING BUREAUCRATIC
AND FIGURES OUT A WAY TO MAKE IT HAPPEN.
SHE BROUGHT TOGETHER SEVERAL DEPARTMENTS INCLUDING REC
AND PARK, SFPD, MTA AND DEPARTMENT OF EMERGENCY
MANAGEMENT COORDINATING THE MANY CONVERSATIONS AND MOVING
PIECES AND MOVING PIECES THAT WERE REQUIRED TO ACTUALLY MAKE
THE FESTIVAL HAPPEN. ALONG THE WAY SHE HELPED JAMES
AND PJ CUT THROUGH THE MAZE OF CITY REGULATIONS AND PROCEDURES
,WRANGLING THE COMPLICATED BUREAUCRATIC PROCESS INTO A
CLEARER SET OF GUIDELINES THAT JAMES P.J. AND THE UNITED IRISH
SOCIETIES COULD FOLLOW NOT JUST FOR THIS YEAR'S FESTIVAL BUT WE
HOPE FOR FUTURE CELEBRATIONS AS WELL.
SO THANK YOU ELLIE, FOR MAKING THAT POSSIBLE.
YOUTH SPORTS DAY WAS A GREAT SUCCESS.
ON THAT BRIGHT MARCH AFTERNOON, CHILDREN DARTED AROUND CIVIC
CENTER LEARNING TRADITIONAL IRISH SPORTS INCLUDING GAELIC
FOOTBALL HURLING AND RUGBY AND HAVING IRISH SPORTS PLAYED
AND REPRESENTED IN THE HEART OF SAN FRANCISCO MADE FOR A
FITTING CLOSE TO THE ST PATRICK'S DAY PARADE.
SHARING AN IMPORTANT PART OF IRISH CULTURE WITH NEW
GENERATIONS ORGANIZING THE ST PATRICK'S DAY PARADE
AND FESTIVAL IS A LABOR OF LOVE FOR FROM EVERYONE INVOLVED.
BUT I DO WANT TO REEMPHASIZE THAT THE UNITED IRISH SOCIETY'S
I KNOW WE GOT A FEW FOLKS HERE IS ENTIRELY VOLUNTARY VOLUNTEER
RUN WITH NO PAID STAFF OR DEDICATED FUNDING AND THE TIME
COMMITMENT OFTEN RIVALS THAT OF A FULL TIME JOB.
>> SO THANK YOU TO JAMES PJ EVERYONE AT THE UNITED IRISH
SOCIETIES FOR ALL YOU DO FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND THANK YOU
ELLIE FOR STEPPING UP IN THIS CASE AS IN SO MANY OTHERS.
>> AND NOW UP OF COURSE THE DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR HAS
WISELY PUT HIMSELF INTO THE QUEUE.
>> SUPERVISOR LONG OKAY. THANK YOU PRESIDENT GENTLEMAN
FOR TAKING THE TIME TO RECOGNIZE THIS WONDERFUL GROUP
AND THE WORK THEY DO FOR OUR CITY.
I JUST WANTED TO TAKE A MOMENT TO SAY THANK YOU AND RECOGNIZE
THE INCREDIBLE PEOPLE WHO HELPED MAKE THE ST PATRICK'S
DAY CELEBRATION SUCCESSFUL. THESE KIND OF TRADITIONS DON'T
JUST HAPPEN THEY HAPPEN BECAUSE PEOPLE CARE ENOUGH TO PUT
IN THE TIME, ENERGY AND HEART TO BRING COMMUNITIES TOGETHER
YEAR AFTER YEAR. WE'RE ESPECIALLY LUCKY TO HAVE
SUCH A STRONG IRISH COMMUNITY IN THE SENSE THAT IT'S A PLACE
WHERE FRIENDSHIPS ARE BUILT. TRADITIONS ARE PASSED DOWN
AND THE BROADER COMMUNITY COMES TOGETHER TO CELEBRATE.
ST PATRICK'S DAY IS ALWAYS SUCH A JOYFUL TRADITION IN SAN
FRANCISCO BUT THAT JOY COMES FROM THE PEOPLE BEHIND THE
SCENES WHO MAKE IT ALL HAPPEN. SO THANK YOU TO THE UNITED
IRISH SOCIETY'S JAMES QUINN, P.J. MASTERSON, ELLIE SCHAEFER,
BEVERLY NG AND EVERYONE WHO HELPED ORGANIZE SUPPORT
AND BRING THIS CELEBRATION TO LIFE.
THANK YOU FOR CONTINUING TO KEEP THIS TRADITION GOING IN A
CITY THAT'S CONSTANTLY CHANGING.
THERE'S SOMETHING REALLY SPECIAL ABOUT THE COMMUNITIES
THAT CONTINUE SHOWING UP BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER AND KEEPING
THESE TRADITIONS ALIVE FOR THE NEXT GENERATION.
CONGRATULATIONS AND THANK YOU FOR ALL THE WORK THAT YOU DO.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR WONG AND NOW JAMES,
THE FLOOR IS YOURS. >> THANKS VERY MUCH FOR HAVING
US HERE THIS AFTERNOON. SUPERVISOR MANAGEMENT THANK
YOU. YOUR BIG SUPPORT FROM THE
MOMENT I MET YOU THERE HAD A CASE WAS SERVED EIGHT MONTHS
AGO FOR THE ROGER CASEMENT DEDICATION.
SO THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
PJ AND ELLIE, I MEAN YOU'VE BEEN AMAZING.
PAGE IS BRILLIANT. HE READS ALL THE FINE PRINT
AND ELLIE, YOU KNOW, HAS BEEN GRACED TO WALK, READ AND I WAS
JUST TALKING TO OUR LEADER NEXT YEAR WE HAVE OUR EYES SET ON
FOLSOM PLAZA SO FAR A BIG FESTIVAL THERE SO AGAIN THIS IS
A FABULOUS ROOM AND I LOVE THIS CITY.
I KNOW WHERE I'M FROM. I GOT MARRIED OUTSIDE THAT DOOR
25 YEARS AGO SO I REALLY APPRECIATE APPRECIATE IT THE
CITY AND EVERYTHING YOU GUYS DO FOR US AND THE PLACE LOOKS
GREAT AND THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. ALL RIGHT WITH AROUND
AND BEFORE WE MOVE ON, I SHOULD NOTE THAT WE HAVE OUR FORMER
WELL NOT OUR COLLEAGUE BUT FORMER MEMBER OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WE HAVE A NAME IS BROWN IS BACK IN THE CHAMBER.
WELCOME REVEREND BROWN AND I THINK WE WERE MADAM CLERK AT
ITEM 18 ITEM PLEASE CALL ITEM 18.
>> ITEM 18 IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE EXECUTION
AND DELIVERY OF MULTIFAMILY HOUSING REVENUE NOTES IN ONE OR
MORE SERIES IN AN AGGREGATE PRINCIPAL AMOUNT NOT TO EXCEED
30 MILLION FOR THE PURPOSE OF PROVIDING FINANCING FOR THE
CONSTRUCTION OF A 94 UNIT MULTIFAMILY RENTAL HOUSING
PROJECT KNOWN AS 1687 MARKET RESIDENCES.
PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM ON ITEM 18 SUPERVISOR WONG
WANG EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR MUHAMMAD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI MANDELL MAN I SUPERVISOR MALKA MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EITHER ATTORNEYS WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED FOR CITY STAFF WHO MAY
BE WONDERING I THINK WE WILL WILL TAKE IT TO THE 3 P.M.
SPECIAL ORDERS AFTER WE GET THROUGH ITEM 20 I THINK MADAM
CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 19. >> ITEM 19 THIS IS A MOTION TO
APPOINT JASPER A VERDIN TERM ENDING JANUARY 1ST 2027 MICHAEL
FRUIT FOR TRO SAM HURST LUZINSKI RESIDENCY REQUIREMENT
WAIVED AND KEESHA MASON TERMS ENDING JANUARY 1ST 2028
AND BRANDON FOUNTAIN AMELIA HARMON, STEPHANIE GONZALEZ
AND TARA GAMBOA EASTMAN. TERMS ENDING JANUARY 1ST, 2029
TO THE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH COMMISSION.
>> ALL RIGHT. I THINK WE CAN TAKE THAT ITEM
SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MOTION IS
APPROVED. >> AND MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 20. ITEM 20.
THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE BUSINESS
AND TAX REGULATIONS CAMPAIGN AND GOVERNMENTAL CONDUCT CODE
ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH, LABOR AND EMPLOYMENT MUNICIPAL
ELECTIONS PART PLANNING POLICE PUBLIC WORKS AND TRANSPORTATION
CODES TO DEFINE AND DISTINGUISH BETWEEN COMMISSIONS
AND ADVISORY BODIES TO ESTABLISH THE TERM AND TERM
LIMITS OF BODIES TO ESTABLISH, MODIFY OR CLARIFY THE SUNSET
DATES OF CERTAIN BODIES TO ABOLISH OTHER BODIES TO MODIFY
THE COMPOSITION AND EXCUSE ME TO MODIFY THEIR POWERS
AND DUTIES TO MODIFY THE COMPOSITION, MEMBERSHIP OR
APPOINTMENT STRUCTURE TO TRANSFER TO CHAPTER FIVE OF THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE PROVISIONS FOR BODIES THAT ARE CURRENTLY
LOCATED ELSEWHERE IN THE MUNICIPAL CODE TO MODIFY THE
DUTIES, RESPONSIBILITIES, DEFINITIONS AND MEMBERSHIP OF
THE CHILD CARE PLANNING AND ADVISORY COUNCIL TO CONFORM
WITH APPLICABLE STATE LAW TO ADD TO STATE REQUIRED BODIES TO
MAKE OTHER MINOR OR CLARIFYING CHANGES AND TO AUTHORIZE
AND DIRECT THE CITY ATTORNEY TO MAKE CLERICAL NON SUBSTANTIVE
CHANGES TO UPDATE THE MUNICIPAL CODE PURSUANT TO CHARTER
SECTION FOUR POINT 100.1 SUB E TWO THIRDS OF THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS WOULD BE REQUIRED TO EITHER AMEND OR DISAPPROVE
THIS ORDINANCE, AMEND IT TO GET THE NAMES IN THE QUEUE BUT
THERE THEY ARE SUPERVISED THEIR MELGAR.
>> THANK YOU PRESIDENT COLLEAGUES I FIRSTLY WANT TO
EXPRESS MY UTMOST GRATITUDE TO THE MEMBERS OF THE COMMISSION
STREAMLINING TASK FORCE I WATCHED ALMOST EVERY MEETING
ALONG WITH MY STAFF. IT WAS LONG HOURS AND A LOT OF
WORK. I PARTICULARLY WANT TO THANK
CHAIR AT HARRINGTON AND THE REMARKABLE STAFF AT THE CITY
ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE ESPECIALLY RACHEL MORAN FOR ALL
THE HOURS THAT THEY DEDICATED TO THE PROCESS TO BEING THERE
BUT ALSO ALL THE RESEARCH AND ANALYSIS THIS WAS A
HERCULEAN EFFORT THAT UNVEILED SO MUCH THAT HAS BEEN LEFT
UNTOUCHED AND LOST IN OUR CODE .
BEFORE THIS PROCESS WE DIDN'T EVEN HAVE AN ACCURATE NUMBER OF
THE COUNT OF OF BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS IN HOW MANY
BODIES THAT WE HAVE. >> THERE'S A PARALLEL PROCESS
THAT NEEDS TO GO BEFORE THE VOTERS AND WE WILL TAKE CERTAIN
PARTS OF THEIR RECOMMENDATION THROUGH THE CHARTER AMENDMENT
PROCESS IN THE COMING MONTHS. >> I FEEL THAT THE ORDINANCE
BEFORE US TODAY REFLECTS MANY OF THE CHANGES WE NEED TO MAKE
AS A CITY. FOR EXAMPLE, ELIMINATING 36
INACTIVE DEFUNCT BODIES REORGANIZE USING THE CODE
SECTION SO THAT THEY'RE EASIER TO INTERPRET CLARIFYING THE
ROLES FOR VARIOUS BODIES AND PROVIDING THE SAME LEVEL OF
UNIFORMITY OF SEATS IN TERMS. >> HOWEVER, THERE ARE
RECOMMENDATIONS OR ELIMINATIONS OR CONSOLIDATIONS OF BODY THAT
I DON'T AGREE WITH OR I FEEL NEED MORE FOCUSED ANALYSIS.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT I'VE ALWAYS YOU KNOW, FOCUS MY
ATTENTION ON WHILE I'VE BEEN SUPERVISOR IS AT THE LITTLE'S
THE EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION IN THIS ORDINANCE PROPOSES THE
ELIMINATION OF THE EARLY CARE AND EDUCATION OVERSIGHT
AND ADVISORY COMMITTEE ON WHICH I SAT WITH ITS DUTIES
CONSOLIDATING IT INTO THE FIRST FIVE COMMISSION WHICH IS A
STATE MANDATED BODY THAT IS REQUIRED TO APPROVE SPENDING OF
STATE PROP TEN TOBACCO TAX REVENUE FUNDING.
>> THE FIRST FIVE COMMISSION INCLUDES MEMBERS OF STAFF FROM
OTHER DEPARTMENTS AND A BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
IT FEELS INAPPROPRIATE FOR OTHER DEPARTMENT HEADS
AND STAFF TO INFLUENCE THIS DEPARTMENT.
THE DEPARTMENT OF EARLY CHILDHOOD, ITS BUDGET AND ITS
PROGRAMS THAT HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH THIS STATE MANDATE.
>> EVEN THE TASK FORCE RECOMMENDATION ACKNOWLEDGED
THAT THIS WAS NOT, YOU KNOW, A GREAT FIX BUT THEY FELT
CONSOLIDATED TO CONSOLIDATE THE BODIES AND YOU KNOW, THEY HAVE
SOME OVERLAP. >> WHILE THE FIRST FIVE
COMMISSION DOES PLAY A SIGNIFICANT ROLE IN SHAPING THE
THE COUNTY STRATEGIC PLAN ON EARLY CHILDHOOD AND FAMILY
SERVICES, THAT IS NOT COMPREHENSIVE ENOUGH.
>> SAN FRANCISCANS APPROVED HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS
TO SUPPORT EARLY CHILDHOOD AND ENVISION UNIVERSAL CHILD
CARE SYSTEM. I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT THAT WE
HAVE PROPER OVERSIGHT AND POLICY ESPECIALLY NOW THAT
WE ARE FORGING AHEAD WITH UNIVERSAL CHILD CARE.
I DON'T FEEL LIKE THIS ORDINANCE ENCAPSULATES ALL THE
CHANGES THAT I WANT TO SEE AND I WOULD LIKE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO SUPPORT TRAILING LEGISLATION TO ADDRESS THOSE
ISSUES. SO AS SUCH BECAUSE THE VOTE
BEFORE US TODAY IS THE ORDINANCE AS A WHOLE AND WE
CAN'T BE VOTING ON DIFFERENT PARTS.
I WILL BE VOTING NO AND FORTUNATELY THERE ARE SOME
AMENDMENTS I THINK MANY OF US HAVE EXPLORED BUT FEEL THAT WE
NEED MORE TIME TO DEVELOP AND TIME IS NOT ON OUR SIDE.
GIVEN THAT THIS ORDINANCE GETS APPROVED WITH OR WITHOUT OUR
VOTE AND THAT IT WAS PUT FORTH BECAUSE OF A VOTE OF THE PEOPLE
. AGAIN, I WANT TO EMPHASIZE THAT
MOST OF WHAT'S IN THIS ORDINANCE IS NECESSARY
AND SHOULD BE ENACTED. I JUST WISH THERE WAS A WAY TO
DO IT WITHOUT TAKING THE OTHER RECOMMENDATIONS THAT I FEEL
LIKE NEED MORE WORK OR HAVE UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES OR
NEGATIVE CONSEQUENCES. >> I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING ON
THE TRAILING LEGISLATION AND TAKING MANY OF THE
RECOMMENDATIONS OFFERED BY THE TASK FORCE AND MY APOLOGIES.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK RACHEL ALONSO FROM THE CITY
ADMINISTRATORS OFFICE FOR HER INCREDIBLE WORK STAFFING THIS
TASK FORCE. >> THANK YOU.
>> SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> COLLEAGUES WANT TO ECHO
SUPERVISOR MELGAR HIS COMMENT ON I'M THINKING A LOT OF PEOPLE
TO HELP GET US HERE BUT I WANT TO START WITH THINKING THE
VOTERS IN NOVEMBER OF 2024 SAN FRANCISCANS PASSED PROPOSITION
E WITH 53% OF THE VOTE CREATING THE COMMISSION STREAMLINING
TASK FORCE AND DIRECTING IT TO METHODICALLY REVIEW ALL THE
CITY'S BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS. AND TODAY WE ARE FOLLOWING
THROUGH ON THAT MANDATE FROM THE VOTERS.
>> IT'S WORTH APPRECIATING THE SCALE OF WHAT THE TASK FORCE
TOOK ON SAN FRANCISCO HAS 152 BOARDS AND COMMISSIONS WITH
OVER 1000 RESIDENTS VOLUNTEERING THEIR TIME BUT
ONLY 115 OF THOSE BODIES WERE EVER EVEN ACTIVE.
>> MANY EXISTED IN LA BUT HADN'T MET IN YEARS.
>> THE TASK FORCE SPENT ALL OF 2525 REVIEWING EVERY SINGLE ONE
OF THOSE COMMISSIONS. THAT MEANS 21 PUBLIC MEETINGS
556 PUBLIC COMMENTS FROM OVER 320 UNIQUE COMMENTERS AND 6667
PIECES OF WRITTEN PUBLIC COMMENT.
THIS ORDINANCE IMPLEMENTS THE TASK FORCE RECOMMENDATIONS
STANDARDIZING TERMS, ADDING TERM LIMITS, LIMITING HOLDOVER
SERVICE AND CONSOLIDATING THE LARGE MAJORITY OF THESE BODIES
INTO A SINGLE READABLE CHAPTER OF THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE.
SOME ARE WORRIED THAT STREAMLINING MEANS LESS
COMMUNITY VOICE BUT THIS PROCESS IS PROOF THAT THOSE
GOALS ARE NOT IN CONFLICT. THE BODIES THAT SURVIVED ARE
BETTER DEFINED AND BETTER STRUCTURED.
THEY'LL BE MORE MEANINGFUL VENUES FOR PARTICIPATION THAN
152 BODIES OF UNEVEN QUALITY. >> WHAT WE ARE ELIMINATING IS
BUREAUCRATIC REDUNDANCY NOT COMMUNITY VOICE.
AND AGAIN BEFORE I CLOSE I WANT TO RECOGNIZE SO MANY OF THE
PEOPLE WHO MADE THIS POSSIBLE. TASK FORCE MEMBERS GAVE AN
ENORMOUS COMMITMENT OF TIME AND EXPERTISE.
>> SOPHIE HAYWARD FROM THE CITY ADMINISTRATOR'S OFFICE.
NATASHA MITCHELL FROM THE COMPTROLLER'S OFFICE, ANDREA
BROSS FROM THE CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AT HARRINGTON AS THE
BOARD'S LABOR REPRESENTATIVE SOPHIA KETTLER FROM THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE AND GENE FRASER OF THE PRESIDIO TRUST WHO SERVED
DURING THE FIRST PHASE OF THIS WORK AND TO THE STAFF WHO
PRODUCED THE FINAL REPORT. RACHEL ALONZO HANNAH GONZALES,
JOANNA BELL, HENRY O'CONNELL AND CHELSEA HALL.
>> THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR SERVICE.
SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG HAD A REPUTATION FOR GOVERNING BY
COMMITTEE SOMETIMES AT THE EXPENSE OF CLARITY
AND ACCOUNTABILITY. THIS ORDINANCE IS A MEANINGFUL
VOTER MANDATED STEP IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION AND I INTEND TO
VOTE FOR IT AND SUPPORT THIS. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU
PRESIDENT MILLIMAN AND COLLEAGUES.
AS YOU CAN SEE THIS CAME TO US WITHOUT RECOMMENDATION.
I WANT TO ECHO ALL OF SUPERVISOR MYRNA MELGAR
STATEMENTS. I AGREE WITH HER
WHOLEHEARTEDLY. I JUST WANT TO ADD A COUPLE OF
THINGS. ONE, I THINK EVEN THOUGH THAT
SOME OF THESE COMMITTEES THAT ARE EITHER BEING ELIMINATED OR
CHANGED EVEN THOUGH THEY MAY NOT BE A PART OF THE CHARTER,
THEY MOST CERTAINLY WERE CREATED BY BODIES THAT CAME
FROM CHARTER BODIES. AND SOME OF THESE CHANGES MOST
CERTAINLY NEEDED TO HAPPEN. BUT I THINK THERE ARE SOME SOME
COMMITTEES THAT ARE STILL IMPORTANT THAT DID PROVIDE A
LOT OF COMMUNITY VOICE THAT WE STILL NEED.
I ALSO THINK THAT WE ARE UNDER THE GUN IN TERMS OF WHAT WE CAN
DO HERE TODAY. AND SO THIS IS ONE OF THOSE
THINGS WHERE IF YOU DON'T ACCEPT EVERYTHING THEN YOU KNOW
WE'RE STUCK. AND SO I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT
IS WHY I WILL SUPPORT IT SITTING HERE WITHOUT
RECOMMENDATION. AND LIKE SUPERVISOR MELGAR
CANNOT SUPPORT THIS IN ITS ENTIRETY AND HAVING NO CHOICE.
I CAN'T SUPPORT THIS TODAY. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. CHAIR WALTON I WILL ECHO THE
THANKS OF MY COLLEAGUES FOR FOUR CHAIR HARRINGTON
AND MEMBERS BRUCE HEYWARD, ME HALL AND KETTLER FOR THEIR WORK
ON THE TASK FORCE. >> I THINK SUPERVISOR MAHMUD
DETAILED SOME OF YOU KNOW THE WORK THAT THEY DID BUT 20
THROUGH PUBLIC MEETINGS IT WAS A HEAVY, HEAVY LIFT.
THEY WERE DEEP IN THE WEEDS FOR A VERY LONG TIME AND I DON'T
KNOW THAT IT'S AS OVER TIME WE WILL THINK WE WILL DECIDE OR
FEEL LIKE EVERY LAST DECISION THAT THEY MADE WAS EXACTLY
RIGHT. BUT THE POINT OF THE BENEFIT OF
THIS BEING AN ORDINANCE IS THAT AT ANY POINT THE BOARD CAN MAKE
A CHANGE. >> I DO THINK IT IS HARD ONCE
BODIES HAVE BEEN CREATED REPORTING REQUIREMENTS HAVE
BEEN ADDED AND THOSE THINGS TEND TO ACCRETE MUCH MORE
RELIABLY THAN THAN WE GET AROUND TO TRIMMING OR PRUNING.
AND I THINK IT IS GOOD FOR THE PEOPLE WHO TRY TO MAKE OUR
GOVERNMENT WORK. IT WOULD BE GOOD IF WE DID A
LITTLE MORE PRUNING, A LITTLE MORE OFTEN.
>> I THINK THE FORCING FUNCTION HERE OF MAKING THIS BOARD VOTE
ON SOMETHING AND HAVING IT TAKE EFFECT EVEN IF WE DON'T
AND UNLESS WE REJECTED BY A SUPERMAJORITY WAS PROBABLY A
LITTLE BIT OF GENIUS IN ACTUALLY FORCING US TO TO
TAKE SOME ACTIONS THAT MIGHT BE HARD.
BUT AGAIN IF A MAJORITY OF US, YOU KNOW, WANT TO CHANGE
SOMETHING ABOUT THIS, WE CERTAINLY CAN DO THAT GOING
FORWARD. AND I'M SURE AND I SUSPECT THAT
WE WILL MAKE AT LEAST SOME CHANGES IN SOME OF WHAT WE'RE
DOING HERE TODAY. BUT I THINK OVERALL THIS IS A
GOOD SET OF A GOOD SET OF CHANGES AND A GOOD PROCESS
AND I WAS HAPPY TO PUT MY NAME ON IT.
AND WITH THAT MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS
ITEM ON ITEM 20 SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN
NO SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN NO SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI
RANDLEMAN I'M SUPERVISOR MELGAR NO MELGAR NO SUPERVISOR SAUDER
SOLDER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON
WALTON NO THERE ARE SIX EYES AND FOUR NOS WITH SUPERVISORS
CHAN CHIN MELGAR AND WALTON VOTING NO.
>> THE ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING.
>> ALL RIGHTS MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO OUR THREE PM OUR FIRST 3
P.M. SPECIAL ORDER ITEM 21 THROUGH 24 COMPRISE A APOLOGIES
MR. PRESIDENT ITEMS 21 AND 22 COMPRISE A PUBLIC HEARING.
THIS IS A HEARING TO CONSIDER OBJECTIONS TO A REPORT OF
ASSESSMENT COSTS SUBMITTED BY THE DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC WORKS
FOR SIDEWALK AND CURB REPAIRS THROUGH THE SIDEWALK INSPECTION
AND REPAIR PROGRAM ORDERED TO BE PERFORMED BY THE PUBLIC
WORKS DIRECTOR PURSUANT TO THE CODE 706.9 AND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE CHAPTER 80 THE COSTS BEING PAID FOR BY THE
CITY AND COUNTY OUT OF A REVOLVING FUND SCHEDULE
PURSUANT TO A MOTION NUMBER M 20 6-037 APPROVED ON APRIL 14TH
2026 AND ITEM 22 CONTAINS THE REPORT OF THE ASSESSMENT COSTS
WHICH WILL BE DELIVERED IN JUST A MOMENT.
>> AND YOU KNOW WHAT I THREW FOR A LOOP, MADAM CLERK I'M
SORRY YOU CAN CALL ITEMS 23 AND 20 FOR THE SECOND SPECIAL
ORDER AS WELL. >> YES, THE SECOND SPECIAL
ORDER WAS SCHEDULED PURSUANT TO A MOTION NUMBER M 20 6-038
APPROVED ON APRIL 14TH 2026 FOR A HEARING TO CONSIDER
OBJECTIONS TO A REPORT OF ASSESSMENT COSTS CONTAINED
IN ITEM 24 SUBMITTED BY THE DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC WORKS FOR
INSPECTION AND OR REPAIR OF BLIGHTED PROPERTIES ORDERED
THROUGH THE ACCELERATED SIDEWALK ABATEMENT PROGRAM TO
BE PERFORMED BY THE DIRECTOR PURSUANT TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE
CODE CHAPTER 80 AND COSTS THEREOF HAVING BEEN PAID FOR BY
THE CITY AND COUNTY OUT OF THE BLIGHT ABATEMENT FUND
COLLEAGUES WE ARE NOW SITTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE FOR
THESE TO HEARINGS ON THE REPORT OF ASSESSMENT COSTS FOR THE
SIDEWALK INSPECTION REPAIR PROGRAM AND THE ACCELERATED
SIDEWALK ABATEMENT PROGRAM AND THESE HEARINGS ARE NOW OPEN
AND WE WILL BEGIN BY HEARING FROM PUBLIC WORKS.
>> WELCOME. GOOD AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT,
PRESIDENT MANDOLIN AND MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
MY NAME IS RUDY CHUNG AND I AM APPEARING ON BEHALF OF SAN
FRANCISCO PUBLIC WORKS CODE ENFORCEMENT FOR THE SIDEWALK
INSPECTION AND REPAIR PROGRAM AND THE ACCELERATED SIDEWALK
ABATEMENT PROGRAM. >> I'LL BE PRESENTING ON BOTH
AGENDA ITEMS 21 AND 23 FOR EFFICIENCY.
UNDER BOTH PROGRAMS PURSUANT TO STATE HIGHWAY CODE 5611
AND MUNICIPAL PUBLIC WORKS CODE SECTION 706 THE PROPERTY OWNER
IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE REPAIR AND MAINTENANCE OF THE SIDEWALK
ADJACENT TO THEIR PROPERTY AGENDA ITEM 21 FOR THE SIDEWALK
INSPECTION AND REPAIR PROGRAM OR COLLOQUIALLY KNOWN AS SERP
IS A PROACTIVE SIDEWALK INSPECTION AND REPAIR PROGRAM
DESIGNED TO INSPECT ALL SIDEWALKS IN SAN FRANCISCO ON A
25 YEAR ROLLING BASIS WE INSPECT AND NOTIFY PROPERTY
OWNERS AND OTHER ENTITIES WHEN DEFECTS ARE FOUND THAT NEED TO
BE REPAIRED. THE PROGRAM IS DESIGNED TO MAKE
IT EASIER FOR PROPERTY OWNERS TO COMPLETE THOSE REPAIRS BY
PROVIDING A CITY CONTRACTOR WHICH THEY CAN USE OR THEY HAVE
THE OPTION OF USING A PRIVATE CONTRACTOR AND MAKING THE
REPAIRS THEMSELVES. WHEN PROPERTY OWNERS ELECT TO
HAVE THE CITY CONTRACTOR MAKE THE REPAIRS OR WHEN NO RESPONSE
IS RECEIVED AND THE REQUISITE REPAIRS HAVE NOT BEEN MADE
WITHIN THE TIME SPECIFIED, THE CITY WILL SEE THAT THE REPAIRS
ARE MADE AND THEN INVOICE THE PROPERTY OWNERS ACCORDINGLY.
AND IN INSTANCES WHERE THESE BILLS GO UNPAID OR INSTANCES
WHERE THE PROPERTY OWNERS ELECT TO HAVE THE COST OF REPAIRS
PLACE ON THEIR PROPERTY TAXES WE SUBMIT THE LINES TO THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR APPROVAL AND INCLUSION ON THE
ANNUAL TAX ROLL SINCE THE LAST HEARING IN MAY OF 2020 FOR 207
THE INVOICES HAVE BEEN ISSUED TO PROPERTY OWNERS BETWEEN
JANUARY OF 2024 TO JANUARY OF 2026 AND 244 OR 90.3% WERE PAID
A TOTAL OF 26 UNPAID INVOICES WERE INITIALLY SUBMITTED FOR
YOUR CONSIDERATION AS OF 11 A.M. TODAY, 20 INVOICES
TOTALING $35,890 WERE REMOVED FROM THE ORIGINAL LIST THROUGH
PAYMENTS MADE IN RECENT WEEKS. 19 OF THE 20 INVOICES WERE PAID
. ONE PAYMENT PLAN WAS REQUESTED
AND GRANTED. THEREFORE THE REPORT WE ARE
SUBMITTING FOR YOUR CONSIDERATION HAS SIX INVOICES
TOTALING $23,121.28 INCLUDING THE TOTAL PERCENT
ADMINISTRATIVE FEE. REGARDING AGENDA ITEM 20 THREE
FOR THE ACCELERATED SIDEWALK ABATEMENT PROGRAM IS MORE SITE
SPECIFIC, SPECIFIC AND DESIGNED TO EXPEDITE REPAIRS OF HIGH
PRIORITY LOCATIONS AS WELL AS ADDRESS OUTSTANDING NOTICES TO
REPAIR AGAIN WE INSPECT AND NOTIFY PROPERTY OWNERS
AND OTHER ENTITIES WHEN DEFECTS NEED TO BE REPAIRED IF THEY
FAIL TO DO SO WITHIN THE ALLOTTED 30 DAYS A NOTICE OF
VIOLATION IS ISSUED WITH THE REQUIREMENT TO MAKE THE REPAIRS
WITHIN 15 DAYS AND AN ASSOCIATED BLIGHT FEE
IN ACCORDANCE WITH ADMINISTRATIVE CODE SECTION 80
IF THE DEPARTMENT MAKES REPAIRS AND THE PROPERTY OWNERS BEHALF
AND THEY FAIL TO PAY OR ELECT TO HAVE THE COSTS PUT ON THEIR
PROPERTY TAXES WE SUBMIT FOR IT TO BE ADDED TO THE TAX ROLL FOR
THIS YEAR THE PROPERTIES ON THE REMAINING LIST HAVE BEEN
ASSESSED THE BLIGHT FEE ONLY SINCE THE LAST HEARING AND MAY
OF 2024 UP UNTIL FEBRUARY OF 20 2650 INVOICES WERE ISSUED TO
PROPERTY OWNERS 17 HAVE BEEN PAID LEAVING A TOTAL OF 34
UNPAID INVOICES THAT WERE ORIGINALLY SUBMITTED FOR YOUR
CONSIDERATION AS OF 11 A.M. TODAY, 19 INVOICES TOTALING
$7,519 WERE REMOVED FROM THE ORIGINAL LIST IN THE RECENT
WEEKS 12 OF THOSE 19 HAVE BEEN PAID.
SEVEN OF THE 19 INVOICES HAVE BEEN WAIVED.
THOSE ADDRESSES INCLUDE 525 SEVENTH AVENUE 6 OR 4 WALLER
STREET 431 CASTRO STREET 1741 TERRIBLE STREET 7 OR 8 ELLIS
STREET AND TWO INVOICES FOR 571 NEVADA STREET.
THEREFORE WE ARE SUBMITTING THE REMAINING 15 INVOICES TOTALING
$6,647.20 INCLUDING THE 12% ADMINISTRATIVE FEE.
IT IS HERE THAT THE DEPARTMENT REQUESTS THE BOARD'S APPROVAL
OF BOTH LISTS FOR AGENDA ITEM 22 AND 24.
WELL, I'M AVAILABLE FOR ANY QUESTIONS YOU HAVE AND I DON'T
SEE ANY COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES SO THANK YOU.
WE WILL NOW OPEN THESE ITEMS FOR PUBLIC COMMENT.
IF YOU ARE A MEMBER OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK
ON ITEMS 21 THROUGH 24 THE LEAN MATTERS MATTERS.
YOU MAY COME UP TO THE PODIUM OR LINE UP ON THE ON YOUR RIGHT
MY MY LEFT IF YOU'RE HERE FOR THESE ITEMS THAT DO NOT WANT TO
PROVIDE PUBLIC TESTIMONY YOU WILL HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO
SPEAK WITH PUBLIC WORKS STAFF OUTSIDE THE CHAMBER TO RESOLVE
YOUR ISSUE. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW OPEN.
ALL SPEAKERS WILL BE ALLOTTED TWO MINUTES TO PROVIDE YOUR
COMMENTS. MADAM CLERK WILL YOU PLEASE
CALL THE FIRST SPEAKER WELCOME WELCOME COME TO THE PODIUM SIR.
>> THANK YOU FOR ALLOWING ME TO BE HERE.
MY NAME IS BORIS FORDHAM AND YOU TRY TO SPEAK CLOSER
CLOSER TO THE MICROPHONE, PLEASE.
MY NAME IS BORDERS FOOD AND I'M THE OWNER OF FIVE ON FOR
VISITATION. FIRST OF ALL ON THIS LIST THIS
PROPERTY TWICE ON THE LIST. I HAVE NO IDEA WHY BUT I'M
TRYING TO BUILD IT HERE IN THIS BUILDING FOR LAST SIX YEARS I
APPLIED THROUGH IDBI THROUGH EVERY DEPARTMENT WHICH IS AS I
HEARD IT'S VERY BUREAUCRATIC. SEE TO SOMEBODY COMING HERE
AND I WENT TO DUBAI THERE'S NO WAY TO GO THROUGH AND SPEAK TO
SOMEONE BECAUSE ALL THESE PEOPLE WORK FROM HOME.
THERE'S NO SINGLE POINT OF CONTACT AND THE LAST I KNOW THE
PROJECT IS BEING HELD BY REQUEST TO PUT THE THREE WHICH
IS ON THE REVISION NUMBER FOR FIRST THREE REVISION THEY WERE
OKAY TO TAKE THE FEES INSTEAD OF THREE AND WHEN I PROVIDED
THE PICTURE TO TWO PEOPLE WHO REQUESTED THE THREE BECAUSE
THERE'S NO WAY TO PUT THE THREE IN FRONT OF THE BUILDING
BECAUSE THERE'S A BUS STOP ELECTRICAL POLE AND DRIVEWAY
AND THE DEPARTMENT IS NOT REPLYING SO I HAVE NO CLUE
WHERE TO GET FROM HERE BECAUSE IF YOU GO TO DUBAI THIS SAYS
WELL WE DON'T HAVE ANYBODY FOR YOU TO SPEAK SEND EMAIL WHEN
YOU SEND EMAIL THE PEOPLE ARE NOT REPLYING BUT YOU DO HAVE
PEOPLE WHO WILL HAVE TIME TO GO AND GIVE ME A FINE WHICH IS THE
WORK WHICH THEY REQUESTED ME TO DO HAVE TO BE REDONE BECAUSE
ACCORDING TO THEIR NOTES I HAVE TO CUT REMOVE THE CUT OF THE
CURB SO THAT WHAT IT IS THAT'S WHERE I AM WITH THIS BUILDING.
OKAY. THANK YOU SIR.
IF YOU WOULDN'T MIND GOING OVER TO THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE
CHAMBER, WOULD YOU? >> CHUNG WILL YOU AND YOUR TEAM
SIGNAL TO THOSE INDIVIDUALS WHO WOULD LIKE ASSISTANCE TO
NEGOTIATE WITH YOU JUST GET THEIR ATTENTION AND DIRECT THEM
TO GO INTO THE HALLWAY PLEASE. ALL RIGHT.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. THANK YOU.
GOOD AFTERNOON, SUPERVISORS. SAN FRANCISCO.
MY NAME IS STARCHILD. I'M CHAIR OF THE LIBERTARIAN
PARTY OF SAN FRANCISCO LP ASPHAUG AND I FIND THIS WHOLE
EXERCISE AND SIDEWALK INSPECTION REPREHENSIBLE.
THERE'S A BACKLOG OF COMPLAINTS THAT PEOPLE HAVE ACTUALLY
SUBMITTED TO THE CITY OF PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE INCLUDING
SIDEWALKS THAT NEED REPAIRING. I THINK IT'S RIDICULOUS FOR THE
CITY GOVERNMENT TO BE INSTEAD OF ADDRESSING THAT BACKLOG
AND THE THINGS THAT PEOPLE HAVE ACTUALLY BROUGHT TO THEIR
ATTENTION THAT NEED FIXING TO BE GOING OUT AND DOING
INSPECTIONS AND THEN BASICALLY NAILING PROPERTY OWNERS FOR
SOMETHING THAT SHOULDN'T EVEN BE THEIR RESPONSIBILITY.
IT'S UNFAIR TO THEM AND IT'S ALSO UNFAIR TO THE PUBLIC
BECAUSE WE'RE TALKING ABOUT PUBLIC SIDEWALKS HERE.
IF YOU MAKE THE PROPERTY OWNERS RESPONSIBLE FOR PAYING FOR
REPAIRS TO THE PUBLIC SIDEWALKS THAT WILL NATURALLY GIVE THEM A
FEELING OF ENTITLEMENT OWNERSHIP OF THOSE SIDEWALKS.
BUT THOSE SIDEWALKS ARE NOT THEIRS.
THEY BELONG TO THE PUBLIC AND IT SHOULDN'T JUST BE THE
PEOPLE WHO HAPPEN TO LIVE NEARBY THAT GET STUCK FOR THE
BILL REPAIRING THEM. AGAIN, THIS ENCOURAGES AN
ENTITLEMENT AND SENSE OF OWNERSHIP AND THEN THEY FEEL
LIKE THEY HAVE THE RIGHT TO CONTROL THOSE SIDEWALKS
AND KEEP OTHER PEOPLE OFF THEM OR OUT OF THE AREA OR WHATEVER
IT IS CREATES MORE NIMBYISM. AND WHY DOESN'T THE CITY
GOVERNMENT JUST ADDRESS THE PROBLEMS THAT HAVE ALREADY BEEN
REPORTED BY THE PUBLIC OF THINGS THAT NEED FIXING?
I KNOW THERE'S A BACKLOG FOR THAT.
IF YOU CHECKED THERE'S PROBABLY A VERY LONG LIST OF STREETS
AND OTHER THINGS THAT NEED REPAIRING.
I THINK THIS INSPECTION PROGRAM IS JUST BASICALLY A WAY TO
EXTORT MORE MONEY FROM THE PUBLIC AND PUT IT IN THE CITY
GOVERNMENT COFFERS. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. STARCHILD FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. NOW THIS THIS IS NO GENERAL
PUBLIC WARD MEMBERS. MY NAME IS RICHARD SD PETERSON.
I WILL BE NOT TALKING ON THE GENERAL COMMENTS BECAUSE THE
COMMENTS I WAS GOING TO MAKE ACTUALLY RELATE TO THE PUBLIC
SIDEWALKS ON THE WAY OVER HERE WALKING FROM MARKET STREET TO
BY THE UP THE THE BUILDING THE EDUCATION BUILDING TO CITY HALL
I WAS NEARLY STRUCK I WAS STRUCK BY ONE UP AND ELECTRIC
SCOOTER AND I WAS NEARLY STRUCK BY TWO BICYCLISTS ON THE
SIDEWALK. NOW IF YOU'RE GOING TO REPAIR
THE SIDEWALKS, ARE YOU GOING TO WEAR OUTSIDE ANY OF THAT MONEY
THAT YOU MAY BE COLLECTING MAYBE FOR ENFORCING THE NO
VEHICLES ON THE SIDEWALK? >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
PLEASE COME ON UP. WELCOME.
HELLO. MY NAME IS WOODY ALBERTINE
AND MRS. RUBY, ONE OF MY MRS. RUBY TRIPPED AND FELL AND DIED
WHILE WALKING HER DOG ON THE MCALLISTER STREET BETWEEN
LAGUNA AND WEBSTER THE SIDEWALK A BRICK WAS LIFTED BY TREE
ROOTS. IT WAS ONLY WHEN SHE DIED FROM
TRIPPING AND FALLING THAT THE SIDEWALK WAS FIXED.
>> TO HAVE THE RESPONSIBILITY OF MAINTENANCE OF SIDEWALK TO
BE ON THE PROPERTY OWNER WHILE THE CITY ENTITY DPW ISSUES
FINES I DON'T BELIEVE THIS ACTION BEST SERVES THE PUBLIC.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON CITY HALL.
I THINK IT'S VERY IMPORTANT TO REMEMBER THAT WE JUST CAME OUT
OF COVID AND A LOT OF BUSINESS OWNERS AND PROPERTY OWNERS
BARELY HAVE ENOUGH MONEY TO MAINTAIN AND KEEP THEIR HOMES
AND I'LL GET IT TAKEN AWAY FROM THE GOVERNMENT.
>> AND I THINK THIS IS A TIME WHERE A LOT OF PEOPLE THAT ARE
BARELY SURVIVING ARE GETTING ATTACKED BY THE GOVERNMENT WITH
MORE TAXES AND FINES WHICH IS WHAT ALL OF YOU DID TODAY JUST
ADD MORE TAXES ON TO THE CITIZENS THAT OWN HOUSES
AND PROPERTY AND AND BUSINESSES AND I JUST THINK IT'S VERY NICE
AND EVERYTHING FOR YOU ALL TO SAY SOMETHING IS FREE BUT
NOTHING IS FREE. YOU'RE TAXING PEOPLE AND YOU
SAY FREE BECAUSE YOU KNOW THAT PEOPLE DON'T HAVE TIME TO PAY
ATTENTION TO POLITICS. YOU ARE ALL VERY INTELLIGENT
PEOPLE. YOU ALL WENT TO VERY GOOD
SCHOOLS. SO DID I.
I ALSO WENT TO VERY GOOD SCHOOLS AND I'M ALSO VERY
INTELLIGENT PERSON BUT I AM NOT A BAD PERSON AND I DON'T
APPRECIATE HOW YOU ALL ARE UP HERE SAYING THIS IS FREE
UNIVERSAL CHILD CARE IS NOT FREE.
>> YOU'RE GOING TO TAX PEOPLE UNLESS YOU GET GRANTS WHICH
MOST OF YOU DON'T. >> AND I DIDN'T SEE A GRANT ON
THIS ON THIS UNIVERSAL MA'AM, THIS IS NOT GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT. >> OKAY.
SO YOU AND ALSO IT'S COMING ON THE SIDEWALK SO LET ME FINISH
ON THE SIDEWALK ALSO I WANT YOU TO MAYBE THINK AND BE A LITTLE
LENIENT ON THE FINES AND MAYBE GIVE THEM MORE TIME OR DON'T DO
IT AT ALL AND THINK OF SOMETHING ELSE BECAUSE LIKE I
SAID, BUSINESSES AND HOMEOWNERS ARE BARELY SURVIVING AND BARELY
KEEPING THEIR HOMES ESPECIALLY IN SAN FRANCISCO.
YES, THE PEOPLE HERE MAKE A LOT OF MONEY BUT EVEN ALL THE MONEY
THEY MAKE THEY STILL CAN'T AFFORD IT.
>> SO PLEASE THINK ABOUT THAT. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
ALL RIGHT. DO WE HAVE ANOTHER SPEAKER WHO
IS ACTUALLY HERE WHO NEEDS TO DISCUSS THE LIENS PURSUANT TO
THEIR PROPERTY? >> WELCOME.
HELLO. MY NAME'S MICHAEL RUSHING.
I'M SPECIFICALLY SPEAKING ABOUT AGENDA ITEM 23.
I WAS ASSESSED A FINE. I DON'T BELIEVE I SHOULD HAVE
BEEN. THERE IS DAMAGE TO THE SIDEWALK
IN FRONT OF MY HOUSE. A LARGE SECTION BECAUSE OF A
TREE ROOTS AND POPPED IT UP. AND THE DPW HAS COME BY PUT
GREEN MARKS ON IT THAT THEY WERE GOING TO FIX.
THEY NEVER FIXED ANYTHING. THEY COME BY AND PUT WHITE
MARKS IN FRONT OF MY DRIVEWAY WHICH ISN'T IN THE PATH OF
TRAVEL. >> THERE'S NO THERE'S NO
TRIPPING HAZARDS. ANYTHING THERE?
BUT NOW THEY SEND ME A BLIGHT. FINE.
AND I JUST DON'T THINK THAT'S RIGHT.
THAT'S ENOUGH. >> THANK YOU, SIR.
ARE YOU GOING TO GO INTO THE HALLWAY AND HAVE A CONVERSATION
WITH THE D P W INSPECTORS? MR. RIGHT, WELCOME.
>> THANKS. THE SIDEWALK INSPECTION IS
ANOTHER EXAMPLE OF POOR SUPERVISION AND MANAGEMENT
AND SHIFTING THE BLAME TO OTHER PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE A THING
TO DO WITH THE PROBLEM. THOSE PROPERTY OWNERS ARE NOT
PLANTING THOSE TREES. THAT'S ROOTS THAT'S CAUSING THE
SIDEWALKS TO BUCKLE AND CAUSES VIOLATIONS AND SAFETY HAZARDS.
YOU ALWAYS SHIFTING THE BLAME TO OTHER PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE
A THING TO DO WITH THE PROBLEM.
THAT'S THE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE CITY AND COUNTY IS SEVEN
GOD SYSCO. YOU'RE THE ONE PLANTING THOSE
TREES ON THAT PROPERTY AND NOW YOU'RE TRYING TO CHARGE THE
PROPERTY OWNERS TO PAY FOR IT. THIS IS THE RESULT OF PEOPLE
PACKING UP AND LEAVING. THE CITY HAS LOST $25 BILLION
IN REVENUE BECAUSE OF THIS TECHNIQUE THAT YOU APPLIED TO
NOT ONLY HIGH INCOME MULTI MILLIONAIRES AND BILLIONAIRES
BUT NOW YOU'RE DOING IT TO PROPERTY OWNERS THAT BARELY
SURVIVED WITH A HIGH PAYING JOB AND YOU'RE TAXING THEM.
SO FOR YOU TO SIT UP THERE AND PENALIZE THEM FOR FUNDS
THAT WERE RESPONSIBLE BY THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC WORKS
AND SHIFT THE BLAME OVER THERE IS AS RIDICULOUS AS DISGUST.
AND IT IS SCANDALOUS. SO FOR THAT CONTINUATION WHICH
IS A PATTERN WHICH DEMONSTRATES THROUGHOUT THE ADMINISTRATION
WHENEVER IT IS A NEGATIVE CASH FLOW, A MULTIMILLION BILLION
DOLLAR NEGATIVE CASH FLOW IS ALWAYS BECAUSE OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO'S ADMINISTRATION ALWAYS.
AND THEN YOU WANT OTHER PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE A THING TO DO
IT WANT OTHER PEOPLE TO DO IT. I REPEAT WE HAVE LOST A MINIMUM
OF $25 BILLION IN TAX REVENUE BECAUSE OF THE PEOPLE THAT YOU
USE THIS TECHNIQUE ON PACKED UP AND LEFT THE CITY.
>> ALL RIGHT. CAN WE HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE? THIS IS SPECIFIC TO SIDEWALK
ABATEMENT. YES.
YOU ACCELERATED SIDEWALK REPAIR?
YES. WELCOME.
THANK YOU. ELISA ROCHELLE HERE, RESIDENT
OF BABY BONUS POINT DISTRICT TEN.
>> THE SIDEWALKS THAT WE'RE TALKING ABOUT.
I FELL ONTO A METAL GATE BECAUSE OF THESE THINGS.
>> THE ROOFS OF THE SIDEWALK STICKING UP AND YES, THE GRAY
EXCUSE ME THE GREEN SPRAY PAINT WAS THERE FOR MONTHS.
>> THERE WERE TWO WOMEN WHO ARE RESIDENTS OF THE BUILDING WHERE
I TRIPPED AND FELL AND THEY WERE SAYING THAT IT'S BEEN LIKE
THAT FOR MONTHS AND IT'S VERY IT'S INCHES HIGH.
>> AND SO THE FOLKS WHO OWN AND WHO ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE
BUILDING HAS NOT REPAIRED IT. >> I'M NOT SURE WHEN THE GREEN
SPRAY COMES WHO'S RESPONSIBLE FOR THAT?
>> BUT I BELIEVE IT'S THE CITY THAT HAS COME OUT AND DID THAT
AND NOTHING HAD BEEN DONE. I WILL GO BACK AND CHECK
AND SEE WHAT THE OUTCOME IS AS OF YET.
LAST TIME I WENT BY THERE THERE WAS SOME WORK BEING DONE BUT
NOT ON THE EXACT SPOT WHERE THE TREE ROOTS WERE COMING UP
AND IT WAS A LITTLE BIT DOWN. >> SO THAT WHOLE BLOCK IS KIND
OF MESSED UP BETWEEN THIRD AND CASITA ON THE EXCUSE ME
QUESADA AND PALU ON THIRD STREET.
AND SO WHO'S RESPONSIBLE FOR THAT?
>> WHO'S GOING TO PAY FOR THE FACT THAT I WAS OUT OF WORK FOR
A WEEK? I HAD TO GET CHILD CARE FOR A
WEEK BECAUSE I WAS UNABLE TO CARE FOR MY CHILD.
>> SO HOW DOES THAT GET TAKEN CARE OF?
AND I HAVE CALLED 311 AND SUBMITTED THAT AND I ALSO
HAVE THE CITY FORM THAT NEEDS TO BE SUBMITTED FOR A
COMPLAINT. >> SO JUST PUT THAT ON THE
RECORD. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS
AND IF YOU COULD GO OUTSIDE TO THE HALLWAY TO REPORT THAT
INFORMATION TO THE DPW SIDEWALK INSPECTOR THAT WOULD BE
HELPFUL. >> THANK YOU.
DO WE HAVE ANOTHER SPEAKER WHO HAS A LINE THAT THEY WOULD LIKE
TO DISCUSS WITH THE BOARD? PLEASE COME FORWARD.
OTHERWISE THIS WILL BE OUR LAST SPEAKER.
>> JUST IN GENERAL I THINK THE SIDEWALKS ARE TOO HIGH.
THEY'RE TOO HIGH AND I FELL ALMOST A COUPLE OF TIMES
BECAUSE I HAD TO BE EXTRA CAREFUL WHEN I'M YOU KNOW I GOT
TO LIFT MY PUT UP LIKE THIS JUST TO GO UP THERE, YOU KNOW
WHAT I MEAN? MAKE SURE THAT I CAN'T WALK
LIKE NORMALLY ON THE SIDEWALKS BE GET CROSSING THE STREETS.
>> YOU KNOW WHAT I MEAN? BUT UM, I JUST THINK THE
SIDEWALKS ARE TOO HIGH, YOU KNOW?
AND I'M ALMOST FELL A COUPLE OF TIMES AND THE PILE HOLES ARE
WOULD YOU CONSIDER THOSE POTHOLES BREAKING AWAY THE
CEMENT? >> I DON'T KNOW.
I THINK IS SOMETHING GOING ON UNDER SAN FRANCISCO THAT'S
CAUSING THESE REOCCURRING ISSUES WHEN THEY GET FIXED?
YOU KNOW, SO I THINK IT'S SOMETHING GOING ON MORE SO
GOING ON BENEATH THE SURFACE OF WHY THESE REOCCURRING ISSUES
KEEP COMING UP ABOUT THE SIDEWALKS IS MY OPINION.
>> ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
AND ON ON THESE ITEMS WE'LL WE'LL BE DOING REAL PUBLIC
COMMENT ITEMS 21 AND 23 HAVE BEEN HEARD HAVE BEEN HEARD
AND ARE NOW FILED. >> UM AND FOR ANYONE WHO WANTS
TO SPEAK WITH PUBLIC WORKS STAFF REGARDING THE ASSESSMENT
ON THEIR PROPERTY YOU SHOULD GO OUT INTO THE HALLWAY NOW STAFF
IS OUT THERE. THEY WILL TALK TO YOU ABOUT
YOUR ASSESSMENT AND THEN WE WILL COME BACK TO ITEMS 22
AND 24 OR LATER IN THE MEETING .
>> MADAM CLERK COULD WE GO TO OUR LAST 3 P.M. SPECIAL COURT
SPECIAL ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER 25 YES.
>> ITEM 25 SCHEDULED PURSUANT TO A MOTION M 20 DASH 125
APPROVED ON SEPTEMBER 15TH 2020.
ITEM 25 IS A PUBLIC HEARING OF THE BOARD TO CONVENE A
COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TO HEAR AND RECEIVE UPDATES ON THE
PROGRESS AND IMPLEMENTATION STATUS OF THE UNITED STATES
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE RECOMMENDING TIONS PERTAINING
TO REFORMS WITHIN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT.
>> SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT, MADAM AND COLLEAGUES
THERE IS NOT MUCH NEW INFORMATION TO REPORT SO WE'RE
I'M REQUESTING THAT WE CONTINUE THIS ITEM TO NOVEMBER 10TH
2026. THERE IS A MOTION TO CONTINUE
THE ITEM TO WHAT DATE? NOVEMBER 10TH.
NOVEMBER 10TH. IS THERE A SECOND SECOND SECOND
BY CHEN AND THEN I BELIEVE THAT BEFORE WE TAKE THAT MOTION WE
NEED TO TAKE PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE CONTINUANCE.
SO THIS IS JUST PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE CONTINUANCE OF ITEM 25
TO NOVEMBER 10TH. IF THERE ARE ANY INDIVIDUALS
YOU'D LIKE TO PROVIDE COMMENT WITH THE UNDERSTANDING OF THIS
MATTER WILL BE CONTINUED. COME ON UP AND LINE UP
SUPERVISORS YOU MAY NOT KNOW ABOUT COPS COMMUNITY ORIENTED
POLICING SERVICES THAT'S WHAT WE ARE TALKING ABOUT WHICH WE
ATTENDED THESE MEETINGS BECAUSE OF THE KILLINGS AND SHOOTINGS
AND WE NEED DUE DILIGENCE FROM THE POLICE AND THE VARIOUS TYPE
OF COMMITTEES THEY FORMED WHO REALLY DON'T CARE ABOUT THE
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE THAT WERE HARMED AND HOW WE HAD TO GO
ATTEND THIS LONG MEETINGS ONLY FOR SOMETHING TO BE ANNOUNCED
ON AN AGENDA LIKE THIS AND SAY ALL RIGHT, LET'S CONTINUE IT
CONTINUE ABOUT WHAT THIS CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO IS
GOING TO THE HOGS. >> THESE ARE RECOMMENDATIONS
WHICH NOW ARE NEUTRALIZED IN WASHINGTON DC.
THERE IS NO REAL DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE.
SO COPS HAD SOME FUNDS. WE HAVE THE PROGRAMS THAT THE
STATE HAS CONTRIBUTED TO IT AND I WANT TO KNOW WHICH OF
YOUR SUPERVISORS ATTENDED THE MEETINGS AND WHAT THE DO YOU
KNOW ABOUT COPS AND WHAT THE HAVE YOU DONE TO SAVE THOSE
PEOPLE OR HELP THOSE PEOPLE WHO ARE HARMED?
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU, MR. DECOSTA MR.
RIGHT YOU AND THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MADE THE COMMENT
YOU WANT TO THANK THE VOTERS. THE VOTERS VOTE IS ALWAYS AN
ACCEPTED AND FUNDS THAT WE VOTED FOR IS ALWAYS SPENT
AND ENJOYED BY PEOPLE IN HIGH INCOME BRACKETS.
>> FOR EXAMPLE PROPOSITION C WE VOTED FOR PROPOSITION C WHICH
WAS A MEASURE TO HELP THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE WHO ARE
ECONOMICALLY DISADVANTAGED. HOMELESS WERE A COMBINATION OF
BOTH MENTAL AND PHYSICAL DISABILITIES AND OUT IN THE
STREET AND PEOPLE IN WHEELCHAIRS.
NOW FAST FORWARD TO THE PRESENT DATE YOU GET THE MAYOR AND I
AGREE I DON'T AGREE IF THIS BOARD GOES ALONG WELL WITH THE
MAYOR IS DOING IS USING FUNDS FROM THAT VOTED PROPOSAL
AND AGREED TO AND VOTED ON TO BE ENJOYED BY PEOPLE IN HIGH
INCOME BRACKETS DOES MAKE MAKING 200,000 TO $230,000 A
YEAR TO PAY FOR THEIR CHILD CARE.
WHY THEY MAKE MAKING THAT MUCH MONEY PER YEAR THOSE FUNDS FOR
PROPOSITION C IS SUPPOSED TO BE FOR THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE
YOU DEMONSTRATING AGAIN THAT YOU JUST OPPOSITE OF ROBIN HOOD
ROBIN HOOD STEALS FROM THE RICH AND GIVES FROM THE POOR.
WHAT YOU'RE DOING IS STEALING MONEY FROM THE PROGRAMS FOR THE
POOR AND GIVING IT AND BENEFITING IT FOR THE RICH.
>> IT'S UNCONSTITUTIONAL, IT'S UNETHICAL AND IS DISGUSTING
AND IT'S DISCRIMINATION NOW ALSO THIS $1.5 BILLION THAT YOU
WERE DEALT WITH, YOU GOT NOBODY TO BLAME BUT YOURSELVES.
POOR SUPERVISION AND MANAGEMENT OF THE TAXPAYERS MONEY THERE TO
. AND THEN ON TOP OF THAT YOU
ALSO LOST TWO POINT FIVE B BILLION STRIKE THAT $25 BILLION
IN TAX REVENUE BECAUSE THE BIG COMPANIES PACKING UP
AND LEAVING. >> SO THAT'S A TOTAL A 20 $6.5
BILLION THAT YOU WASTED AND ABOUT YOU CELEBRATE
IN CELEBRATING ST PATRICK'S DAY PARADE ST PATRICK'S DAY MADE
SEVEN POINT $5 BILLION MILLION DOLLARS THAT DAY.
>> MR.. BUT THIS IS SPECIFIC THIS IS
NOT GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENTS OR I THOUGHT YOU SAID GENERAL
PUBLIC CAN THIS IS SPECIFIC TO THE UPDATES ON THE PROGRESS OF
THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT
JUSTICE RECOMMENDATIONS? OH WELL YOU SHOULD HAVE TOLD ME
THAT. >> I THINK YOU MR. RIGHT MR.
QUINN CHANDLER AND SPEAKING OF THE DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE
AND FRANCISCO DE CASCA SPOKE VERY WELL.
I WENT TO FRANCISCO THE COSCO WHEN MY SON WAS MURDERED
CONCERNING THE DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE AND I STILL DID NOT GET
ANY JUSTICE. I HAD TO BE THE ONE TO FIGHT
FOR THE INVESTIGATION AND FOR THE ARREST OF THE MURDER OF MY
SON JELANI JAY MASTER JOHN MARIN DE DE SAN FRANCISCO
QUADRUPLE HOMICIDE AND I AM GOING TO SPEAK AT THE END WITH
GENERAL BUT THERE IS NO JUSTICE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
THE POLITICAL SYSTEM HAS FAILED THE COMMON PEOPLE AND THE
DISENFRANCHIZED AND IT'S GOING TO BE A TIME THAT MANY OF YOU
THAT KNOW THIS TO BE TRUE YOU'RE GOING TO PAY A PRICE
BECAUSE WHAT YOU DO YOU HAVE US COME HERE AND SPEAK BEHIND
THESE WALLS AND ACTUALLY NOTHING HAPPENS.
>> MANY OF YOUR FIGHT IS FOR YOUR OWN CONSTITUENTS AND I
KNOW THAT AND THE DISRESPECT THIS MIGHT BE OFF BUT THE
DISRESPECT OF YOU GIVEN THE BLACK NATION A REPARATIONS THAT
HAS TO DO WITH A GO FUND ME IS AN INSULT AND I'M A LEAVE YOU
WITH THIS. WHAT YOU PUT OUT IS WHAT YOU
DON'T GET BACK BECAUSE YOU HAVING US BEG YOU FOR SOMETHING
THAT YOU KNOW WAS RIGHTFULLY VOTED AT THIS AT THIS THIS THIS
THIS EXCUSE ME THIS CHAMBER HERE.
SO I'M GOING TO COME AND SPEAK AT THE END.
BUT IT'S NO JUSTICE IN THIS IN THIS STATE AND IS SURE NO
JUSTICE IN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND IT'S GOING TO BE A
TIME THAT EVERY ONE OF YOU IS GOING TO REAP WHAT YOU SOW.
THANK YOU, MISS CHANDLER STARCHILD THANK YOU, MADAM
CLERK. >> GOOD AFTERNOON AGAIN.
>> MEMBERS OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS SAN FRANCISCO.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT THE DELAY IS BUT THIS ITEM KEEPS GETTING
CONTINUED OVER AND OVER AGAIN. WHY IS IT SO HARD FOR LOCAL
POLICE TO COMPLY WITH THE RECOMMENDATIONS OF THE JUSTICE
DEPARTMENT? VERY IRONIC NOW THAT WE HAVE
YOU KNOW, OF COURSE THE JUSTICE DEPARTMENT UNDER THE CURRENT
ADMINISTRATION WHICH IS MORE ANTI LIBERTY AND MORE WILLING
TO TOLERATE POLICE ABUSE IN A POSITION OF TELLING THE LOCAL
POLICE DEPARTMENT THAT THEY ARE OUT OF LINE AND IF THE LOCAL
POLICE DEPARTMENT WHICH YOU CONTROL AND THE MAYOR CONTROLS
WOULD GET ITS ACT TOGETHER, WE WOULDN'T BE IN THIS
EMBARRASSING SITUATION OF HAVING THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION
LOOKING OVER OUR SHOULDERS TO TELL THE LOCAL POLICE HOW TO DO
THEIR JOBS. ONE REASON IS THAT THEY DON'T
HAVE ANY COMPETITION. BACK IN THE 1990S AND BEFORE
THEN ACTUALLY SINCE BEFORE THE SPD WAS CREATED THERE WAS A
GROUP CALLED THE PATROL SPECIALS WHO WERE BASICALLY
LIKE PRIVATE SECURITY GUARDS EXCEPT THEY COULD MOVE AROUND
FROM LOCATION TO LOCATION. THEY HAD BEATS AND PEOPLE HIRED
THE MERCHANT GROUPS HIRE THEM AND OTHER PEOPLE HIRE THEM TO
PROVIDE MORE EXTRA SECURITY AND COMMUNITY ORIENTED POLICING
THAT PEOPLE ACTUALLY WANTED IN THE CASTRO THERE'S A PLAQUE
DEDICATED TO ONE OF THEM JANE WARNER AT THE CORNER OF MARKET
AND 17TH WHO WAS A LONG TIME PATROL SPECIAL OFFICER INJURED
IN THE LINE OF DUTY AND A MUCH LOVED BY THE COMMUNITY.
I THINK YOU SHOULD TRY TO BRING BACK THE PATROL SPECIALS,
PROVIDE SOME COMPETITION TO THE POLICE DEPARTMENT, SHOW THEM
WHAT GOOD POLICING LOOKS LIKE. HELP THEM UNDERSTAND THE
IMPORTANCE OF CIVIL LIBERTIES AND RESPECTING THE RIGHTS OF
MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC. THEN WE WANT TO HAVE THAT TRUMP
ADMINISTRATION AND OTHERS LOOKING OVER OUR SHOULDERS
IN THIS EMBARRASSING FASHION. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. HOLD YOUR APPLAUSE PLEASE.
ARE THERE ANY OTHER SPEAKERS WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE RECOMMENDATIONS PERTAINING TO
REFORMS IN THE POLICE DEPARTMENT?
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT AND PUBLIC COMMENT ON THE CONTINUANCE IS
NOW CLOSED. SUPERVISOR WALTON HAS MADE MUST
CONTINUE THIS HEARING TO NOVEMBER 10TH.
IT HAS BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MOTION TO CONTINUE
ITEM 25 TO NOVEMBER 10TH SUPERVISOR WANG WONG EYES
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD
ABSENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I THERE ARE NINE EYES AND THE
HEARING IS CONTINUED TO NOVEMBER 10TH.
>> ALL RIGHT MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO COMMITTEE REPORTS PLEASE
CALL ITEM NUMBER 26 ITEM 26 WAS CONSIDERED BY THE RULES
COMMITTEE AT A REGULAR MEETING ON MONDAY MAY 11TH.
IT WAS RECOMMENDED AS AMENDED AS A COMMITTEE REPORT WITH THE
SAME TITLE IT NOW READS ITEM 26 ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE THE DOWNTOWN HOSPITALITY ZONE
IN MULTIPLE AREAS BOUNDED BY FIFTH STREET FROM FOLSOM STREET
TO MARKET STREET SERIAL MAGNON STREET FROM MARKET TO EDDY
STREET EDDY STREET FROM CIRCLE MAGNIN STREET TO MASON STREET
MASON STREET FROM EDDY STREET TO ELLIS STREET ELLIS STREET
FROM MASON STREET TO TAYLOR STREET TAYLOR STREET FROM ELLIS
STREET TO POST STREET POST STREET FROM TAYLOR STREET TO
MASON STREET MASON STREET FROM POST STREET TO BUSH STREET BUSH
STREET FROM MASON MASON STREET TO KEARNY STREET KEARNY STREET
FROM BUSH STREET TO MARKET STREET MARKET STREET FROM THIRD
STREET TO SECOND STREET SECOND STREET FROM MARKET STREET TO
FOLSOM STREET AND FOLSOM STREET FROM SECOND STREET TO FIFTH
STREET. AND TO AFFIRMED THE PLANNING
DEPARTMENT'S DETERMINATION UNDER THE CALIFORNIA
ENVIRONMENTAL QUALITY ACT SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU
PRESIDENT AMENDMENT BEFORE WE VOTE I JUST WANTED TO GIVE A
BIT OF CONTEXT ON THIS. THIS IS THE LOCAL
IMPLEMENTATION OF A STATE LAW THAT WOULD ALLOW FOR UP TO 20
NEW LIQUOR LICENSES SPECIFICALLY DESIGNATED FOR
DOWNTOWN SAN FRANCISCO WITHIN A HOSPITALITY ZONE.
THE BOUNDARIES AS READ BY OUR CLERK WHICH IS ROUGHLY SPLIT
BETWEEN MY DISTRICT AND DISTRICT SIX WITH
SUPERVISOR DORSEY. THIS STATE LAW WAS INTRODUCED
OVER A YEAR AGO IN FEBRUARY 2025, THEN SIGNED INTO LAW BY
GOVERNOR NEWSOM IN OCTOBER 2025.
AND WHAT WE'RE LOOKING AT HERE TODAY IS THE LOCAL
IMPLEMENTATION OF THAT SINCE THE SIGNING BY GOVERNOR NEWSOM
IN OCTOBER OF 2025, THE MAYOR'S OFFICE HAS BEEN ENGAGING WITH
KEY STAKEHOLDERS INCLUDING THE GOLDEN GATE RESTAURANT
ASSOCIATION, UNION SQUARE ALLIANCE THROUGH YERBA BUENA
PARTNERSHIP AND INDEPENDENT BAR OWNERS AND WE HAVE BEEN PART OF
THOSE CONVERSATIONS AS WELL BASED ON THE FEEDBACK RECEIVED
FROM BAR OWNERS, AN AMENDMENT WAS MADE AND RULES COMMITTEE
YESTERDAY TO REDUCE THE NUMBER OF TOTAL LICENSES AVAILABLE
THROUGH THIS PROGRAM FROM 20 TO 15.
THE STATE LAW DICTATES THAT A MAXIMUM OF TEN LICENSES CAN BE
GRANTED IN THE FIRST YEAR WITHIN FIVE MORE AVAILABLE
IN THE SECOND YEAR. SO THAT WAS THE AMENDMENT MADE
YESTERDAY AND THE FILE IS AS AMENDED BEFORE YOU.
BUT THE FILE WAS ALSO DUPLICATED IN COMMITTEE
YESTERDAY WHICH I THINK IS IMPORTANT AND WILL GIVE US TIME
FOR FURTHER CONSIDERING FURTHER AMENDMENTS.
WE ARE UNDER A TIME CONSTRAINT HERE AS THERE IS A JULY 1ST
DEADLINE IN THE STATE LAW TO HAVE A LOCAL ORDINANCE
IN EFFECT AND I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT WE MEET THAT DEADLINE
AND DO NOT LOSE THIS REALLY IMPORTANT OPPORTUNITY.
SO IT IS MY INTENT TODAY THAT WE PASS THIS AND AGAIN HAVE
THAT DUPLICATED FILE IN COMMITTEE FOR FURTHER
AMENDMENTS. >> THANKS SUPERVISOR JAN THANK
YOU. >> PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN I WILL
BE VOTING IN SUPPORT OF THIS WITH THE KNOWLEDGE THAT THIS
LEGISLATION HAS BEEN DUPLICATED AT COMMITTEE AND THAT THERE'S
AN INTENTION TO AMEND TO MAKE SURE THAT WE HAVE EQUAL PLAYING
FIELD FOR ALL THOSE BUSINESS OWNERS AND SMALL BUSINESSES
THAT HAVE LIQUOR LICENSE AND THAT WE DON'T END UP
SETTING UP A TWO TIER SYSTEM. SO I WILL BE VOTING IN SUPPORT
BUT I ALSO LOOK FORWARD TO THE AMENDED VERSION OR TWO THAT
IT'S TO COME. >> THANK YOU.
CHAIR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT AMENDMENT AND THANK
YOU SUPERVISOR SAUTER FOR SUMMARIZING WHAT HAPPENED
IN THE RULES COMMITTEE YESTERDAY WE HAD A HEFTY
DISCUSSION AGAIN ABOUT MAKING SURE THAT WE PROTECT EXISTING
BUSINESSES AS WE MOVE FORWARD TO DO EVERYTHING WE CAN TO
REVITALIZE THE DOWNTOWN AREA. ALSO JUST WANT TO NOTE THAT WE
WERE NOT HAPPY TO BE PUT UP AGAINST THE GUN AND HAVING TO
MAKE THIS DECISION IN SUCH A SHORT PERIOD OF TIME BECAUSE WE
ARE CAUGHT UP AGAINST THE TIMELINE SO IT'S LIKE WE
SUPPORT IT OR WE DON'T BUT WE DID DUPLICATE THE FILE SO THAT
WE COULD WORK WITH COMMUNITY AND BUSINESSES TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE COME UP WITH SOMETHING THAT WILL NOT TO USE THE TERM
MAKE EVERYBODY HAPPY WOULD MOST CERTAINLY DO EVERYTHING WE CAN
TO SUPPORT FUTURE BUSINESS AND KEEP DOWNTOWN THRIVING BUT
TO MAKE SURE THAT OUR CURRENT BUSINESSES ARE ABLE TO THRIVE
AS WELL. >> SUPERVISOR CHERYL.
ECHOING WHAT MY COLLEAGUE SAID ESPECIALLY SUPERVISOR WALTON.
>> A LITTLE HEAD'S UP A LITTLE EARLIER WOULD HAVE SOLVED A LOT
OF PROBLEMS. I THINK THERE'S BEEN MUCH MORE
NEGOTIATION ON THIS MATTER, MUCH MORE BACK AND FORTH THAN I
AND PROBABLY MY MY COLLEAGUES ON THE RULES COMMITTEE WERE
MADE AWARE OF MY CONVERSATIONS OVER THE LAST 36 HOURS TO 24
HOURS REALLY HAVE MADE ME A LOT MORE COMFORTABLE WITH THE WORK
THAT'S BEEN DONE. >> BUT AT SAME TIME I THINK A
LOT OF THIS COULD HAVE BEEN AVOIDED.
I REALLY DON'T LIKE THE BACK AGAINST THE WALL.
I'M GLAD THAT WE DUPLICATED THE FILE.
I'M GOING TO BE VOTING TO SUPPORT THIS.
I THINK THE WORK THAT'S BEEN DONE SO FAR WAS MUCH MORE
ROBUST THAN I WAS INITIALLY LED TO BELIEVE AND I APPRECIATE
THAT. I'M GLAD THAT'S TRUE.
SO I'LL BE VOTING SUPPORT ON THIS TODAY BUT I'M GLAD WE HAVE
A DUPLICATE FILE AND CONTINUE TO WORK ON THIS.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THIS ITEM AND ITEM 26
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG EYES SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY EYES
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON I
THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS
PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO ROLL CALL FOR
INTRODUCTIONS. >> SUPERVISOR WONG YOUR FIRST
UP TO INTRODUCE NEW BUSINESS SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHAN SUBMIT THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR CHEN SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
COLLEAGUES I'M TODAY INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION
COMMEMORATING THE 140TH ANNIVERSARY OF THE LANDMARK
CIVIL RIGHTS CASE JACOBO V HOPKINS WITH ZERO PRECEDENT TO
SUGGEST THEY MIGHT SUCCEED LEE YOCK AND THE CHINESE SIX
COMPANIES OF SAN FRANCISCO BRAVELY ASSERTED THE PROMISE OF
THE U.S. CONSTITUTION IN 1885 WHEN THEY SUED OVER
DISCRIMINATORY ENFORCEMENT OF A LOCAL LAW.
THAT CASE REMAINS ONE OF THE FOUNDATIONAL EQUAL PROTECTION
PRECEDENTS IN CONSTITUTIONAL LAW AND HAS BEEN CITED
COUNTLESS TIMES IN RULINGS EVER SINCE.
IT WAS ALSO AMONG HISTORY'S FIRST INSTANCES IN WHICH SAN
FRANCISCANS OF PRINCIPLE AND DARING CHALLENGED AN
INJUSTICE AND IN SO DOING CHANGED AMERICA FOR THE BETTER.
IT'S ALSO AMONG THE ENDURING LEGACIES OF SAN FRANCISCO'S
CHINESE COMMUNITY. THE CASE AROSE BECAUSE UNDER A
LAW ENACTED BY THE BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, THE CITY
AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO DENIED NECESSARY PERMITS TO ALL
BUT ONE OF MORE THAN 200 CHINESE LAUNDRIES INCLUDING
YAKS WHILE GRANTING PERMITS TO ALL BUT ONE WHITE OWNED
LAUNDRY. THE CITY DECLINED THE RENEWAL
OF LEE PERMIT DESPITE THE FACT THAT HE HAD OPERATED FOR MORE
THAN TWO DECADES WITH A CLEAN SAFETY RECORD.
HE WAS A FINED AND THEN IMPRISONED FOR REFUSING TO PAY
WHEN HE FILED SUIT IN 1885. HE DID SO ALONG WITH WOLSEY,
ANOTHER SAN FRANCISCO LAUNDRY OPERATOR.
THEY WERE BACKED BY THE CHINESE CONSOLIDATED BENEVOLENT
ASSOCIATION, ALSO KNOWN AS THE CHINESE SIX COMPANIES WHICH
RAISED SOME $20,000 FOR THE CASE.
THAT'S MORE THAN $600,000 IN TODAY'S DOLLARS.
THEIR LEGAL TEAM WAS LED BY AN ALL STAR ATTORNEY NAMED HELM
HALL MCALLISTER WHOSE STATUE STANDS ON THE STREET THAT STILL
BEARS HIS NAME RIGHT OUTSIDE CITY HALL.
THE EQUAL CASE WAS APPEALED ALL THE WAY TO THE U.S. SUPREME
COURT AND ON MAY 10TH, 1886, THE NATION'S HIGHEST COURT
ISSUED AN UNANIMOUS RULING THAT HELD THAT A LAW APPLIED IN A
RACIALLY DISCRIMINATORY MANNER VIOLATED THE CONSTITUTIONAL
GUARANTEE OF EQUAL PROTECTION TO ALL PERSONS CITIZENS OR NOT.
THIS REMAINS A FOUNDATIONAL CASE IN AMERICAN JURISPRUDENCE
AND IT IS PART OF A STILL LARGELY UNDERRECOGNIZED
TRADITION OF LEGAL ACTION BY CHINESE-AMERICAN IMMIGRANTS WHO
FOUGHT DISCRIMINATORY LAWS IN AMERICAN COURTS AT A TIME
WHEN THEY WERE BARRED FROM CITIZENSHIP AND LARGELY
STRIPPED OF POLITICAL POWER. IT IS MORE IMPORTANT NOW THAN
EVER TO CELEBRATE THAT HISTORY AND TO RECOGNIZE THE
ACHIEVEMENTS AND CONTRIBUTIONS OF OUR IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES.
EDUCATION AND PLAYMAKING PLACEMAKING OUR POWERFUL TOOLS
TO HIGHLIGHT AND CELEBRATE HISTORY.
WHICH IS WHY THIS RESOLUTION ALSO SUPPORTS PLACEMAKING AT
THE SITE OF YOUR LAUNDRY IN MY DISTRICT.
AS SOMEONE WHO SPENT MUCH OF MY CAREER AROUND LAWYERS IN THE
CITY ATTORNEY'S OFFICE AS WELL AS THE DISTRICT ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE, I'VE LONG BEEN FAMILIAR WITH THE CASE BUT ONLY LEARNED
RECENTLY THAT THE EQUAL LAUNDRY WAS ACTUALLY LOCATED IN MY
DISTRICT. SO I BELIEVE PLACEMAKING
AND PHYSICAL RECOGNITION NEAR THE SITE WOULD BE WARRANTED.
I WANT TO THANK THE COMMUNITY MEMBERS AND ORGANIZATIONS WHO
ORGANIZED THE EVENT YESTERDAY WHERE WE CELEBRATED THE CASE
AND SPOKE ABOUT THE IMPORTANCE OF RECOGNIZING THIS STORIED
HISTORY. WE WERE JOINED TO BY MY
COLLEAGUES SUPERVISORS RANDLEMAN SAUDER CHAN AND CHEN
WHO ARE CO-SPONSORING THIS RESOLUTION AND I HOPE IT CAN
EARN EVERYONE SUPPORT AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR DORSEY SUPERVISOR
MAHMUD. >> COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M
INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF SENATE BILL 1422
INTRODUCED BY SENATOR MARIA ELENA DURAZO WHICH WOULD
RESTORE FULL SCOPE MEDI-CAL ACCESS FOR UNDOCUMENTED ADULTS
IN CALIFORNIA. >> CALIFORNIA HAS MADE REAL
PROGRESS ON HEALTH COVERAGE. >> WE BROUGHT OUR UNINSURED
RATE DOWN TO ABOUT 6% THROUGH HEALTH FOR ALL EXPANSIONS
GIVING ROUGHLY 1.5 MILLION UNDOCUMENTED CALIFORNIANS
ACCESS TO PREVENTIVE AND PRIMARY CARE.
>> THAT PROGRESS IS NOW AT RISK.
>> THE 20 2526 STATE BUDGET IMPOSED A FREEZE ON MEDI-CAL
ENROLLMENT FOR UNDOCUMENTED ADULTS WHICH IS PROJECTED TO
STRIP COVERAGE FROM OVER 1 MILLION CALIFORNIANS BY 2030.
>> CUTTING PEOPLE OFF FROM MEDI-CAL DOESN'T MAKE THEIR
HEALTH NEEDS DISAPPEAR. >> IT JUST PUSHES THOSE COSTS
ONTO COUNTIES, HOSPITALS AND EMERGENCY ROOMS INCREASING
UNCOMPENSATED CARE AND STRAINING LOCAL PUBLIC
HEALTH SYSTEMS LIKE OURS HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> PREVENTIVE AND PRIMARY CARE SAVES MONEY.
WHEN PEOPLE CAN SEE A DOCTOR REGULARLY.
WE REDUCE AVOIDABLE E.R. VISITS, HOSPITALIZATIONS
AND LONG TERM COSTS TO THE HEALTH CARE SYSTEM.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HAS LONG SERVED AS A PROVIDER OF LAST
RESORT. >> THIS ENROLLMENT FREEZE WILL
DIRECTLY INCREASE THE FISCAL AND SERVICE BURDENS ON OUR
CITY. SB 1422 WOULD SUNSET THIS
ENROLLMENT FREEZE AND RESTORE FULL SCOPE MEDI-CAL BEGINNING
JANUARY 1ST, 2027. A COMMON SENSE INVESTMENT
IN PUBLIC HEALTH AND FISCAL RESPONSIBILITY.
>> UNDOCUMENTED CALIFORNIANS CONTRIBUTE AN ESTIMATED $8.5
BILLION ANNUALLY IN STATE AND LOCAL TAXES.
THEY DESERVE ACCESS TO THE SAME HEALTH CARE THAT KEEPS OUR
COMMUNITIES HEALTHY AND OUR ECONOMIES STRONG.
I WANT TO THANK SILVER AS A STARTER FOR BEING AN EARLY
CO-SPONSOR. >> AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MAHMUD PRESIDENT
RANDLEMAN. >> THANK YOU MADAM CLERK.
I HAVE A COUPLE ITEMS. FIRST, I'M INTRODUCING A
RESOLUTION IN SUPPORT OF H.R. 8426 THE CRIME SURVIVORS
SUPPORT AND STABILITY ACT OF 2026 INTRODUCED BY
REPRESENTATIVE LATIFA SIMON AND REPRESENTATIVE AMELIA
SYKES. THIS LEGISLATION TAKES THREE
IMPORTANT STEPS FORWARD FOR SURVIVORS OF VIOLENCE.
IT DIRECTS STATES TO ENUMERATE AND PROTECT SURVIVOR RIGHTS
AND ESTABLISHES A FEDERAL GRANT PROGRAM TO FUND COMMUNITY BASED
ORGANIZATIONS AND DISTRIBUTING DIRECT CASH ASSISTANCE TO
SURVIVORS. AND IT AUTHORIZES AUTHORIZES
STATE LEVEL VICTIM NEED SURVEYS TO STRENGTHEN THE EVIDENCE BASE
FOR FUTURE FEDERAL INVESTMENTS. THE NEED IS SUBSTANTIAL.
THE BUREAU OF JUSTICE STATISTICS REPORTED
APPROXIMATELY 6.4 MILLION VIOLENT VICTIMIZATION IN THE
UNITED STATES IN 2023 WITH ASSOCIATED COSTS, MEDICAL
EXPENSES, LOST WAGES, MENTAL HEALTH SERVICES TOTALING TENS
OF BILLIONS OF DOLLARS ANNUALLY.
VIOLENCE LEAVES PEOPLE MATERIALLY DEVASTATED AT THE
VERY MOMENT THEY ARE MOST VULNERABLE.
AND THE EVIDENCE IS CLEAR THAT PRIOR VICTIMIZATION IS AMONG
THE STRONGEST PREDICTORS OF FUTURE VIOLENCE.
EXISTING VICTIM COMPENSATION PROGRAMS HAVE DONE IMPORTANT
WORK BUT THEY CONTAIN GAPS THAT LEAVE MANY SURVIVORS WITHOUT
ACCESS TO SUPPORT PROGRAMS. THAT CONDITION ELIGIBILITY ON
REPORTING TO OR COOPERATING WITH LAW ENFORCEMENT WHILE
WELL-INTENTIONED, OFTEN EXCLUDE IMMIGRANTS, DOMESTIC VIOLENCE
SURVIVORS AND OTHERS WHOSE CIRCUMSTANCES MAKE COOPERATION
DIFFICULT OR UNSAFE. THESE ARE OFTEN THE SAME
INDIVIDUALS WHO FACE VIOLENCE AT DISPROPORTIONATELY HIGH
RATES AND MAY NEED SUPPORT MOST URGENTLY.
H.R. 8426 ADDRESSES THOSE GAPS. UNDER THIS LEGISLATION,
SURVIVOR RIGHTS AND ACCESS TO ASSISTANCE WOULD NOT BE
CONDITIONED ON REPORTING IMMIGRATION STATUS, HOUSING
STATUS, ARREST OR CONVICTION RECORD OR ANY CLAIM THAT THE
SURVIVOR CONTRIBUTED TO THEIR OWN VICTIMIZATION.
>> DIRECT CASH ASSISTANCE DELIVERED THROUGH COMMUNITY
BASED ORGANIZATIONS WOULD BE EXCLUDED FROM INCOME AND ASSET
CALCULATIONS FOR FEDERAL MEANS TESTED PROGRAMS TO ENSURE IT
WOULD NOT REDUCE SURVIVORS ELIGIBILITY FOR OTHER PUBLIC
BENEFITS. >> I WANT TO ACKNOWLEDGE
AND THANK REPRESENTATIVE SIMON FOR HER LEADERSHIP ON THIS
LEGISLATION AND REPRESENTATIVE SYKES FOR HER CO-SPONSORSHIP.
I ALSO WANT TO THANK IVEY LEE AND BARBARA LOPEZ IN THE
MAYOR'S OFFICE FOR VICTIMS RIGHTS FOR FOR ALL THEIR HELP
WITH THIS RESOLUTION. AND I WANT TO THANK RONNELL THE
JOY IN MY OFFICE FOR HIS WORK AS WELL.
>> SECONDLY, COLLEAGUES, I'M ASKING THAT WE ADJOURN TODAY'S
MEETING IN MEMORY OF LAWRENCE MICHAEL STEPHANIE THE BELOVED
FATHER OF OUR FORMER COLLEAGUE ASSEMBLYWOMAN STEPHANIE WHO
DIED ON APRIL 29TH, 2026 AT THE AGE OF 82.
>> HE WAS BORN ON DECEMBER 18TH, 1943, RAISED IN MASUD,
CALIFORNIA IN A TIGHT KNIT ITALIAN CATHOLIC FAMILY.
GROWING UP HE WORKED IN THE FAMILY BUSINESS.
STEPHANIE CLOTHIERS. AFTER GRADUATING FROM
BELLARMINE COLLEGE PREP IN COLLEGE PREPARATORY IN 1961,
LAWRENCE MOVED ACROSS THE COUNTRY TO ATTEND UNIVERSITY OF
NOTRE DAME. AT NOTRE DAME HE FORMED
LIFELONG FRIENDSHIPS AND DEVELOPED A DEEP
AND ABIDING LOVE FOR THE UNIVERSITY AND ITS TRADITIONS.
LONG AFTER HE GRADUATED HE WOULD FILL HIS HOME WITH NOTRE
DAME SONGS, STORIES AND SPIRIT AND MANY OF US WILL REMEMBER
THAT HIS DAUGHTER ALSO CARRIED THAT AFFECTION WITH HER
AND TALKED ABOUT IT OFTEN. >> HE EARNED A MASTER'S DEGREE
IN INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS FROM UC BERKELEY BEFORE SERVING AS A
FIRST LIEUTENANT IN THE UNITED STATES ARMY INCLUDING A YEAR
STATIONED IN VIETNAM IN 1968. HE WAS AWARDED THE ARMY
COMMENDATION MEDAL FOR OUTSTANDING PROFESSIONAL
COMPETENCE AND DEVOTION TO DUTY.
HE WENT ON TO BUILD A LONG AND RESPECTED CAREER
IN FINANCIAL SERVICES BEGINNING AT BANK OF AMERICA AND LATER AT
PAINEWEBBER AND UBS AND MORE SAID HE MANAGED ONE OF THE MOST
SUCCESSFUL BRANCH OFFICES AND PAINEWEBBER GROUP'S GLOBAL
INVESTMENT NETWORK. FOR MORE THAN TWO DECADES
AND REMAINED DEEPLY COMMITTED TO MENTORING COLLEAGUES,
SERVING CLIENTS AND LEADING WITH INTEGRITY THROUGHOUT HIS
37 YEAR CAREER, HE AND HIS PROFESSIONAL ACCOMPLISHMENTS,
LARRY WAS ENDLESSLY CURIOUS, DEEPLY THOUGHTFUL AND FULL OF
LIFE. HE WAS AN AVID READER
AND DEVOTED STUDENT OF HISTORY, PARTICULARLY THE CIVIL WAR.
HE LOVED TRAVELING TO ITALY TO STAY CONNECTED TO HIS FAMILY
AND HERITAGE AND FOUND JOY IN MUSIC AND PERFORMANCE
THROUGHOUT HIS LIFE. >> FROM SINGING IN A BOYS CHOIR
AND THE BELLOWING GLEE CLUB TO PERFORMING WITH THE MASUD
CENTER FOR THE PERFORMING ARTS AND LATER SERVING SINGING TENOR
AT ST PATRICK'S PARISH. >> ABOVE ALL HE WAS A DEVOTED
HUSBAND, FATHER, MENTOR AND FRIENDS.
HE MADE PEOPLE FEEL SEEN, VALUED, WELCOMED.
HIS WORDS OF ENCOURAGEMENT PLAN FOCUS EXECUTE AND PERSEVERANCE
AS THE PRICE OF GREATNESS REFLECTED THE VALUES BY WHICH
HE LIVED AND INSPIRED OTHERS INCLUDING KATHARINE TO DO THE
SAME. REST IN PEACE.
REST IN PEACE LAWRENCE STEPHANIE.
MAY YOUR MEMORY AND LEGACY BE A BLESSING AND THE REST I SUBMIT.
>> THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. >> NEXT UP IS SUPERVISOR
MELGAR. >> I THINK YOU COLLEAGUES
PRESIDENT IF IT'S OKAY I WOULD LIKE TO BE ADDED TO YOUR
IN MEMORIAM FOR OUR DEAR FORMER COLLEAGUES.
>> FATHER, DID YOU GET THAT APOLOGY?
>> WANTED TO BE ADDED TO THE IN MEMORIAM FOR NOW.
WHY DON'T WE DO THAT? >> YEAH.
ON BEHALF OF THE FULL I WOULD APPRECIATE THAT.
THANK YOU. >> OKAY.
AT COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING A RESOLUTION TO
URGE STATE OFFICIALS TO SUPPORT SENATE BILL 436 THAT IS AISHA
SCHWAB'S BILL THE KEEPING CALIFORNIA'S HOUSE ACT OF 2026
THE BEST WAY TO PREVENT HOMELESSNESS IS TO PREVENT
PEOPLE FROM BEING HOMELESS. SB 436 IS A BILL THAT WOULD
EXTEND THE NOTICE PERIOD FOR RENTERS TO PAY, LAY RENT OR
MOVE OUT FROM THREE DAYS TO 14 DAYS.
A THREE DAY NOTICE PERIOD MAKES IT VERY DIFFICULT FOR RENTERS
TO FALL BEHIND ON RENT TO ACCESS EMERGENCY RENTAL
ASSISTANCE. THIS IS PARTICULARLY DIFFICULT
FOR PEOPLE WHO RECEIVE SUBSIDIES EITHER SECTION EIGHT
OR ANY OTHER LOCAL SUBSIDIES WHERE THEY HAVE TO DEAL WITH A
BUREAUCRACY THAT MAY NOT MOVE AS FAST.
THE THREE DAY NOTICE WHETHER IT'S GETTING HELP FROM FAMILY
OR PAY IT AND GET HELP FROM SOMEONE IS SHORT.
SO IN 2022 THE POLICY PROVIDES WAS AGREED AND UNANIMOUSLY
PASSED A SIMILAR ORDINANCE THAT WOULD HAVE REQUIRED A TEN DAY
WARNING PERIOD AN OPPORTUNITY TO PAY BEFORE EVICTION
PROCEEDINGS COULD HAPPEN. >> HOWEVER, THE COURT SAID THAT
IT NEEDED TO BE STATE LAW AND THAT IS WHAT WE'RE
ATTEMPTING TO DO NOW. SB 436 WOULD BE THAT TENANT
ADVOCATES HAVE ASKED OUR OFFICE TO DRAFT THIS RESOLUTION SO
THAT SAN FRANCISCO COULD BE ON THE RECORD TO SUPPORT
REPRESENTATIVE STEPHANIE AND HANEY SUPPORTED THE 22
LOCAL VERSION WHILE ON THE BOARD AND NOW THEY WILL HAVE AN
OPPORTUNITY TO SUPPORT THE STATE VERSION WHEN IT COMES
BEFORE THEM. THANK YOU SUPERVISORS MAHMUD
SADR AND CHEN FOR CO-SPONSORING IN ADVANCE AND THE REST I
SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MELGAR
. >> SUPERVISOR SAUTER THANK YOU
COLLEAGUES TODAY I'M INTRODUCING HEARING REQUESTS TO
DISCUSS HOW WE CAN MAKE IT MORE WELCOMING FOR FAMILIES TO USE
PUBLIC TRANSIT IN SAN FRANCISCO .
>> THIS HEARING REQUEST IS PART OF THE STROLLER ACT MY PUSH TO
FOCUS ON MAKING LIFE EASIER FOR YOUNG FAMILIES IN SAN FRANCISCO
WHILE PUBLIC TRANSIT IN SAN FRANCISCO DOES OFTEN FEEL EASY
AND ENJOYABLE NAVIGATING BUSSES AND SUBWAYS WITH TODDLERS
IN TOW OR STROLLERS IN HAND CAN PRESENT ITS OWN UNIQUE
CHALLENGES ARE HERE. OUR HEARING WILL PROVIDE SPACE
TO HEAR FROM OPERATORS INCLUDING MUNI AND BART
AND UNDERSTAND THEIR PROGRESS, SUCCESS AND SHORTCOMINGS
IN FACTORS THAT MAKE A BIG DIFFERENCE FOR FAMILIES USING
PUBLIC TRANSIT SUCH AS ELEVATOR AND ESCALATOR ACCESS
AND RELIABILITY WAYFINDING AND SIGNAGE, RESTROOM
AVAILABILITY FARES FOR YOUTH AND FAMILIES SAFETY SPEED
AND FREQUENCY MOVING AROUND A CITY BE IT FROM HOME TO SCHOOL
OR WEEKEND TRIPS TO LIBRARIES, PARKS AND PLAYGROUNDS IS A
MAJOR PART OF THE EXPERIENCE OF RAISING A FAMILY IN SAN
FRANCISCO. WE SHOULD MAKE SURE OUR TRANSIT
AGENCIES ARE DOING EVERYTHING THEY CAN TO MAKE SURE THAT
THESE ARE THESE EXPERIENCES ARE MORE POSITIVE.
YES, BUT ALSO MORE IMPORTANTLY FASTER, LESS EXPENSIVE AND MORE
RELIABLE. DOING SO IS A MAJOR WAY THAT WE
CAN MAKE IT MORE AFFORDABLE TO RAISE A FAMILY IN SAN FRANCISCO
. >> THE COST OF OWNING A CAR IS
ENORMOUS AND IT'S GOTTEN CONSIDERABLY MORE EXPENSIVE
IN RECENT YEARS BETWEEN THE VEHICLE INSURANCE PARKING
AND MAINTENANCE YOU'RE LOOKING AT A PRICE TAG THAT COULD BE
WELL NORTH OF $10,000 ANNUALLY. GIVEN THIS THE ABILITY FOR OUR
PUBLIC TRANSIT SYSTEMS TO BE GOOD ENOUGH FOR MORE FAMILIES
TO NOT FEEL FORCED TO DRIVE IS AN OPPORTUNITY TO PUT THOUSANDS
OF DOLLARS BACK IN THE POCKETS OF AN AVERAGE FAMILY EACH YEAR
AS THE SUPERVISOR REPRESENTING THE NEIGHBORHOODS WITH THE
LOWEST CAR OWNERSHIP IN OUR CITY, I'LL ALWAYS FIGHT FOR
BETTER PUBLIC TRANSIT. AND AS WE FACE FISCAL
CHALLENGES THIS FOCUS IS ALSO A GOOD INVESTMENT WHEN YOU MAKE
IT PRACTICE TO RIDE TRANSIT EARLY ON YOU'RE MORE LIKELY TO
BE A LIFELONG MUNI RIDER AND CUSTOMER.
FINALLY, I WANT TO EMPHASIZE THAT WHEN WE MAKE IT MORE
WELCOMING FOR FAMILIES TO RIDE PUBLIC TRANSIT WE ALSO MAKE IT
BETTER FOR EVERYONE. THAT'S WHY WE'VE BEEN WORKING
WITH PARTNERS INCLUDING SENIOR IN DISABILITY ACTION AND THE
OFFICE OF DISABILITY TO SHAPE THIS HEARING AND MAKE SURE THAT
TRANSIT CAN WORK BETTER FOR ALL THOSE WHO NEED EXTRA TIME OR
SPACE TO MOVE ABOUT OUR CITY. SO I LOOK FORWARD TO OUR
HEARING FOR A FULL DISCUSSION ON THIS IMPORTANT TOPIC AND THE
REST SUBMIT THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUPERVISOR
CHERYL SUBMIT THANK YOU AND SUPERVISOR WALTON SUBMIT.
THANK YOU MR. PRESIDENT. SEEING NO NAMES ON THE ROSTER
THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW BUSINESS.
>> GREAT. AND MADAM CLERK, ARE WE READY
TO GO BACK TO ITEMS 22 AND 24? >> I BELIEVE WE ARE.
MR. PRESIDENT WILL ASK ALL RIGHTS DPW REPRESENTATIVE TO
COME UP PRESIDENT MANDOLIN MEMBERS OF THE BOARD THANK YOU
FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE PRODUCTIVE CONVERSATIONS
OUTSIDE THE CHAMBERS. MANY OF THEM WERE JUST
INFORMATIONAL. >> THEY HAD QUESTIONS NOT
PERTAINING TO THE ANY OF THEM TEN ITEMS ITSELF.
THERE WAS ONE INDIVIDUAL IN WHICH WE HAD STRUCK IN ONE
FROM THE LIST FOR ITEMS 21 AND 20 TWO THE THE LIST REMAINS
THE SAME AND FOR ITEMS 23 AND 24 THERE IS ONE ITEM THE
PROPERTY AT 514 VISITATION AVENUE WHICH HAS BEEN STRICKEN
WITH THE REVISED AMOUNT THAT IS BEING ON REQUEST FOR APPROVAL
IS $6,204.80. WE WILL PROVIDE THAT REVISED
REPORT HAS BEEN ISSUED TO THE CLERK WHICH IS THIS DAY STRIKE
OUT FORM BUT WE'LL WILL PROVIDE A MORE FORMAL REPORT IN THE
MORNING. THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT. THANK YOU FOR YOUR WORK.
COLLEAGUES, CAN WE ACCEPT THE AMENDMENTS TO THE REPORT SOUGHT
IN ITEM 24 AND REMOVE THE PROPERTY IDENTIFIED BY
DEPARTMENT STAFF WITHOUT OBJECTION AND SEEING NO
OBJECTION, THOSE CHANGES ARE ACCEPT THAT CHANGE IS ACCEPTED
AND THEN MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE
RESOLUTIONS ITEM 22 AND 24 WITH THE AMENDED REPORT ON THE
AMENDED REPORTS FOR ITEM 22 AND 24 SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN EYES SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN EYES
SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN ALL RIGHT MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR
MALKA MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SARDAR SAUTER EYES SUPERVISOR
CHERYL CHERYL I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EITHER ATTORNEYS
WITHOUT OBJECTION ITEMS 22 AND 24 ARE ADOPTED WITH THE
AMENDED REPORTS. AND NOW LET'S GO TO PUBLIC
COMMENTS AT THIS TIME THE BOARD WELCOMES YOUR GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT IF YOU'LL LINE UP ON YOUR RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE
CHAMBER YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED THE
MAYORAL APPEARANCE ITEMS 29 THROUGH 31 THESE ARE THE ITEMS
UP FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AND OTHER
GENERAL MATTERS THAT ARE NOT ON THE PUBLISHED AGENDA TODAY BUT
MUST BE WITHIN THE BOARD'S SUBJECT MATTER JURISDICTION.
I WILL MAKE A SPECIAL NOTE OF THREE ITEMS IF YOU SPEAK TO THE
REPORT OF ASSESSMENT COSTS FOR EITHER THE SIDEWALK INSPECTION
AND REPAIR PROGRAM OR THE BLIGHTED PROPERTIES FOR THE
ACCELERATED SIDEWALK ABATEMENT PROGRAM OR THE UPDATE ON
FINDINGS AND RECOMMENDATIONS PERTAINING TO LAW ENFORCEMENT
PRACTICES. THOSE THREE ITEMS ARE NOT
ELIGIBLE FOR YOUR PUBLIC COMMENT DURING THIS GENERAL
PUBLIC COMMENT YOU WILL BE REDIRECTED AND THE CLOCK WILL
CONTINUE TO TICK. >> SO LET'S HEAR FROM OUR FIRST
SPEAKER. >> WELCOME.
WE'RE SETTING THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
MY NAME IS MICKEY GEORGE WATKINS AND I'M A FIRST GIVE AN
HONOR TO GOD WHO WAS THE HEAD OF MY LIFE.
>> I WOULD LIKE TO SAY GOOD EVENING TO THE SUPERVISORS.
I'VE LIVED IN THE FILLMORE FOR MOST OF THE 53 YEARS OF MY LIFE
. I'VE WORKED THERE FOR 3030
YEARS AS A LICENSED COSMETOLOGIST FROM FROM MY
BUSINESS TO MY HOME. I'M ON THE GROUND EVERY DAY I
SEE THE GAPS THAT THE CITY OFTEN MISSES FOR OVER A DECADE
,THE ELLA HILL CHURCH CENTER HASN'T LIVED UP TO ITS
POTENTIAL. WE NEED IT TO BE MORE TRUE TO
BE A TRUE COMMUNITY HUB AGAIN A PLACE FOR SENIOR ACCESS FOR
YOUNG ADULTS, FOR KIDS AND FOR SINGLE MOTHERS AND FATHERS WHO
NEED INFORMATION AND RESOURCES. >> IT SUGGESTS IT SHOULDN'T
JUST BE FOR A GROUP. IT NEEDS TO BE FOR A LIFELINE A
LIFELINE FOR EVERYONE FROM OUR ELDERS TO OUR INFANTS.
>> BUT WE CANNOT BUILD THAT VISION THROUGH GOVERNMENT
OVERREACH TRYING TO RUSH A SINGLE PERSON INTO LEADERSHIP
WITHOUT CHANCE, WITHOUT A TRANSPARENT COMMUNITY PROCESS
IS A MISTAKE IN A NORTH IGNORES THE PEOPLE WHO ACTUALLY LIVE
THERE. >> THIS DEMANDS COLLECTIVE
ACTION AND A FAIR PROCESS NOT A TOP DOWN APPOINTMENT.
>> WE NEED A LEADER WITH THE HEARTBEAT FOR THE COMMUNITY
SOMEONE WHO COMMUNICATES WITH US NOT TO US.
>> WE ARE NOT HERE TO HATE YOU BUT WE ARE HERE FOR JUSTICE.
WE HAVE PETITIONS FROM RESIDENTS WHO BELIEVE THAT MY
ROLE IS LEADERSHIP BECAUSE I BELIEVE IN MY ROLE AS
LEADERSHIP BECAUSE WE WANT THIS TO WORK.
WE ARE ASKING FOR A CALL DIRECTOR MODEL BETWEEN SHAKIRA
SMILEY AND RENARD MONROE SUPERVISORS PLEASE DO NOT VOTE
ON A SINGLE DIRECTOR HONOR THE COMMUNITY'S VOICE LET'S MAKE
ELDER HILL THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENT.
>> THANK YOU KINDLY. BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER
APPROACHES WE DO HAVE AN ADA CALLER WHO HAS MADE A PRIOR
ARRANGEMENT AND IS ON THE LINE AND PREPARED TO GIVE THERE TO
COME TWO MINUTES OF COMMENT DELFINO BRODY ARE YOU PREPARED
TO SPEAK? >> AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS DUFFY
AND BRODY THE MAYOR HAS PROPOSED NOT TO RENEW VITAL
CITY FUNDING FOR THIS PROJECT RENTAL HOUSING SUBSIDY PROGRAMS
FOR TRANS PEOPLE WHICH WOULD ELIMINATE THESE PROGRAMS
AND THE SUBSIDIES THEY PROVIDE FOR MORE THAN 300 TRANS PEOPLE
FUNDED BY THE CITY OVER THE PAST FIVE YEARS.
>> SUSTAINING AND EXPANDING THESE PROGRAMS NOT TO ELIMINATE
THEM IS KEY TO THE CITY GOAL DECLARED FIVE YEARS AGO AT THE
INCEPTION OF THE PROGRAM PROVIDING THE SUBSIDY I
RECEIVED TO END TRANSGENDER HOMELESSNESS.
SPEAKING FOR MYSELF AS A FORMERLY HOMELESS, DISABLED
TRANS WOMAN AND ADVOCATE WHOSE WORK IN SUPPORT OF TRANS
PRISONERS 25 YEARS AGO PAVED THE WAY FOR THE FOUNDING OF THE
TRANSGENDER PERIOD AND AND INTERSEX JUSTICE PROJECT AND AS
AN SSI BENEFICIARY WITH A MEANS TESTED INCOME BELOW THE FEDERAL
POVERTY LEVEL FOR 20 OF THE 20 OF THE PAST 28 YEARS SINCE I
WAS DIAGNOSED WITH POST-TRAUMATIC STRESS DISORDER
AFTER SURVIVING A SERIES OF TRAUMATIC ORDEALS UNABLE TO
MAINTAIN A SUBSTANTIAL GAINFUL INCOME AS THE COST OF RENTING A
STUDIO APARTMENT IN SAN FRANCISCO AND OTHER PARTS OF
THE INNER BAY AREA ROSE FURTHER AND FURTHER OUT OF REACH FOR
THE PAST FOUR YEARS AS MY DISABILITIES HAVE MULTIPLIED
BECOME MORE SEVERE AND KEPT ME HOMEBOUND MOST DAYS IN ORDER TO
KEEP THIS ROOF OVER MY HEAD OUT OF NECESSITY I'VE HAD TO RELY
ON THE RENTAL HOUSING SUBSIDY I NOW RECEIVE FROM THE T.G.I.
JUSTICE PROJECT TODAY THE COST OF A STUDIO APARTMENT IN SAN
FRANCISCO IS 2560 A MONTH MORE THAN TWICE THE MONTHLY INCOME I
RECEIVED FROM SSI IF THE CITY DOES NOT RENEW THE FUNDING FOR
TWO PROPOSED HOUSING SUBSIDY PROGRAMS, I WILL BE ONE OF
HUNDREDS OF TRANSGENDER BARRIER RESIDENTS WHO COULD NO LONGER
AFFORD TO RENT OUR APARTMENTS AND FACE PERMANENT DISPLACEMENT
AND A RETURN TO HOMELESSNESS AND THE DANGEROUS TRAUMATIC
CONDITIONS THAT EXACERBATED MY PTSD AND PRECIPITATED MY
PERMANENT DISABLEMENT ALMOST THREE DECADES AGO.
>> ALL RIGHT, LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> WELCOME. THANK YOU.
I'LL START GIVING HONOR TO THE LORD JESUS CHRIST WHO IS AHEAD
IN MY LIFE. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR. MY NAME IS ERIKA SCOTT.
ARE YOU ALL RECEIVED AN EMAIL FROM ME LAST WEEK REGARDING THE
ALLEY HILL HUTCH COMMUNITY CENTER SUPERVISOR BYLAW.
IT'S NO DISRESPECT TO YOU BUT I AM ASKING THE OTHER SUPERVISORS
TO NOT SUPPORT THE LEASE TRANSFER TO BOOKER T WASHINGTON
COMMUNITY CENTER WITH THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR SHE CARES
SIMILARLY AS WE ALL KNOW THE LARGE COMMUNITY CENTER RIGHT
NOW IS FACING COURT PROCEEDINGS REGARDING THE LEADERSHIP THE
FORMER LEADERSHIP OF OUR COMMUNITY CENTER TO RUSH
AND GIVE THE PROPERTY TO ANOTHER ENTITY WITHIN OUR
COMMUNITY CREATES ANOTHER MONOPOLY THAT WE'RE JUST
GETTING OUT OF. THE FORMER LEADERSHIP HAD NO
REAL ACCOUNTABILITY. >> THEY USE THE CENTER TO THEIR
ADVANTAGE DECIDING WHO WOULD RECEIVE SERVICES, FUNDING
AND SUPPORT AND SHAKIRA SIMILARLY IS A DIRECT PRODUCT
OF THAT SAME LINE OF LEADERSHIP .
>> SHE WORKED DIRECTLY WITH THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION.
>> SHE'S SHE'S THE ONE THAT THE THE EXISTING LEADERSHIP IS
PUSHING TO GET INTO THE BUILDING.
IT'S JUST NOT A FAIR PROCESS. IT DOES NOT SUPPORT OUR
COMMUNITY. WE ARE IN TRAUMA RIGHT NOW
AND TO GIVE SUCH A LEADERSHIP POSITION TO ONE PERSON WHO'S
NOT FROM OUR COMMUNITY, WHO'S NOT WILLING TO WORK WITH ANYONE
FROM OUR COMMUNITY IS JUST NOT A GOOD DECISION FOR US AS A
WHOLE. >> SO I AM ASKING THAT YOU DO
NOT AGREE WITH THE INFORMATION THAT'S BEEN SHARED BY.
>> THANK YOU ERICA SCOTT FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
MR. WRIGHT. >> DISCRIMINATORY PRACTICES
AND TRICKING DEVICES REAL COMPLICATED AND SOPHISTICATED
BUT YOU'RE NOT MORE SOPHISTICATED THAN ME.
YOU TRY TO PUT ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION ILLEGAL ALIENS ON
MEDICAL INSURANCE PROGRAMS IS A REASON WHY WE HAVE A $1.5
BILLION NEGATIVE CASH FLOW DEFICIT RIGHT NOW.
YOU CAN'T GIVE STATE AND FEDERAL FUNDS TO PEOPLE WHO
SNUCK IN THE COUNTRY ILLEGALLY AND VIOLATE FEDERAL RULES
AND THEN BY THE SAME RESPONSE EXPECT TAXPAYERS WHO ARE UNITED
STATES CITIZENS TO PAY FOR THEIR INSURANCE.
THAT'S THE REASON WHY YOU GOT A $1.5 BILLION NEGATIVE CASH FLOW
RIGHT NOW. WHAT PART OF THAT YOU DON'T
UNDERSTAND IT BRINGS INTO QUESTION IF YOU'RE DOCUMENTED
OR NOT. >> OKAY.
AND BY THE SAME RESPONSE THIS BOARD PARTICIPATES IN ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION AND HARBORING ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION.
>> YOU GOT A MEMBER ON YOUR BOARD, CONNIE CHEN.
SHE'S NOT EVEN A US CITIZEN. UNDERSTAND ME?
YOU GOT A JOB. THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO BE HELD BY
US CITIZEN A PERSON THAT LIVES IN THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO JURISDICTION THAT IS BORN IN THE UNITED STATES, NOT
SOMEBODY THAT'S SNUCK INTO THE COUNTRY AND COMES FROM CHINA
AND ALWAYS CREATING A MULTIMILLION DOLLAR NEGATIVE
AGAINST MR. RIGHT. >> WHY NOT?
WE DO NOT ENDORSE THOSE COMMENTS THAT YOU JUST MADE.
WELL, WHEN YOU GO TIME IS TICKING.
>> OKAY. STOP ME FROM SPEAKING SO AM
CLAIMING MY TIME. SO AS A RESULT EXAMPLE YOU LET
PEOPLE COME TO THE CHINESE NEW YEARS RIGHT?
MEANING FOR FREE MONEY IS $1.5 MILLION IN DEBT.
OKAY. >> ADD TO THAT CHINESE
CELEBRATION NOW MONEY IS $3.5 MILLION IN DEBT BECAUSE OF YOU
. A ST PATRICK'S DAY PARADE A
WEEK OR TWO LATER MAY 7TH POINT $5 MILLION.
>> THAT'S AN EXAMPLE YOUR TIME IS CONCLUDED AND MR. RIGHT YOU
CANNOT COME HERE AND INSULT PEOPLE.
>> I TELLING YOU THE DAY OF TO THE JUNE 1ST ANNUAL FLY BELOW
THE BELT AMEN CAN THE NEXT SPEAKER GET READY TO COME
FORWARD PLEASE? >> SO WE TALK ABOUT THE
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT TO TALK LIKE THAT DOES.
>> NO, YOU DO NOT. IT'S A LIMITED RIGHT.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. WELCOME.
>> SEE ABOUT THAT? YES.
PLEASE PROCEED. HI LADIES MANDELMAN OF THE
BOARD. THANK YOU FOR HAVING US HERE
TODAY. I REALLY APPRECIATE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO MAKE A GENERAL COMMENT.
MY NAME IS ERIN ROACH. I'M THE PRESIDENT OF THE MARINA
COMMUNITY ASSOCIATION AND I'M HERE TO JUST GIVE YOU ALL AN
UPDATE ON WHAT'S HAPPENING WITH THE MARINA SAFEWAY PROJECT
BECAUSE I THINK IT'S A PROJECT THAT HAS IMPLICATIONS FOR ALL
OF YOUR DISTRICTS AT SOME POINT OR ANOTHER.
>> WE ARE CHALLENGING ITS ELIGIBILITY FOR AB 2011.
FORTUNATELY WE'VE HAD THE SUPPORT OF SUPERVISOR CHERYL
IN THIS RECENTLY. >> IT'S A PROJECT THE PROJECT
SITE IS RIDDLED WITH COMPLEXITY AND IT IS NOT ONE THAT EASILY
FITS IN A SERIES OF CHECKED BOXES.
>> THE LANDMASS THAT THIS PROJECT REPRESENTS IS EQUAL TO
A HALF A PERCENTAGE OF ALL OF THE MARINA.
AND SO WHEN THE IMPLICATION IS ABOUT INFRASTRUCTURE, SEWAGE,
LIQUEFACTION. SOIL CONTAMINATION AREN'T
SERIOUSLY CONSIDERED, IT'S GOING TO BE A PROBLEM.
AND IF ANY OF YOU LIVED THROUGH THE RECENT F1 DEBACLE YOU'LL
KNOW WHAT I MEAN WHEN THINGS GET CROWDED AT THE MARINA IT'S
VERY DIFFICULT ON THE REST OF THE CITY.
SO I WANTED TO TELL YOU THAT WE'VE SENT A LETTER TO CITY
PLANNING THAT DETAILS THE CHALLENGES THAT WE'RE MAKING TO
AB 2011 AND I WOULD LOVE TO GIVE YOU ALL A COPY.
IT'S A BIG DOCUMENT BECAUSE THERE'S LOTS OF SUPPORTING
EVIDENCE HERE AND I CAN SEND IT VIA EMAIL.
I CAN GIVE IT TO THE CLERK TO MAKE COPIES BUT I WOULD LIKE
YOU ALL TO TAKE IT SERIOUSLY AND HOPE THAT WE CAN WORK WITH
THE CITY TO MAKE A MORE REASONABLE DEVELOPMENT AT THAT
SITE. THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME MR. DE COSTA
SUPERVISORS, I WANT TO TALK ABOUT TWO ISSUES ISSUE NUMBER
ONE WE HAVE RESERVOIRS IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT ARE CONTAMINATED
. IMAGINE CLEAN DRINKING WATER
CONTAMINATED BROUGHT THIS TO THE ATTENTION OF THE SRP YOU
SEE 16 TIMES TOOK THIS TO THE OCEAN, BROUGHT THIS TO THE
ATTENTION OF ONE OF YOUR IN THIS CHAMBER.
ARE WE GOING TO PUT SAN FRANCISCANS IN HARM'S WAY?
YOU BETTER LOOK INTO IT. >> SECONDLY, I SEE PEOPLE THEY
HAVE NO UNDERSTANDING OF WHAT THEY ARE TALKING ABOUT.
IF YOU TAKE COPS COMMUNITY ORIENTED POLICE SERVICE SAYS
OVER $1 MILLION WAS SPENT IN ORDER TO IMPROVE SAFETY
AND BRING CHANGES TO HOW POLICE FORCE WE SHOULD BE 2000 WHICH
IS 800. >> WHAT I WAS DOING ABOUT THAT
YOU SEEM NOT TO KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT OPERATIONS.
>> YOU SEEM NOT TO KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT NEEDS
ASSESSMENT. >> MICKEY MOUSE IS WHAT YOU ALL
NEED. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> UM OKAY.
OKAY. HELLO EVERYBODY.
SO ON A GOOD NOTE MY NAME IS DANNY DELMAR I ARI AND I TELL
THEM WHY ADELIA AMARI THE POLICE DEPARTMENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO DOES A GREAT JOB IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I JUST WANT TO SAY I WANT TO TAKE A MOMENT TO SAY THAT
BECAUSE I NOTICE I WANTED TO TAKE A MOMENT TO SAY HOW I WALK
DOWN THE STREETS OF JERRY POWELL, FRANKLIN AND BUSH
AND OTHER STREETS OFTEN I WALK ALONE OFTEN AND I ALSO OFTEN
FEEL MYSELF I DO VLOGS I STARTED DOING WAS ABOUT A MONTH
AGO AND THE REASON I DO IT IS BECAUSE I STARTED WATCHING THIS
YOUNG MAN CALLED QUERCUS AND HE DOES LOGS ALL OVER THE WORLD
AND HE'S A NOMAD AND I THINK I MIGHT END UP BEING ONE IN THE
NEXT YEARS BUT I'M A BIT NOT HAPPY ABOUT IT BECAUSE THE REST
OF THE WORLD IS A LOT MORE VIOLENT AND THEY ALSO LACK
POLICE THE WAY WE DO HERE. A LOT OF THEM HAVE FERAL
GOVERNMENT LIKE MILITIA WORKING.
THEY DON'T HAVE POLICE LIKE WE HAVE HERE AND IT LOOKS VERY
DANGEROUS. BUT I HOPE WHEN I GET OUT THERE
THEY HAVE POLICE. I KNOW THEY DON'T DO THAT BUT I
HOPE THEY CONSIDER OTHER COUNTRIES CONSIDER HAVING
REGULAR POLICE LIKE WE DO. >> I STARTED BECOMING VERY
ACTIVE IN THE PUBLIC OF SAN FRANCISCO ABOUT THREE YEARS AGO
AND I STARTED SINGING ON THE STREETS MAKING VIDEOS AND I
STARTED ATTENDING THE FRENCH ALLIANCE MEETINGS WHICH WE HAVE
A HUGE ALLIANCE WITH THE FRENCH GOVERNMENT.
IF YOU GUYS DID NOT KNOW ONE OF THE BIG REASON THAT WE WON THE
CIVIL WAR AND THE AMERICAN REVOLUTION AND ALL OF OUR WARS
WAS THANKS TO THE FRENCH ARMY WHICH ALWAYS CAME TO HELP US.
>> SO I SPEAK TO THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO MONTHLY
AND SOMETIMES WEEKLY AND I HAVE A GREAT LOVE FOR SAN FRANCISCO
BECAUSE I WAS ABLE TO BUY MY FIRST HOUSE WORKING TWO JOBS
IN SAN FRANCISCO. I ALSO DON'T OWN THE HOUSE
ANYMORE THANKS TO COVID I CAN SAY WITH ASSURANCE EVERY WEEK
SAN FRANCISCO BECOMES MORE LIVELY AND MORE POPULAR
WORLDWIDE. I HOPE TO ONE DAY PARTICIPATE
IN INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS AND HELP PROMOTE THE BEAUTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO WORLDWIDE AND BRING THE CULTURE OF UNION
SQUARE WORLDWIDE BECAUSE IT IS ONE OF MY FAVORITE PLACES
IN THE WORLD. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENT.
THANK YOU. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO EVERYBODY.
MY NAME IS LYDIA BETWEEN UH MY COMMENT WOULD BE ABOUT THREE
LIKE OKAY SO JUJU MENTIONED THAT THE COMPLAINTS THAT HIS
OFFICE RECEIVE COMES FROM AREAS OF SAN FRANCISCO THAT ARE MORE
RESPECTED AND I WANT TO PROPOSE THAT DPW LEADS A CAMPAIGN THAT
INFORMS THE PUBLIC ABOUT THE 311 APPLICATION AND HOW TO
SUBMIT A RESPONSE AND THAT IT SHOULD BE A COLLABORATION
EFFORT. AND IN ADDITION TO A311
APPLICATION CAMPAIGN, THE CITY SHOULD EXPAND THE SIDEWALK
INSPECTION AND REPAIR PROGRAM AND THEN THAT CAN ALSO BE LIKE
WHAT'S THE WORD? I DON'T KNOW WHAT THE WORD I'M
TALKING ABOUT BUT A PIPELINE TO WORK INTO THE CITY.
>> UM ANOTHER COMMENT THAT'S THE ONLY COMMENT I HAVE RIGHT
NOW. >> THANK YOU MR. CUI CHANDLER.
>> WELCOME TO YOU IN ON UM I'VE NOTICED THAT IT'S BEEN A LOT OF
BLACKS THAT HAD CITY POSITIONS THAT ARE EITHER IN PRISON OR BE
IN CHARGE. THE NAME IS MOHAMMED NURU AND I
WANT TO SAY THESE INDIVIDUALS I DON'T KNOW THE STORY AS FAR AS
GUILT OR INNOCENCE BUT I'M LOOKING AT THE TIMELINE HERE OF
ALL THESE BLACK INDIVIDUALS MOHAMMED NURU, HARLAN KELLEY
BLACK SURE. DAVIS BLACK, GWENDOLYN
AND WESTBROOK BLACK CAR WERE WORTHY BLACK JAMES SPINOLA
BLACK CHERYL DAVIS BLACK. >> DWAYNE JONES BLACK.
>> NOW IT'S OBVIOUS THAT IS A LOT OF INVESTIGATION GOING ON
AROUND HERE WITH THESE BLACK SO-CALLED EXECUTIVES BUT IT'S
NOT MUCH INVESTIGATION GOING DOWN CONCERNING THE OTHER
NATIONALITIES. WHAT'S GOING ON AROUND HERE?
>> NO ONE IS BLIND ANYMORE. WE ARE AWAKENED PEOPLE WHO HAVE
STEPPED INTO OUR POSITION OF POWER.
THE TRIBE OF JUDAH HAS RISEN. >> THE HEBREW NATION IS
AWAKENING. BUT WHAT I WANT TO SAY THE
DISRESPECT OF INSULTING US AS A COMMONLY CALLED BLACK NATION
AND SAYING THAT EVERY ONE OF YOU HAVE VOTED FOR REPARATIONS
FOR US YET AS A GO FUND ME FOR US TO GET THE MONEY OURSELVES.
>> BEING NICE TO THE SYSTEM IS NOT GOING TO WORK.
BUT I'M HERE TO LET YOU KNOW I HAVE NO PROBLEM WHEN IT'S TIME
TO CALL IN THE ORDER. >> I HAVE NO PROBLEM BECAUSE
MANY OF OUR YOUNG BLACK BOYS HAVE BEEN MURDERED AND THE
BLOOD HAS SPILLED IN THIS COUNTRY AND THE ENSLAVEMENT
AND THE CONDITION OF MY PEOPLE. >> I HAVE NO PROBLEM IN CALLING
THE ORDER. >> THANK YOU, MISS CHANDLER,
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. THANK YOU, MISS CHANDLER.
ALL RIGHT. NEXT SPEAKER WELCOME.
THIS IS TOUGH GUYS, GALS, GUYS. >> ELISE ROCHELLE AGAIN.
>> >> I ONLY GOT TWO MINUTES. I WASTED MY GAS.
EXCUSE ME? I USED MY GAS TO GET HERE.
>> I'M JUST GONNA STAY IN HERE BECAUSE I'M NOT NECESSARILY I
DON'T WANNA SAY I'M DISAPPOINTED.
I'M TRYING TO FIND MY SPACE IN THIS POLITICAL SITUATION.
I NEVER WANTED TO BE POLITICAL ,BUT EVERYTHING IS POLITICAL.
I WILL SAY SHARON, HE WAS NAME AGAIN BECAUSE SHE TOLD ME THAT
THIS IS HOW IT IS AND I STILL DON'T AGREE WITH IT.
BUT HERE I AM. I'M LOOKING AT ALL OF Y'ALL
AND I HEARD SO MUCH GOING ON TODAY, SO MANY THINGS JUST THE
WHOLE DAY IS HERE IN THIS THESE CHAMBERS AND YOU KNOW, WHEN WE
SPEAK HERE AT THIS MICROPHONE, WHAT IN THE WORLD ARE YOU GUYS
DOING WITH THIS INFORMATION? I WANT TO KNOW AND I JUST
REALLY WANT TO SEE A MORE TRANSPARENT SYSTEM HERE BECAUSE
I MEAN I'M 50 PLUS AND WHAT I'VE SEEN IS NOT THE BEST
SYSTEM OF HOW THINGS WORK FOR ME AS A NATIVE SAN FRANCISCAN
GREW UP HERE. >> YEAH, JUST YEAH, JUST
LISTEN. I GUESS I'LL WAIT FOR THE BEEP
TOO, BUT IT'S JUST IS REALLY INTERESTING HOW THIS PROCESS IS
WORKING AND I'M HERE FOR IT. >> I'M NOT GOING ANYWHERE.
I'M GOING TO FIND OUT MY PLACE IN THIS SPACE BECAUSE GOD TOLD
ME THAT I'M TO BE WORKING WITH THE SUPERVISORS.
>> SO HERE ARE THE SUPERVISORS. HERE I AM.
YOU'LL SEE MORE OF ME AND I AM LISTENING TO SEE WHAT'S NEXT
WHEN I CALL YOU PLEASE ANSWER WORK WITH ME.
I'M READY TO WORK WITH YOU. OKAY?
BECAUSE WE ARE LIVING HERE IN THIS SPACE TOGETHER.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. HI MY NAME IS NICK PIAZZA
AND I'M HERE TO ASK THAT IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE CHARTER
OF SAN FRANCISCO THAT YOU PLEASE ACT TO MEET THE NEEDS OF
THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO TO FUND THE CITY'S SERVICES
AND HOLD THE AIR COMPANIES ACCOUNTABLE.
THERE IS A JUSTIFIED AND GROWING PUBLIC CONCERN
REGARDING THE CURRENT HARMS AND IMPENDING RISKS OF
ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE. THESE INCLUDE NEGATIVE
COGNITIVE EFFECTS AIR ADDICTION AND PSYCHOSIS INVASIONS OF
PRIVACY, ENVIRONMENTAL DEGRADATION, WIDENING
SOCIOECONOMIC INEQUALITY, JOB DISPLACEMENT, OUTRIGHT SOCIAL
ENGINEERING, MASTER SURVEILLANCE, CYBER ATTACKS,
AUTONOMOUS WEAPONS SYSTEMS AND EVEN AN EXISTENTIAL THREAT
TO THE HUMAN SPECIES. I HOPE I HAVE YOUR ATTENTION.
THESE CURRENT HARMS AND IMPENDING RISKS OF AI
CONSTITUTE A PUBLIC EMERGENCY. RIGHT NOW IT IS IMPERATIVE THAT
EVERY LEVEL OF OUR CITY GOVERNMENT ADDRESS THEM SATISFY
UTTERLY AND IMMEDIATELY. WE SAN FRANCISCANS ARE ALSO
AWARE OF THE SEVERE BUDGET CUTS WHICH WILL IMPACT IMMIGRANT
FAMILIES AND LOW INCOME COMMUNITIES THE MOST
AND ELIMINATES MANY HARM REDUCTION PROGRAMS.
THESE ISSUES AND CONCERNS CAN BE RESOLVED.
SO WE PROPOSE THAT YOU DO THE FOLLOWING AS SOON AS POSSIBLE.
NUMBER ONE MANDATE BY EMERGENCY ORDER OR CITY ORDINANCE THAT NO
A.I. COMPANY IN SAN FRANCISCO OPERATE WITHOUT A VALID A.I.
LICENSE ISSUED BY THE CITY AND NOT WITHOUT A MONSTER BILL
AND CERTIFIABLE EVIDENCE AND ONGOING PROOF THAT THE A.I.
COMPANY'S MODELS ARE SAFE, SECURE AND UNDER HUMAN CONTROL
. NUMBER TWO SET THE ANNUAL COST
TO OBTAIN THE AI LICENSE AT 2% OF THE COMPANY'S ANNUAL REVENUE
AND SET THE FINE FOR OPERATION WITHOUT THE VALID LICENSE AT $2
MILLION PER DAY PAID TO THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
AND THREE ALLOCATE THE REVENUE GAINED FROM THE LICENSING
PROGRAM TO FUND THE CITY SERVICES THAT ARE OTHERWISE
BEING CUT. THANK YOU IN ADVANCE FOR YOUR
PROMPT ATTENTION TO THIS URGENT ISSUE.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER .
GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD PRESIDENT GENTLEMEN AND BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS FIONA YIM AND I'M
THE COMMUNICATIONS MANAGER AT WALK SAN FRANCISCO.
>> FIRST I WANT TO THANK SUPERVISOR DORSEY MANAGEMENT
AND MELGAR FOR CO-SPONSORING THE RESOLUTION TO FURTHER
EMBRACE SPEED CAMERAS TO SAVE LIVES, MAKE STREETS SAFER
AND OUR CITY BETTER. >> ALREADY THE THREE SPEED
CAMERAS IN SAN FRANCISCO'S PILOT PROGRAM ARE MAKING A
REMARKABLE DIFFERENCE. DATA FROM THE FIRST YEAR OF THE
SPEED CAMERA PROGRAM SHOWS THE CAMERAS ARE WORKING WITH A
NEARLY 80% DROP IN DRIVERS TRAVELING TEN MILES PER HOUR OR
MORE. BUT THE SPEED LIMIT ACROSS ALL
CAMERA LOCATIONS WHEN THE CAMERAS WERE TURNED ON BAYSHORE
AVENUE GAVE AN AVERAGE OF 255 NOTICES PER DAY.
NOW IT GIVES AN AVERAGE OF 74 PER DAY.
THAT'S A 71% DECREASE. MICHIGAN BETWEEN SEVENTH
AND EIGHTH SAW A 83% DROP IN SITUATIONS IN YOUR SOCIAL
AND HEALTH SERVICES. GENEVA HAS SEEN A 94% DROP
IN NOTICES IN CROCKER AMAZON THERE ARE MORE THAN 40,000
FEWER INSTANCES OF DANGEROUS SPEEDING EVERY DAY AND 65% OF
VEHICLE OWNERS WHO RECEIVE A NOTICE DO NOT RECEIVE A SECOND
CITATION. BRINGING DOWN SPEEDS IS THE
NUMBER ONE WAY TO MAKE OUR STREETS SAFER.
THIS PILOT HAS SHOWN THAT SPEED CAMERAS WILL DO JUST THAT.
BUT THE PROGRAM MUST BE BROUGHT TO SCALE.
>> CALIFORNIA'S BECOME A PILOT HAS STRONG PRIVACY PROTECTION
PARAMETERS THAT ENSURE THAT THE DATA DOES NOT GET INTO THE
WRONG HANDS. AND EQUITY WAS EXPLICITLY
DESIGNED INTO THE LAW. >> SAFE SPEEDS IS ONE OF THE
PILLARS OF THE CITY'S STREETS SAFETY INITIATIVE AND STREET
SAFETY ACT. >> THE CAMERAS ARE ONE TOOL TO
REACH THE CITY'S GOAL OF ENDING DEATHS AND SERIOUS INJURIES
FROM TRAFFIC CRASHES. THANK YOU AGAIN, SUPERVISOR
DORSEY FOR REESTABLISHING THE CITY'S COMMITMENT TO THIS
TECHNOLOGY AND BEGINNING THE EXPLORATION OF HOW TO EXPAND
THE LEGISLATION TO MEET THE DEMAND.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> WILL HONORABLE SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS THE DRAGON KING. I'M A SAN FRANCISCO DRAG KING A
TRANS MAN, A MAN RAISED TO LOVE HIS NEIGHBORS BY HIS CATHOLIC
LUTHERAN AND ASHKENAZI JEWISH RELATIVES AND I RUN A FREE
COMMUNITY DAY AT 575 CASTRO STREET SUPERVISOR HARVEY MILK'S
CAMPAIGN HEADQUARTERS AND CAMERA STORE.
FOR TEN WEEKS WE HAVE OFFERED FREE USE OF TYPEWRITERS TO
WRITE TO THE MAYOR'S OFFICE BECAUSE WE DON'T BELIEVE
IN USING CBD. WE OFFER FIVE DIFFERENT NEWS
SOURCES TO ASSIST IN DRAFTING AND FOR TEN WEEKS WE HAVE BOTH
HAND-DELIVERED AND SENT SCANNED EMAILS TO THIS WITH A SIMPLE
REQUEST WE WOULD APPRECIATE THE COURTESY OF A RESPONSE FROM YOU
OR A MEMBER OF YOUR STAFF REGARDING THE CONTENTS
AND PROPOSALS SET FORTH IN THIS LETTER WE HAVE RECEIVED ZERO
RESPONSES. THE SAN FRANCISCO CITIZENS THAT
CAME TO CASTRO THE CASTRO WROTE TO THE MAYOR OR OR AT LEAST ONE
OF HIS STAFF EXPECTING A RESPONSE FROM THEIR ELECTED
OFFICIAL BUT THEY HAVE BEEN IGNORED.
WHERE ARE THESE CITIZENS NOT IN PORTLAND OR WHERE ARE THEY
ENOUGH FOR A RESPONSE? >> COULD THE MAYOR'S OFFICE NOT
SPARE AT LEAST ONE OF HIS 45 BUDGETED STAFF MEMBERS IN THE
OFFICE TO RESPOND? WE HAVE WRITTEN ABOUT CUTS TO
COMMUNITY SERVICES, CUTS TO HIV FUNDING, ATTEMPTS TO INCREASE
MAYORAL EXECUTIVE POWER AND WE HAVE EVEN WRITTEN IN TO ASK
THAT SPEED LIMITS BE PUT ON OUR SHIPS SO THEY STOP KILLING
WHALES IN THE BAY. I HOPE HE HAS SOME STAFF TO
SPARE TODAY FOR TODAY COMPLETELY INDEPENDENT FROM ME
AND THE 575 FIGHTING FOR THE MOVEMENT TO CONTINUE THE S.F.
PEOPLE'S BUDGET AND THE S.F. AIDS FOUNDATION TOOK THAT IDEA
OF SENDING THE MAYOR LETTERS AND INNOVATED IN WAYS BEYOND MY
WILDEST DREAMS. SO MANY POSTCARDS WITH
GRIEVANCES FEARS AND COMMUNITY NEEDS TO THE MAYOR ALL HELD UP
BY SAN FRANCISCANS WHO QUITE FRANKLY GAVE THE COPS PANIC
ATTACKS MAYBE BECAUSE THEY REALIZE THEIR OVERSATURATED
BUDGETS ARE UNDER THREAT. >> THAT IS SAN FRANCISCO.
SO THOSE ARE YOUR PEOPLE DEMANDING TO BE HEARD BY THEIR
ELECTED OFFICIALS. SO MY QUESTION TO THE BOARD IS
THIS HOW CAN THE PEOPLE OF SAN FRANCISCO TRUST THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE AND BY THE EXTENSION ITS SUPERVISORS IF THEY FEEL
UNHEARD? HOW CAN THE MAYOR OF SAN
FRANCISCO POSSIBLY REPRESENT AND MEET THE NEEDS OF HIS
NEIGHBORS IF EVEN THE LETTERS FROM THE MAYOR OF THE CASTRO
STREETS HOME OF HIS HOME BE BLATANTLY IGNORED?
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND WHAT WILL YOU DO TO HELP
FOR THE MOVEMENT TO CONTINUE? >> LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT
SPEAKER PLEASE. I WELCOME.
HI. YES, JESSICA PERSICO DISTRICT
TEN CANDIDATE AND ARE AN EXPERT WITNESS.
>> AND I'M HERE TO DISCUSS HOW WE CAN IMPROVE SOME OF OUR WAYS
FOR PEOPLE TO GET AROUND IN OUR TRANSPORTATION.
>> SPECIFICALLY I'D LIKE TO WORK WITH YOU GUYS AS WELL AS
AS OF MTA AND REDOING SOME OF OUR BUS ROUTES.
>> FOR EXAMPLE, WE HAVE A LOT OF OVERLAPPING BUS ROUTES NINE
NINE HOUR 14 14 HOUR AND THERE'S OTHER BUS ROUTES
IN MY DISTRICT SUCH AS THE 54 AND THE 19 THAT WE COULD REDO
SO WE CAN GET BETTER ACCESS TO THE HOSPITAL AND MAJOR EVENTS
WITHIN OUR DISTRICT AND OUTSIDE .
SO I'D LIKE TO WORK TOGETHER TO DO THAT.
ALSO IF WE COULD WORK TOGETHER TO EVALUATE WAYS TO DECREASE
THE COST OF PARKING TICKETS IT'S EXPENSIVE ENOUGH TO OWN A
CAR LET ALONE AFFORD GAS NOW AND WE HAVE TO FIGURE OUT A WAY
TO KEEP COSTS DOWN FOR OUR RESIDENTS AS WELL AS PROVIDE
THEM SAFE PLACES THAT ARE THAT WE CAN WORK.
WE'RE OFTEN FINDING THAT A LOT OF OUR EMPLOYEES WELL NOT
EMPLOYEES THEIR 1099 WORKERS ARE BEING MISCLASSIFIED
AND THEY SHOULD BE W2 EMPLOYEES.
THE PROBLEM IS THE DEPARTMENT OF LABOR A.K.A ALSO THE
CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF INDUSTRIAL RELATIONS IS NOT
ONLY UNDERSTAFFED BUT THEY NEED A BIGGER BUDGET TO HELP SOME OF
THESE WORKERS GET THEIR BENEFITS BECAUSE WE'RE OFTEN
SEEING THAT THERE'S A BIG LACK OF ACCESS TO HEALTH CARE AND A
LOT OF THESE EMPLOYEES ARE WORKING A LOT OF HOURS BUT THEY
CANNOT AFFORD HEALTH INSURANCE. THEY'RE AFRAID OF WORKING MORE
BECAUSE IF THEY DO THAT THEY DON'T GET MEDICAL BECAUSE THE
LIMIT IS $1,800. SO WE NEED TO FIGURE OUT WAYS
TO IMPROVE OUR HEALTH CARE ACCESS.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS SHANNON GILMER. >> I WORK WITH 18 STAFFING.
AND I ALSO SERVE AS A VOLUNTEER ASSISTANT FOR JESSICA PASCOE
RIGHT HERE BEHIND ME. >> SHE'S CANDIDATE FOR SAN
FRANCISCO DISTRICT TEN SUPERVISOR.
I'D LIKE TO RESPECTFULLY REQUEST TIME TO SPEAK AND SHARE
IF YOUR RECOMMENDATIONS REGARDING THE ENTERTAINMENT
COMMISSION REGARDLESS OF THE GUIDELINES PERMITS FOR AN
ORDINANCE AND THINGS LIKE THAT AND TIMES AND STUFF I WOULD
LIKE TO SEE IF YOU GUYS WOULD LIKE ME TO SPEAK WITH MY FRIEND
JESSICA ON THE PODIUM IF THAT'S OKAY.
>> ALL RIGHT. COOL.
THANKS SO. AFTER GOING TO THE
ENTERTAINMENT COMMISSION SPEAKER'S TIME YOU CAN USE THE
TIME IS ALLOTTED TO YOU. >> I ASKED IF SHE CAN SPEAK
WITH ME. NO, WE DON'T DO THAT.
SHE'S COMPLETED HER TIME. >> SO REGARDLESS OF OF THE
VENTILATIONS REQUIREMENTS OR CURRENT GUIDELINES AND EMPHASIS
ON KEEPING DOORS AND WINDOWS CLOSED INSIDE OF VENUES, I'D
LIKE TO PROPOSE RECONSIDERING THIS APPROACH AND I'M PAUSING
YOUR TIME. ALL RIGHT.
JUST SO YOU KNOW, THERE IS NO ELECTORAL, NO ELECTIONEERING
YOU CAN DO IN THE CHAMBER DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT.
OKAY. SO JUST KEEP YOUR COMMENTS
GENERAL. I DO NOT TALK ABOUT THE
ELECTION OR THE FACT THAT YOU'RE A CANDIDATE OR ANYONE
ELSE IS A CANDIDATE. OKAY.
OKAY. THANK YOU.
>> WE'RE NOT TALKING ABOUT THAT RIGHT NOW.
CURRENTLY THE LIKE GAL THE FOUNDER OF THE MODERN NURSING
ENFORCES IMPORTANCE IN THE FRESH AIR HAVING WINDOWS OPEN,
DOORS OPEN DURING EVENTS AND NEVER TO BE AFRAID TO OPEN
THE WINDOWS AND THINGS LIKE THAT.
>> SO FOR HEALTH REASONS AND THINGS LIKE THAT FOR INDOOR
ENVIRONMENTAL HEALTH TO HELP PREVENT NOISE COMPLAINTS I
RECOMMEND THAT ENTERTAINMENT COMMISSIONS PROVIDE CLEAR
GUIDANCE TO BUSINESSES ABOUT SOUND LIMITS SPECIFIC TO THEIR
LOCAL AREA. AS NOTED IN THE PERMIT GUIDANCE
BUSINESS ARE EXPECTED TO BE FAMILIAR WITH THEIR SOUND
LIMITS CLEARER MORE ACCESSIBLE INFORMATION WILL HELP IMPROVE
COMPLIANCE FOR BUSINESS APPEARING IN COMMERCIAL ZONES I
SUGGEST ARE CONSIDERING WHETHER PERMITS ARE NECESSARY FOR LOWER
IMPACT ACTIVITIES SUCH AS KARAOKE REDUCING THE
STREAMLINED PERMIT REQUIREMENTS IN THESE CASES COULD LOWER
COSTS FOR SMALL BUSINESSES AND MAKE COMPLIANCE MORE
EFFICIENT. ALL RIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
HELLO. MY NAME'S DARRYL DANIELS, BORN
AND RAISED IN THE CITY. >> I WANT TO SPEAK ON THE AIR.
YOU CAN HOLD THAT MICROPHONE UP TOO STRAIGHT THAT AS MUCH AS I
WANTED TO SPEAK ON THE ELLA HILL SITUATION, I THINK EVERY
HOUSEHOLD SHOULD HAVE ITS OWN PARENT AND I THINK ELLA HILL
HUT SHOULD HAVE ITS OWN PARENT AND I DON'T THINK A PERSON
SHOULD HAVE TWO JOBS LIKE THAT BECAUSE IT NEEDS ITS OWN
ATTENTION FROM WHAT'S BEEN GOING ON IN THE PAST.
THERE AND I THINK IT WOULD BE VERY UNFAIR FOR ONE PERSON TO
RUN TO PLACES LIKE THAT. IT NEEDS TO BE ONE PERSON
RUNNING HERE AND ONE PERSON RUN IT THERE.
>> AND I WANT TO SAY THIS TO THE SUPERVISORS AND I WANT YOU
TO TAKE THIS PERSONAL. >> I SAT AND I WATCHED CERTAIN
PEOPLE SPEAK. YOU DON'T LOOK THEM IN THE EYE.
YOU LOOK DOWN, YOU TALK AND YOU SHOULD TREAT EVERYTHING THE
SAME THE ENERGY YOU GUYS HAVE FOR THE GUY WHO SPOKE ON THE
TRENDS AND THE KIDS THE FIRST GUY EVERYBODY WAS INTO IT.
YOU SHOULD BE LIKE THAT WITH EVERYONE ESPECIALLY THE
NATIVES. >> GOD BLESS.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER GOOD AFTERNOON
AGAIN. STARCHILD CHAIR OF THE
LIBERTARIAN PARTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> STARCHILD THAT FOR LIBERTY DAWG REFERENCING ONE OF THE
PREVIOUS COMMENTS I WANTED TO TALK ABOUT THE CAMERAS, THE
SPEED CAMERAS. >> THIS IS PART OF A MUCH
LARGER TREND IN OUR SOCIETY OF MASS SURVEILLANCE.
EVERYTHING FROM MONITORING CARS THROUGH THE FAST TRACK THING
THAT GO OVER THE BRIDGE CAMERAS IN OUR MUNI BUSSES CAMERAS ON
BART ALL KINDS OF INFORMATION BEING DATA HARVESTED THROUGH
TECH COMPANIES AND OFTEN ENDS UP IN THE HANDS OF GOVERNMENT
IF GOVERNMENT ISN'T HARVESTING IT DIRECTLY.
THIS IS A GROWING THREAT TO ALL OF OUR PRIVACY AND CIVIL
LIBERTIES. I UNDERSTAND WANTING TO REDUCE
DEATHS ON THE STREET. I DON'T OWN A CAR.
I'M A CYCLIST. I BIKE MOSTLY TO GET AROUND BUT
I DO NOT WANT MORE CAMERAS OUT THERE SURVEILLING US.
THE CURRENT TRUMP ADMINISTRATION AND EVERYTHING
THEY'RE DOING TO ERODE CIVIL LIBERTIES AND DEMOCRACY IN THIS
COUNTRY SHOULD REALLY MAKE YOU THINK TWICE BEFORE BEING
WILLING TO PUT IN A NETWORK LIKE THIS.
YOU DON'T KNOW WHO'S GOING TO SUCCEED YOU.
I MEAN SAN FRANCISCO SEEMS SOLIDLY DEMOCRATIC RIGHT NOW.
I KNOW YOU'RE ALL DEMOCRATS. YOU MAY FEEL LIKE THAT'S GOING
TO EXIST AND BE THE CASE FOREVER BUT IT ISN'T
NECESSARILY GOING TO BE THE CASE FOREVER.
ANY POWER THAT YOU GIVE TO GOVERNMENT IT THINKING THAT OH,
THIS IS SOMEONE I AGREE WITH AND I TRUST THEM WITH THIS
POWER WELL THAT POWER WILL STILL BE THERE WHEN THEY'RE
SUCCEEDED BY SOMEBODY WHOSE AGENDA YOU DON'T NECESSARILY
AGREE WITH AND ALL THESE MASS SURVEILLANCE CAMERAS REALLY
AGAIN POSE A STANDING THREAT TO ALL OF US.
SO PLEASE THINK ABOUT OTHER WAYS THAT DON'T INVOLVE
MONITORING AND SURVEILLING THE PUBLIC AND ADDING TO THIS
GROWING TURNKEY TOTALITARIAN POLICE STATE THAT'S BEING BUILT
IN THIS COUNTRY. >> PLEASE REMOVE THE CAMERAS
AND LOOK INTO SPECIFICALLY THE FLOCK COMPANY.
IT'S GETTING A LOT OF NEGATIVE PRESS.
THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF DISINGENUOUS INFORMATION FROM
THEM. I DON'T HAVE TIME TO GO INTO IT
BUT PLEASE THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER AND BEFORE YOU SPEAK, ARE THERE
ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS
WELCOME THE BOARD DURING GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT?
ALL RIGHT. PLEASE PROCEED.
WE'LL SET THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
HI, THIS IS KIMBERLY SIMMONS AND I JUST LIKE TO MAKE A
PROPOSAL A FEW IDEAS THAT I HAVE.
>> KIMBERLY, CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THE MICROPHONE
FOR US? >> I JUST WANTED TO PROPOSE A
FEW IDEAS THAT I HAVE FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
ONE OF THE IDEAS THAT I HAVE BEEN PROPOSED ONE WOULD LIKE TO
PROPOSE IS SAN FRANCISCO BAY SEAWALL.
THE WATER YOU KNOW THESE ANXIETY ATTACKS ABOUT THIS
WATER AND OCEAN AND YOU'VE GOT THE BAY AND YOU GOT THE OCEAN.
EVERYTHING IS ALL AROUND SAN FRANCISCO SO SMALL I DON'T KNOW
IF IT CAN HOLD UP AS MUCH AS WE WOULD LIKE TO BELIEVE.
>> HOWEVER, I'M NOT A PROFESSIONAL.
I DON'T HAVE ANY CONSTRUCTION IDEAS ON HOW TO FIX IT.
>> HOWEVER I JUST WANTED TO MAKE A FEW SUGGESTIONS FOR
PROFESSIONAL HELP IN THESE SITUATIONS BUT HAVEN'T.
IT WOULD BE SAN FRANCISCO BAY SEAWALL AND I WAS ALSO THINKING
ABOUT A BOAT HARBORING STATION OVER THERE IN CANDLESTICK BAY
VIEW AREA FOR BOAT HARBORING. >> I DON'T KNOW IF YOU GUYS
EVER BEEN TO LONG BEACH QUEEN MARY IT'S LIKE A BOAT THERE
AND IT'S A HOTEL RESTAURANT FOOD JUST LIKE YOU KNOW JUST
LIKE A NICE BOAT AN AREA ONLY IN THE CITY THE CITY OF
BAYVIEW, CANDLESTICK PARK. HAVE YOU EVER THOUGHT ABOUT
EXTENDING THE SAN FRANCISCO BAY?
IS A LOT OF COMPLAINTS ABOUT NOT ENOUGH HOUSING AND OTHER
STUFF BUT EXPANDING SAN FRANCISCO BAY I'M NOT SURE WHAT
ALL PROFESSIONAL LEVELS YOU GUYS DEAL WITH THIS
RECONSTRUCTIONS RECONSTRUCTION IN SAN FRANCISCO BUT I JUST
WANT TO MAKE A FEW SUGGESTIONS AND IDEAS FOR SAN FRANCISCO.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. IF I COULD RECOMMEND THAT YOU
CHECK OUT THE PORT COMMISSION THEY ARE WORKING ON EXACTLY
BUILDING A SEAWALL. OKAY.
WELCOME REVEREND BROWN. MR. PRESIDENT, MADAM CLERK,
MEMBERS OF THIS ORGANIZED BODY, THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS IS OF
THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAINT FRANCIS.
OBVIOUSLY I SAT AND LISTENED FOR MY GRANDMOTHER SAID GOD
GAVE US TWO EYES TO SEE AND TWO YEARS TO HEAR AND THE MORE WE
LOOK AND LISTEN UNLESS WE SPEAK THE BETTER WE SHALL ALL BE HERE
AND I RISE AT THE AGE OF 80 AND VIVE SAY I SAT OR YOU SAT
YOU SIT RATHER RIGHT NOW AND I MADE EVERY EFFORT TO DO THE
RIGHT THING FOR THE SALMON BALLROOM THE COMMON GOOD AND NO
ONE I FELT SHOULD MONOPOLIZE GOODNESS AND ALSO ANOTHER
MATTER I WOULD LIKE TO CALL TO YOUR ATTENTION OUR STAR ROSE
SAID AND HIS POLITICS DURING THE FIRST CENTURY SEE THAT THE
BLACK MAN ARE THE ETHIOPIAN BOY INFERIOR BECAUSE OUR SKIN WAS
DARK AND THAT WE WOULD NEVER BE CAPABLE OF SELF-GOVERNANCE
AND THAT WE WOULD ALWAYS HAVE TO HAVE A WHITE PERSON OVER US
. >> MR. PRESIDENT, MEMBERS OF
BOARD LET US NOT GIVE CREDENCE AND TRUTH TO THAT FOR THE BLACK
COMMUNITY IN SAN FRANCISCO FEELS THAT WHAT'S HAPPENING
AROUND THE ISSUE OF L.A. HILL HUTS CENTER IS AN OBVIOUS
SITUATION WHERE SOMEONE SEEKS TO MAKE DECISIONS FOR.
>> PLEASE HEAR ME. THE BLACK COMMUNITY I'M
STANDING HERE REPRESENTING THE BLACK FAITH COMMUNITY, THE
BLACK CHURCH WHICH IS THE BASE THE FOUNDATION OF OUR COMMUNITY
. THE SOCIOLOGISTS OF ALL SAID
AND THE HISTORIANS HAVE SAID IT BUT THE DECISION THAT WAS MADE
AROUND LITTLE HUTCH NOT ONE BLACK FAITH COMMUNITY WAS
CONSULTED. THAT'S BAD POLITICKING THAT
DENIES A PERSON'S ENFRANCHISED ENFRANCHISEMENT.
>> SO WE ARE SAYING AS A COMMUNITY THE CIVIL RIGHTS
COMMUNITY I'M REPRESENTING ACP TOO AND THE FAITH COMMUNITY
BETHLEHEM CHURCH, THIRD BAPTIST FIRST A.M.E. ZION CORNERSTONE
THAT I CAN'T CALL ALL OF THEM BUT WE ARE UNITED AND WE ARE
SAYING PLEASE, PLEASE PRETTY PLEASE DON'T INSULT US AGAIN BY
MAKING DECISIONS FOR THE BLACK COMMUNITY.
>> OLDER APPLAUSE PLEASE. SO I TRUST THAT YOU ALL WILL
SEE ALSO THAT WE HAVE WISDOM. WE KNOW HOW TO BE STATES
PERSONS. >> BUT LEADERSHIP SOMEWHERE
IN THE BODY POLITIC AND FROM BOOKER T HAVE SAID NO TO REASON
AND COMMON SENSE. WHEN WE WAS ADVANCED IDEA THAT
WE WOULD HAVE AT THAT CENTER JOINT LEADERSHIP SO THAT WE
WOULD COME FROM UNDER THAT PAIN ANGUISH AND AGONY OF A CLOUD
THAT HAS BEEN OVER THE COMMUNITY.
SO MEMBERS OF THE BOARD PLEASE LISTEN PLEASE WORK WITH US
AND DON'T DISMEMBER US. >> THAT'S WHAT WAS DONE DURING
THE DAYS OF LYNCHINGS OF THE SOUTH AFTER THEY STRONG US UP.
>> WHAT DID THEY DO? >> THEY CUT OFF OUR FINGERS
AND OUR TOES. >> CHECK IT OUT ON THE
INTERNET. IT'S THE TRUTH.
AND WHAT WE DO WHEN WE PLAY DIVISIVE POLITICS WE DISMEMBER
A COMMUNITY. >> SO PLEASE LISTEN.
THANK YOU. AND NOT ACT ON WHAT YOU ARE
THINKING OF DOING. THE COMMUNITY NEEDS TO BE
RESPECTED. >> THANK YOU.
AND I NOW PRESENT TO YOU A YOUNG MAN FROM THE COMMUNITY
THAT YOU SHOULD HEAR AND SEE. >> THE NEW DIRECTOR OF KOMEN
ADVOCATES COMING UP HERE. >> THANK YOU.
WELL, I'M A FATHER AND I WILL JUST MACHARIA I WILL MAKE A
NOTE THAT PURSUANT TO THE BOARD RULES THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS
ALLOWED REVEREND BROWN PRIVILEGE OF THE FLOOR AS HE IS
A FORMER MEMBER OF THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
BUT GENERALLY THERE ARE WE SET THE TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES.
WELCOME, SIR. >> IF YOU'RE THE LAST SPEAKER,
PLEASE. >> HE BRINGS GREAT CREDENTIALS
. >> HOW ARE WE FEELING?
SCALE. HELLO BOARD.
HELLO, SAN FRANCISCO. >> I JUST WANT TO SAY STEPHEN,
HOW ARE YOU? GOOD TO SEE YOU AGAIN.
I'M IT'S AN HONOR TO BE HERE TO BE A SMALL COG IN A MIGHTY
CLOCK THAT MAKES UP THE ECOSYSTEM OF SAN FRANCISCO.
ALTHOUGH I'M NOT BORN HERE AND I CONSIDER THIS MY MY HOME.
I WOULD SAY THAT COLEMAN HAVING 52 YEARS OF LEGACY AND SUCCESS
IS WILLING AND READY TO WORK NOT ONLY AS A PREVENTATIVE ARM
OF THE ECOSYSTEM BUT ALSO AS AN ACCOUNTABILITY ARM.
SO I ASKED REVEREND BROWN TO ALLOW ME TO COME HERE SIMPLY TO
SAY CONSIDER US YOUR PARTNER. >> AS HE WAS SAYING, THE BLACK
COMMUNITY AS ANY OTHER COMMUNITY HAS A VOICE.
IT HAS A MIND AND IT HAS AUTONOMY.
>> WHENEVER YOU'RE MAKING DECISIONS I THINK IT IS
PERTINENT THAT YOU CONSIDER THOSE WHO ARE MOST AFFECTED BY
THE DECISIONS THAT YOU ARE MAKING.
AGAIN, IT'S AN HONOR TO BE HERE AND HAVE A GREAT DAY.
>> GOD BLESS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT. ARE THERE OTHER MEMBERS OF THE
PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? MR. PRESIDENT, PUBLIC COMMENT
IS NOW CLOSED. MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL THE
FOR ADOPTION OF THAT COMMITTEE REFERENCE AGENDA ITEMS 29
THROUGH 31 ITEMS 29 THROUGH 31 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE. A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED
FOR ADOPTION OF A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TODAY.
ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO
GO TO COMMITTEE. >> SUPERVISOR WALTON.
THANK YOU. JUST SENDING ITEM 32 COMMITTEE
SUPERVISOR DORSEY. >> I'D LIKE TO 730 JUST TO
SPEAK TO IT IF IT'S POSSIBLE. >> YEAH.
MR. PRESIDENT, WHEN A MEMBER INDICATES AN ITEM IT CAN BE
SENT TO COMMITTEE JUST AS SUCH AND YOU CAN INDICATE WHICH
COMMITTEE IT'S GOING TO GO TO. WE'D WE WOULD RECOMMEND SAYS
YEAH I MEAN IT WOULD GET A PIECE PERFECT.
>> BUT I HAVE A MEMBER IN THE QUEUE BECAUSE HE CAN SAY
WHATEVER HE WANTS. >> YEAH IT'S A SINGLE MEMBER'S
PRIVILEGE THERE'S NO DEBATE ON. BUT IS.
>> BUT IF THERE'S AND THAT'S WHY IT'S GOING TO COMMITTEE IT
IS CERTAINLY GOING TO COMMITTEE.
I MEAN THERE'S NOT A QUESTION OF WHETHER IT'S GOING TO CREDIT
COMMITTEE THE QUESTION IS I HAVE A MEMBER IN THE QUEUE WHO
WANTS TO SPEAK ABOUT THEY'RE NOT ALLOWED TO SPEAK AFTER THAT
MEMBER TOO. >> IF WE'RE GOING TO DO THAT I
MEAN SURE. >> OH, SURE.
OKAY. I MEAN THIS IS SORT OF A BOARD
RULE QUESTION. >> I'M NOT SURE WHAT THE ANSWER
HERE IS. I THINK IF YOU JUST SEE SURE.
>> I JUST WANTED TO SAY ALTHOUGH IF THIS IS GOING TO BE
GOING TO A COMMITTEE HEARING AS IS ANY MEMBER'S RIGHT, I DID
WANT TO TAKE THE OPPORTUNITY TO EXPLAIN WHY I'VE BEEN SUCH A
STRONG PROPONENT OF THE AUTOMATED SPEED ENFORCEMENT
PROGRAM DURING MY TIME ON THE BOARD.
THIS PROGRAM TOOK SEVERAL TRIES IN THE CALIFORNIA LEGISLATURE
AND I'M GRATEFUL FOR THE LEADERSHIP FORMER ASSEMBLY
MEMBER LAURA FRIEDMAN PROVIDED AND FINALLY GETTING THIS BILL
ACROSS THE FINISH LINE. I ALSO WANT TO RECOGNIZE THE
LEADERSHIP OF OUR CITY ATTORNEY DAVID CHIU WHO DURING HIS TIME
IN THE STATE LEGISLATURE SPONSORED THIS LAW SEVERAL
TIMES BACK IN 2023 I JOINED ADVOCATES FROM WALK US F
AND FAMILIES FOR SAFE STREETS FOR AN ADVOCACY DAY IN IN
SACRAMENTO. IT WAS DEEPLY MOVING TO SEE HOW
TRAFFIC VIOLENCE CAN AFFECT PEOPLE'S LIVES AND HOW SOME
FAMILY MEMBERS AND LOVED ONES FIND PURPOSE IN ADVOCATING FOR
TRAFFIC SAFETY LIKE SPEED ENFORCEMENT CAMERAS TO ENSURE
THAT NO MORE FAMILIES FACE THE TRAGEDIES THAT THEY DID.
SAN FRANCISCO MOVED QUICKLY TO IMPLEMENT THE BILL AND TO
MAXIMIZE THE PROGRAM TO THE FULLEST EXTENT OF THE LAW.
THIS BOARD TOOK ACTION TO ALLOW DESIGN BUILD A CONTRACT TO
ALLOW FOR SMOOTH IMPLEMENTATION.
LAST WEEK S.F. MTA RELEASED ITS DATA ON THE FIRST FULL YEAR OF
THE PROGRAM AND THE RESULTS SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES.
SPEED HAS DROPPED AN AVERAGE OF 80% AT 33 LOCATIONS IN THE
PROGRAM MANY OF THEM IN MY DISTRICT.
DISTRICT SIX HAS MANY DANGEROUS ARTERIALS WHERE DRIVERS BEHAVE
AS IF THEY ARE ON A HIGHWAY WHEN IN REALITY THEY'RE IN THE
MIDDLE OF A DENSE URBAN NEIGHBORHOOD.
THE STREETS WITH CAMERA DO FEEL SAFER AND WE'VE SEEN INCREDIBLE
PROGRESS. THIS PROGRAM IS PROVING WHY WE
SHOULD HAVE MORE OF THIS LIFE SAVING TECHNOLOGY.
THIS RESOLUTION WOULD RECOGNIZE THE PROGRAM'S SUCCESS AND PUT
SAN FRANCISCO ON RECORD IN SAYING THAT WE SUPPORT IT,
THAT WE BELIEVE THE STATE LEGISLATURE SHOULD STRENGTHEN
IT. I LOOK FORWARD TO WORKING WITH
OUR LOCAL ADVOCATES AND OUR STATE DELEGATION TO SEE SLOWER
CARS AND SAFER STREETS. I WANT TO THANK WALK S.F. FOR
THEIR UNRELENTING ADVOCACY ON THIS ISSUE.
FOR THE REPRESENTATIVES WHO SPOKE TO IT AND TO MTA FOR
THEIR DILIGENT WORK TO IMPLEMENT AND RUN THE PROGRAM.
I APPRECIATE THE SPORT'S PRIOR SUPPORT FOR THE RESOLUTIONS TO
SUPPORT THE STATE LAW. HB 645 AS WELL AS THE TRAILING
LEGISLATION NEEDED TO IMPLEMENT IT PROMPTLY.
AND I HOPE YOU'LL JOIN ME IN SUPPORTING THE RESOLUTION
WHEN IT COMES BACK FROM COMMITTEE.
>> SUPERVISOR WONG THANK YOU PRESIDENT MADELINE.
ANYTHING WITH SURVEILLANCE INVOLVED IN IT?
I AM GOING TO SEND IT TO COMMITTEE FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT
COMMITTEE REFERENCE MAKES A BLANKET STATEMENT THAT WE'RE
ALL IN AGREEMENT WITH EVERYTHING AND THAT'S NOT
ALWAYS THE CASE. >> THAT'S WHY THIS IS GETTING
SENT TO COMMITTEE AND WE SEND IT TO COMMITTEE SO WE DON'T
HAVE A DEBATE ON IT RIGHT HERE BECAUSE IT'S FOR ADOPTION
WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE. SO FOR US TO BE GOING BACK
AND FORTH IS INAPPROPRIATE. THERE ARE RULES THAT WE NEED TO
GO BY AT THIS BOARD EVEN OUT OF RESPECT FOR OUR COLLEAGUES.
>> SO WE NEED TO REMEMBER THAT MR. PRESIDENT, BECAUSE WE
SHOULDN'T BE GOING BACK AND FORTH OVER SOMETHING THAT
GOT SENT TO COMMITTEE. >> THAT'S WHAT COMMITTEE IS
FOR. >> I BELIEVE SUPERVISOR WALTON
IS CORRECT AND THAT I AM IN ERROR.
>> I DON'T SEE ANYBODY ELSE. THANK YOU.
MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON ITEMS 29
AND 31. 931 ON ITEMS 20 NINE AND 31.
>> SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG I. SUPERVISOR CHAN CHEN I.
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN I. SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
SUPERVISOR MAHMUD MAHMUD I. SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN I.
WOMEN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR.
I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL. I AND SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
EITHER ATTORNEYS. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ARE ADOPTED. AND THEN MADAM CLERK DO WE.
>> DO YOU HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE? DO WE HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE
AGENDA ITEMS? THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT.
>> ALL RIGHT. COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE
IN MEMORIAM? TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUAL.
ON BEHALF OF THE ENTIRE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
ON THE MOTION MADE BY PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR THE LATE MR.
LAWRENCE MICHAEL STEPHANIE. >> AND I BELIEVE THAT BRINGS US
TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA. MADAM CLERK.
>> DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK WE ARE ADJOURNED